<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The tragedies of tyrantes Exercised vpon the church of God, from the birth of Christ vnto this present yeere. 1572. Containing the causes of them, and the iust vengeance of God vpon the authours. Also some notable comfortes and exhortations to pacience. Written by Henrie Bullinger, and now Englished.</title>
            <title>Von der schweren, langwirigen Verfolgung der heiligen Christlichen Kirchen. English</title>
            <author>Bullinger, Heinrich, 1504-1575.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1575</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 240 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 100 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B11843</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 4078</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S106917</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99842624</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99842624</idno>
            <idno type="VID">176431</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B11843)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 176431)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 185:01)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The tragedies of tyrantes Exercised vpon the church of God, from the birth of Christ vnto this present yeere. 1572. Containing the causes of them, and the iust vengeance of God vpon the authours. Also some notable comfortes and exhortations to pacience. Written by Henrie Bullinger, and now Englished.</title>
                  <title>Von der schweren, langwirigen Verfolgung der heiligen Christlichen Kirchen. English</title>
                  <author>Bullinger, Heinrich, 1504-1575.</author>
                  <author>Twyne, Thomas, 1543-1613.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 42, [2] leaves   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By William How, for Abraham Veale, dwelling in Paules Churchyard at the signe of the Lamb,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1575.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Translator's dedication signed: Tho. Tvvinus.</note>
                  <note>A translation of the Latin translation by Josias Simmler of: Von der schweren, langwirigen Verfolgung der heiligen Christlichen Kirchen.</note>
                  <note>With two final contents leaves.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: Tragedies of tirants.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the University of Chicago. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Persecution --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:176431:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:176431:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:176431:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:176431:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:176431:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:176431:3"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Of the fyrſt Tragicall</hi> Acte or perſecution after the <hi>birth of Chriſt, in which Herod</hi> ſurnamed the great, ſlew the young and innocent Children. <hi>Chapter. i.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter the perſecutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of the</hi> faithfull in the auncient ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Church, hereafter I will declare the perſecutions of the chriſtian Church, which began im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly after the byrth of Chriſte, in the reigne of <hi>Auguſtus</hi> the Emperour.</p>
            <p>When Chriſte in great pouertie was borne in a certen ſtable, ther came wiſe <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Herode</hi> the great firſte perſecuted our ſauiour</note> men from the Eaſt vnto <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring the birth of the late borne king. With this tidings <hi>Herod</hi> (whom they call the greate, and <hi>Aſcalonite</hi>) beinge merueilous affraied, for he doubted leſt the new borne king ſhoulde driue him out of the kingdome of <hi>Iudea,</hi> whiche then he poſſeſſed at pleaſure &amp; good will of the <hi>Romanes:</hi> he determined to ſlay this newe and latelye borne Kinge
<pb facs="tcp:176431:4"/> whilſt as yet hée lay in his ſwath clothes. And beinge ignorant wl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> was the lately borne kinge, yet ki<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>inge that hée was borne at <hi>Bethe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> beecauſe hée would bee ſure not to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> him: cauſed all the infantes of <hi>Be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lem</hi> and the places néere about, ſut<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> were two monethes ould or young bée ſlayne by his officers, and ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ours. Amongſt which his officers ſouldiours, this moſte cruell T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> fownd ſome, that were not a frai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> commit this ſtraunge tragedie, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ell murther. For the murderers, vngodly rakehelles, the ſeruantes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> butcherly kinge, departinge vnto <note place="margin">A cruell ſlaughter.</note> 
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>thelem,</hi> fulfilled his commaundm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> killinge all the younge children o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>thelem</hi> and the borders about, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> doubtleſſe the numbre was not ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> For, which is horrible to heare, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>trarie to the nature of mankinde, ſpared not ſomuch as the tendre in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in their cloutes, but haled them their mothers breſtes: wherby aroſe a great and miſerable cla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſchritches and outcries of them, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:176431:4"/> moſt deare pledges and children were pluckt away by moſt vniuſte Tyranie and ſo cruelly and vnkindly murthered. Mathew the <hi>Euangeliſt</hi> maketh menci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this ſorow and heuines, by whom <note place="margin">Math. 2.</note> this ſtorie is diligently writen, and for the better ſettinge foorth to the eie the greatnes of this miſerie and calamitie, the woordes of <hi>Ieremie</hi> are by him alea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged who writeth thus: <hi>A voice was heard in Rhama, lamentation, weep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge, and mutch mourninge, Rachell weepinge for her children, and would receaue no comfort becauſe they were not.</hi> In which woordes this is alſo to be noted, how perſecution doth not only touch and appertayne vnto thoſe that are tormented or ſlayne, but vnto thoſe alſo, who, although they ſuffre not the ſame thinges: yet do they loue them, and are ioyned vnto them that ſuffer, ſo that by the paines and ſuffryng of their frendes they ſuſtayne great gréefe of mynde, and thereby themſelues do ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, and are partakers of perſecution.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Herod</hi> mooued this perſecution not ſo mutch for the infantes to ſlaye them,
<pb facs="tcp:176431:5"/> but for our Lorde Jeſus Chriſte to ſéeke him, finde him, and kill him.</p>
            <p>Wherefore theſe innocent Infantes were ſlayne for Chriſtes ſake, and they whoſe Children they were ſuſtayned this great ſorrowe and heaueneſſe for Chriſts ſake, although at that time they vnderſtoode not the miſteries of God.</p>
            <p>And therefore verie well theſe glytleſſe children, with their parentes are num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred among them whiche haue ſuffered perſecution for Chriſtes ſake. Neither is it to bée doubted, but theſe children by the force and efficacye of the frée grace and promiſe of God, were in the league and therfore had receyued Cyrcumcy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, the ſigne and token of the league, and were the ſunnes of God, and then alſo were endued with the crowne of martyrdome for Chriſtes cauſe. <note place="margin">Curious queſtions touching theſe Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Since therefore God of his mercye, and goodneſſe hath ſo gloryouſlye delte with theſe Children, let theſe curious queſtioners ceaſe here to inquire, what God did meane, &amp; why he ſuffred theſe ſéelly and giltleſſe babes to be ſlayne for Chriſtes ſake? Why he deliuered not
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:176431:5"/> them alſo as he dyd Chriſte, whome he conuaied by flight into <hi>Aegipt?</hi> why he ſuffred the cruell Tyrant to commit ſo foule a murther? doth anie ſutch vnac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed crueltie &amp; ſauagenes delight God? Likely enough it is, that at that time when theſe thinges were doone, troubleſome and carnall men vttered foorth mutch ſutch like talke. But the Godly, and men of ſownde iudgement, do quite reiect ſutch thoughtes and que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions, nether do they ſpeake againſt the gouerment of God why hée premitteth this or that, but with all their hart they ſay with Dauid: <hi>The Lorde is iuſt in all his wayes, and holly in all his wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes.</hi> Although the innocent children were depriued of this preſent life, yet were they rewarded with euerlaſtinge lyfe, and endued with vnſpeakeable glorie and honour. As for the mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninge and ſorowe of the parentes, God could requite that, ſundrie waies.</p>
            <p>And God, likewiſe, who is diſpleaſed with crueltie, who alſo doth no euell, nether ſuffreth it to bée doone vnpuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, vſeth euell déedes, wrath, and
<pb facs="tcp:176431:6"/> ſauage crueltie of his enemies vnto the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modity of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> faithful, their deedes ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>while being naught, and nothyng ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the better. Poiſon is euil by his own nature, but by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſkil of the Phiſitions y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which is naught by nature is applied in medecines vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> commoditie of men. So ſaid <hi>Ioſeph</hi> to his brethren that thei imagined miſchief againſt him, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thei ſold him into <hi>Egipt,</hi> howbeit god turnd it to good, ſo likewiſe doth God in perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutions. For in this firſt perſecution, wée béeholde euidently, as it were in a glaſſe, what is the ſubſtance &amp; ſtate of al other perſecutions. For although this perſecution were very cruel &amp; vnkind: notwithſtanding it tended vnto the ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation &amp; glory of all thoſe whom it tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched. And likewiſe al other perſecutions of the faithful, although they be ſharp &amp; cruell, yet are they profitable &amp; honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vnto thoſe that ſuffer them. And like as the wiſe wil not much diſpute in this place, why god ſuffred thoſe children to be ſlaine: ſo are y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faithful of a moderate and quiet mind in perſecutions, nether do they accuſe god demaunding why he doth this or y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> for wicked men, ſuffring
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:176431:6"/> the godly &amp; innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to be oppreſſed. For they know, &amp; beleue, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gods gouerment is in al things good &amp; iuſt, &amp; without all reprehention. And like as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> giltleſſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts were killed for chriſtes ſake and amongſt them Chriſt was ſought to be ſlayne: ſo in al perſecutions y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faithful a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> murdered for Chriſts ſake, &amp; Chriſt is he whom y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> perſecutours ſéek and ſtudy to make away. And like as chriſte then was nether found, nor ſlain, but eſcaped ſo al perſecutions may ſlay y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> godly, but they are neuer able to extinguiſh chriſt. But as <hi>Herod,</hi> contrary to his hope &amp; ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pectation, notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding this murther could not be careles nor quiet in mind: ſo likewiſe, al perſecutors, although thei kil neuer ſo many yet ar thei not at reſt but alwaies remaining in feare, &amp; care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes. Ambition and deſire to rule only enforced <hi>Herod</hi> to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit theſe horrible ſlaughters: al other perſecutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s likwiſe <note place="margin">The cauſe of this per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution.</note> haue ſprong foorth from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> like diſeaſe &amp; euill affection. For in times paſt what ſtirs ambitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; deſire to rule, haue mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kigdoms of <hi>Iuda</hi> &amp; <hi>Iſrael</hi> it mai be known by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tyrannical déeds of <hi>Saul Abner, Iereboam, Athalia,</hi> &amp; ſuch lyke.
<pb facs="tcp:176431:7"/> And in our age manie of the clergie, and eccleſiaſticall ordre, hauinge obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned great honours: do feare leaſt their glory, pompe, ritches, pleaſures, prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes and honours ſhould decay, if the Goſpell were fréely preached. Sutche therfore for their kingdome, and pleaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res: with <hi>Herod,</hi> oppoſe themſelues a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Chriſte and his woord, and are not ſtroken with horrour in eggynge foorth vnto, or executinge a cruell déede, ſo that themſelues may lurke ſafe and quiet in their neaſtes. To conclude, like as this gréeuous and cruell perſecution of Chriſte, béegan immediatly after his incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation by ſlaughter of the innocent babes: ſo is there nothing that the churche of Chriſte muſt looke for vntill the laſt iudgment, but perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="chapter">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:176431:7"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Of the ſecond Tragical</hi> Acte or perſecution, wherein <hi>Iohn the Baptiſt was beheaded,</hi> Jeſus Chriſt the Sunne of God crucified, and his Diſciples diſperſed. <hi>Chapter. ii.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He ſecond perſecution began</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi> firſte prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher of the Goſpell.</note> at one time, with the preaching of the Goſpell, &amp; <hi>Iohn</hi> the <hi>Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſte</hi> firſte preached the Goſpell, as S. <hi>Marke</hi> witneſſeth writting: how that the Goſpell of Jeſus Chriſte the Sun of God, began ſo as it was foretold by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prophets, namely by the forerunner of of Chriſt, who prepared his waies, and made the mindes of men apt and ready to receaue Chriſte. Whiche <hi>Iohn</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt,</hi> pointed vnto Chriſt, as it were <note place="margin">What <hi>Iohn</hi> preached.</note> with his finger, teſtefinge that he was the Lambe of God, that ſhoulde take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the ſinnes of the world. The ſame exhorted men to beléeue in Chriſte, and ſent his diſciples from him to Chriſte, as vnto him in whome dwelled al ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,
<pb facs="tcp:176431:8"/> and through whom only the way was open vnto euerlaſtinge life: affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minge that hée was the verie Sunne of God, into whoſe hande the father committed all thinges, and whoſoeuer béeléeued in him ſhould haue euerlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge life, and whoſo béeleeued not, vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon him remained the wrath of God. Therewith alſo he ſharply rebuked the vices of men, exhortinge all to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, pronouncinge vnto the impeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent and vnbéeléeuinge, the wrath of God and deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to hang ouer them. Theſe are me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tioned by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>Euangeliſtes Mathew. 3. chap. Iohn. 1.</hi> and. <hi>3. chap.</hi> and <hi>Luke. 3. chapter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For this doctrines ſake, when as manie hated John and his diſciples, and ſpecially the high byſhoppes and prie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes, who by meſſengers ſent vnto him required an accoumpt of his doctrine, endeuoringe to ſtoppe, and hindre him from that function. Afterwarde, when he had rebuked <hi>Herode</hi> called <hi>Antipas</hi> of inceſt, which was ſun to <hi>Herod</hi> ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named the great, that ſlew the children (for the ſame <hi>Antipas</hi> had taken away <note place="margin">Iohn. 1.</note>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:176431:8"/> his owne brother <hi>Philippes</hi> wife and his daughter, and kept her openly for his owne wife) when, as I ſay, hée had preached againſt that wicked déede mutch blaminge the filthines of the fact was by the ſayd <hi>Herode</hi> apprehended, and caſt into priſon. Then on a time, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> taken.</note> when <hi>Herod</hi> had made a ſolemne feaſt for his nobles and courtiars: amonge his greate and manie cuppes beinge o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſéene and merie with wine, promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed large rewardes vnto <hi>Herodiadas</hi> the daughter, a ſtrumpet, béecauſe ſhée had daunced in his preſence, where ſhée beinge inſtructed by the ould harlot her mother, required the head of John the Baptiſt. <hi>Herod</hi> although hée knew<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> John to bée a godly and holy man, yet ſending the executioner: commaunded the innocent man without iudgment, his cauſe beinge vnhearde, ſhamefully, and through tyranicall luſt to bée ſlayn in the priſon. The daughter preſented the Head of John to the inceſtuous har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lot <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> behea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</note> her mother, in the feaſt, and euen as ſhée was ſitting at the table. Which cruell déede, what greife and ſorow it
<pb facs="tcp:176431:9"/> brought to Johns diſciples, and al other godly men: euerie faithfull man maye eaſely repute with himſelf. Wherfore this perſecution by <hi>Herode</hi> committed, not only touched <hi>Iohn:</hi> but was gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous alſo to the reſt of the faithful.</p>
            <p>Doublteſſe ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ch carnall reaſons as theſe are, perplexed the mindes of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie <note place="margin">Sundry<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e opinions of this dede.</note> that time, why God ſuffred that man to be afflicted that was ſo dear vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Lorde, and greater then whome there was none borne of a woman? Why permitted hée him by inceſtuous perſons ſo miſerablye to bée ſlayne in priſon, and they the meane time drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in riotinge, drounkennes, and dauncinge? why hée ſuffred that holye head, diſdainfully to be touched and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſed by the handes of a filthie harlot? Theſe thinges are ſtraunge in the ſight of men, and the fact it ſelf is horrible, yet no wyſe man ought to accuſe God in permittinge the ſame, which doth all thinge in iudgment, and iuſtice yea, if hée chaunce at theſe dayes to ſée ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous and godly men, miſerably ſlayne by the vngodly and wicked, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reprochefully
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:176431:9"/> vſed, thus hée reaſoneth with himſelf: if God could beehold it, that ſo holy a man, Gods freende, the firſt miniſter of the Goſpell, ſhould ſo diſpightfully bée murthered in priſon, and his head alſo reprochfully handled: wée ought leſſe to merueyle if now like wiſe hée ſuffre the like to béefall to his fréences, who are not yet in ſo great eſtimation, and dignitie as John was.</p>
            <p>But like as Johns cauſe was not therfore vniuſte, and <hi>Herodes</hi> iuſte, in that hee preuailed, and oppreſſed, and ſlew John: in our age likewiſe their doctrine and faith which abide perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and are wofully ſlayn for Chriſt and his woordes ſake, is not therfore the woorſe, nether the faith of the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecucions and murthers for that cauſe the better.</p>
            <p>Semblably, as there was none other <note place="margin">Cauſes of <hi>Herods</hi> par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution.</note> cauſe that mooued <hi>Herod</hi> to this perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution and greeuous ſlaughter, then that hée would not bée rebuked in his wickednes, neither offend his bouſinge mates and inceſtuous harlot: ſo, manie perſecutions are raiſed by thoſe that
<pb facs="tcp:176431:10"/> will not bée reproued for Idolatrie for their ſins and wickedneſſe, perſecuting the innocent, that they may pleaſe wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked men, which prouoke them vnto it.</p>
            <p>In the ſame age, after John the bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt, <note place="margin">Chriſtes doctrine.</note> vnder <hi>Tyberius</hi> the Emperour, our lorde Jeſus Chriſt béegan to prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che the goſpel, and to pronounce remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of ſinnes, and life euerlaſtynge through faith in him, and alſo béegan ſharply to withſtande, and ſpeake a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gainſt the falſe doctrin of the Teachers namely of the Phariſes, Scribes, and preiſtes ſeuerely accuſinge their hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie, couetouſnes, and other crimes, warnings them alſo of the wrath of God which hunge ouer them, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortinge moreouer all men to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. Hée declared this doctrine, and deuine power, by ſundrie wounders and miracles, wherby it is ſet clere, and vndoubted, and as a man ſhould ſay ſhewed with handes, that hée was the ſunne of the liuinge God, the lorde that had power ouer ſatan, ſinne, death and hell.</p>
            <p>But the high biſhops thoſe Teachers
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:176431:10"/> or religious men as they call them, which alonely ruled the roſte, and were of greateſt auctoritie in the counſell of the Jewes, the prieſtes likewiſe, and Leuits, acknowledged not Jeſus, as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>déede he was, to be the true Meſſias: but they maliced him, and laid waite to take away his life. And at ſomtimes they called him Samaritane, ſomtime they ſaid hée was poſſeſſed with a diuell railinge, and reprochinge his doctrine, which they could in no wiſe abide, bée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it was quighte contrarie vnto theirs.</p>
            <p>For they ſpake litle or nothinge of <note place="margin">Phariſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal doctrine.</note> faith, but of woorkes only, how wée were iuſtified by the lawe or obſeruing the law, but ſpecially by ſacrifice: like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe they taught litle of Charitie, but applied all to their auarice makinge of the lordes houſe a verie ſhoppe of Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandize. For in the temple were ſhéep and Dxen, and doues to bée ſold, for ſutch as offred ſacrifice, and for their farther gaine they had ſet vp tables for vſerie, and exchange. But Chriſte ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king a ſcourge of ſmall cordes: draue
<pb facs="tcp:176431:11"/> them all out of the temple, as well the ſhéepe oxen, and doues as thoſe that ſold them, as alſo the bankers, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changers, and all that ſold religion for monie.</p>
            <p>Wherfore, for this cauſe only they <note place="margin">Chriſtes perſecution.</note> dayly perſecuted Chriſte, goinge about to ſtone him or kill him, and hée often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times conuaid himſelf away, flying out of <hi>Iudea</hi> in to <hi>Galile,</hi> and ſuſtained pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently ſundrie afflictions, reproches, and traueyles. And laſt of all, hée was béetraid, and ſold by one of his owne diſciples, apprehended, and brought in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the eccleſiaſticall iudgment of the prie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes, and by <hi>Pontius Pilate,</hi> the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane</hi> Lieutenant, condemned to the death of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> croſſe, for no other cauſe, but for that, as indéede he was, hée affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med himſelfe to bée the verie ſunne of the liuinge God, the trew Meſſias or Chriſte, the only, and eternall ſauiour of al the world. But before that he was brought vnto the Lieutenant: y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts and miniſters of the prieſts ſhamefully mocked, &amp; miſuſed him in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> high biſhops hal: they blindfolded him, &amp; ſpet in his
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:176431:11"/> face, buffeted him, reprochfully and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainfully intreating his diuine wiſdom <note place="margin">Accuſation aginſt chriſt</note> and maieſtie. In the morning, when they brought him before the lieutenant they falſly accuſed him to bee a ſeductor of the people, a ſeditious fellow, &amp; well worthye to be hanged on the Croſſe.</p>
            <p>But <hi>Pilate,</hi> when he had diligently ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amined all the matter, vnderſtanding the cauſe: ſundrye times pronounced that hee was not guiltie, and that hee could not condemne him by lawe, and notwithſtanding that hee was inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, yet was he handled diſpightfullye. For he was led vnto <hi>Herod,</hi> &amp; by him contemptuouſly abuſed, flouted of his courtiars and galantes, with all ſcorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full demeanure. He was compared vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Barrabas,</hi> the moſt notorious théefe, <note place="margin">His paſſion</note> and murtherer of that age, whom the Jewes preferred before Chriſt, ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinge that hée was woorſe then that wicked villayn, whome all the worlde hated. Hée was ſcurged alſo, and crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with a crowne of wreathed thorns, and being in this ſorte miſerably hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and tormented: was brought foorth
<pb facs="tcp:176431:12"/> into the ſight of the vnthankfull people. But for al this, there was no grace nor pardon to bée found, ſpecially amonge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preiſtes, egginge the Lieutenant to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne the innocent, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hée ſhoulde permit them to leade him to execution, &amp; to crucifie him béetwen two théeues. And when hée was in moſte gréeuous paines, and the very panges of death: he was moſte outragiouſly intreated with blaſphemous frumps, ſcornes, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>procheful vſages. For the préeſtes with many other mo walking before y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> croſſe vttred foorth ſundrie horrible and grée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous woords againſt him, which are by <hi>S. Mathe</hi> diligently ſet downe in wri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tinge. Amongſt which moſt gréeuous temptations and iniuries, in the midſt of theſe ſorowes, Chriſte yéelded vp the ghoſt vpon the croſſe.</p>
            <p>Whilſt Chriſte ſuffred theſe thinges his diſciples were miſerably diſperſed, and all the faythfull conceaued woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull and incredible ſorowe for the paſſion, and death of Chriſte. Manie fearfully doubted, leaſt at that time the doctrine of the Goſpell were wholy ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſhed.
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:176431:12"/> So that this perſecution which was againſt chriſte: both touched and troubled the whole Church, and all the faithfull. And although the enemies of Chriſt hoped that they had gotten the conqueſt, and deſtroyd the doctrine of the Goſpell: notwithſtandynge, their victorie made not the phariſaicall doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine one iote the better, nor y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> doctrine of the Goſpell: the woorſer. For it is no good conſequent: the Phariſes put Chriſte to death, wherefore, their doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine is true, and Chriſtes falſe.</p>
            <p>The cauſe which moued the Phariſes, and al other enemies of Chriſt to perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute him: ſurely was none other, then y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> they were deſierous to retaine their owne erronious doctrine, &amp; oppreſſe the goſpell w<hi rend="sup">e</hi> the followers therof, wherby they might with ſecuritie enioye their raigne, luſtes, and pleaſures. And like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe in our age, many of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Papiſts do perſecute y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faithful for none other cauſe</p>
            <p>This is a comfort vnto vs, that in ſo great afliction, when the diſciples were ſcattered, &amp; Chriſt of all men forſaken: yet only <hi>Iohn</hi> amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other diſcipls
<pb facs="tcp:176431:13"/> durſt boldlye approche to the croſſe of Chriſte, and ioyne himſelf vnto Mary the vndefiled and perpetuall virgin the mother of our Lord, and <hi>Mary Magde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len Cleophas,</hi> with other moe. Heere, by their infirmitie the power of God is declared. Likewiſe <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> and <hi>Nico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demus</hi> valiently béehaued themſelues. Like as at this day alſo it falleth out, for wher as the trueth is taught to bée ſo greuouſly preſſed with perſecution, that there ſéemeth to be no man that taketh regard or care therof: then moſt times by the meaneſt ſort, and not ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome by noble and great perſonages, there bée newe and fortunate fownda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions laid, wherby the trueth is won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully increaſed. Wherfore wée muſt not in the greateſt perſecutions, caſt of our hope and comfort.</p>
            <p>Here, béefore althinges, this is to bée obſerued, that wée iudge far other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe of Chriſtes death and paſſion, then of the death and affliction of Iohn and other ſainctes, who haue ſuffred perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution for God and the truethes ſake, and with their bloude borne recorde
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:176431:13"/> to the heauenly trueth: but wée ought far more excellently to accompt of the blood and death of Chriſte. For as hée is the euerlaſtinge ſunne of God, and life vnto all thoſe that béeleue in him: ſo his blood, death, and paſſion are a clen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinge ſacrifice, and a propitiation for the ſinnes of the whole worlde. For by his death wée obtayne life, and by his blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed wée get remiſſion of ſinnes. And vnto this opinion all the doctrine of the Prophetes, and Apoſtles bear witnes, ſpecially the epiſtle of Saint <hi>Paule</hi> to the <hi>Hebrues.</hi> Wherfore our life and forgiuenes of ſinns, is repoſed in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deth and paſſion of Chriſte only, and not in the martyrdom, or paſſion of any ſainct.</p>
            <p>Since therfore, Chriſte is the head of his Church, and hée ſuffred ſo manye thinges: by his example the church alſo learneth that it muſt ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer many things, as it is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundantlye ſhewen in the writings of the Euangeliſts and Apoſtles.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:176431:14"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Of the thirde Tragical</hi> Acte or perſecutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, wherin the <hi>Apoſtles were taken and ſcurged</hi> Steeuen was ſtoned, the Church and congregation of <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> baniſhed, &amp; diſperſed. <hi>Chapter.</hi> iii.</head>
            <p>THe third perſecution of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan alitle after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Aſcencion of chriſt into heauen which is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> feaſt of <hi>Pente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coſt</hi> or <hi>Witſontyde,</hi> when the Apoſtles earneſtly preached the Goſpel, and had gathered together great and worthye Congregations vnto Chriſte.</p>
            <p>The ſame is verye dillygentlye and copiouſly deſcribed in the <hi>Actes</hi> of<note place="margin">Apoſtles Sermons.</note> the Apoſtles. The Apoſtles preached then openlye the Goſpell of Chriſte in Ieruſalem, only in the name of our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt, which was cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied and raiſed from the dead, in whom if they béeléeued, was remiſſion of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, &amp; life euerlaſting, that al men ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ought to béeléeue in him, bée bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed and ioyne in fellowſhip of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church repent and liue a godly lyfe, &amp; looke for ſaluation in none other thinge, for that
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:176431:14"/> there is none other name vnder heuen giuen to men wherein they may be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued: but the name of Ieſus Chriſte. Theſe Sermons, the Scribes and Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niours at <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> coulde not abyde, wherfore thei laide hand vpon the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, and ſhut them vp in Priſon, and brought them before the counſel, where quarreyling and chidinge with them: they forbid them to preach this Goſpell of Ieſus chriſt. But the Apoſtles frank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly profeſſing that in this behalfe by no meanes they might obey them, but that God muſt rather be obeyed then men: were neuertheles much, and gréeuouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thretned by the Magiſtrats &amp; elders.</p>
            <p>Vpon occaſion hereof, the Church be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing<note place="margin">Sorrowe, and praiers of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church.</note> ſtrock with great heauines: prayed hartely vnto God for co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinuance in the Goſpell. And when as the Apoſtles went forward conſtantly in teachyng, and Chriſte effectually woorkinge in them confirmed the trueth of their doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine with great miracles, that a great numbre of men followed them, ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the Churche was daily increaſed by thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſandes: then the magiſtrates &amp; officers
<pb facs="tcp:176431:15"/> ſetting vppon them a freſhe, caſt the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles againe into priſon, intending to put them to death. But by the interceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and meanes of <hi>Gamaliel</hi> the lawyer that was <hi>Pauls</hi> maſter: they were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyuered, but notwithſtanding whipped, and ſharply forbidden, that they ſhould not preach the Goſpel of Ieſus Chriſt. Who departing out of the counſell and Court: prayſed God that they were founde worthy to ſuffer reproch for his name.</p>
            <p>Shortly after, bleſſed <hi>Steeuen</hi> burning<note place="margin">Steuen ſtoned.</note> in the ſpirite of Chriſte, and with great zeale diſputing in the ſynagogs againſt the ſkilfull in the lawe, and ſtoutly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendyng the doctrine of Chriſte: was caſt into priſon and brought to araine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and falſly accuſed. Who although he clered hymſelfe with ſufficient, wiſe, and graue reply: yet it nothyng avayled him, for hee was condemned to die, and ſtoned to death.</p>
            <p>There followed not long after a very<note place="margin">Actes. 8.</note> vehement and ſharp perſecution of the chriſtian Church, deſcribed by <hi>Luke</hi> in the Acts of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> Apoſtles, by theſe words:
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:176431:15"/> 
               <hi>There <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>roſe about that time, a greate perſecution againſt the Church which was at Ieruſalem, and they were al diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearſed through the Regions of <hi>Iudeae</hi> and Samaria, ſauinge the Apoſtles. For Saul waſted the Churche, entring into euery mans houſe, &amp; haling forth Men and women, deliuered them to priſon.</hi> Yea, <hi>Paul</hi> himſelfe concerning this his perſecution againſt the church, ſpake thus in preſence of King <hi>Agrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pa:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Actes. 76.</note> 
               <hi>truli I was determined with my ſelf to do many things againſt the name of Ieſus of Nazareth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>VVherof partly I dyd ſomwhat at Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem, and many of the Saints I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted too Priſon, hauing receaued auctoritie of the cheef priſts, on whom alſo I gaue iudgment when they were executed. I punished the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alſo in the Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogs, compelling them to blaſphem (that is to denye the Chriſtian faith, whiche is a great blaſphemie) and ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging againſt them aboue al meaſure, I perſecuted them vnto ſtrange Cities.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, as touching the cauſe that moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued <hi>Paule,</hi> the Preiſtes, and people of
<pb facs="tcp:176431:16"/> the <hi>Iewes</hi> to perſecute the Church: was almoſt none other, but a ſiniſter &amp; vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſonable zeale &amp; affection which they bare for the lawe of <hi>Moyſes,</hi> and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies, which being lead w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> errour: they ment to retaine and preſerue, and could not therfore beléeue in chriſt, nor his Goſpel. For thei ſuppoſed that thei ſhould be iuſtified &amp; ſaued by righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law. Contrariwiſe, the goſpel teacheth vs y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> wee ſhal not be ſaued by works of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> law, but by faith in Chriſt. At this ſtone y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> 
               <hi>Iewes</hi> haue ſtumbled, &amp; fallen, &amp; periſhed, as <hi>S. Paul</hi> witneſſeth in theſe words: <hi>I proteſt for them that</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 10.</note> 
               <hi>they haue the zeale of god, but not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to knowledge. For, beyng ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of the righteouſnes before god and ſtudeinge to eſtabliſh their owne righteouſnes: they were not ſubiect vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to the righteouſnes which is allowed of god. For Chriſte is th' end of the law vnto the iuſtification of al that beleue.</hi> Likewiſe in another place: <hi>Iſraell whiche</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 9.</note> 
               <hi>enſued the Lawe of righteouſneſſe attayned not to the lawe of righteouſnes, (that is to ſay was not iuſtified) becauſe they ſought it no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> by faith, but by workes of the lawe. For they
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:176431:16"/> haue ſtumbled at the ſtumbling ſtone, as it is written: Beholde: I lay a ſtumblyngſtone, and a rock to hurt and make men fall and who ſo beleueth in him ſhal not be ashamed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In this our age likewiſe, and for the<note place="margin">Cauſe of perſecutyon at this time</note> ſame very cauſe, they aboue all other, haue moſt veheme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly, and ſharply per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted the chriſtian church, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> haue bin better men then the reſidew, and leſſe giuen to carnal affection. Thei hate the Goſpell, and perſecute the profeſſours therof, bicauſe they confeſſe &amp; erneſtly defende, that wée be iuſtified, and ſaued by faith only in Chriſt, and not by any woorkes. Suppoſing y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> by this doctrine good woorkes are taken away, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing regarded, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> men are made care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, and ſtirred vp vnto wickedneſſe, which is not to bée ſuffred in y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> churche. But there is a far other vnderſtanding in y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> queſtion of good woorkes, then thei either thinke or vtter, nether are they co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>temned, and naught ſet by, although y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> glory of Iuſtification which appertey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth vnto Chriſte only, bée not aſcribed vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For vnto faith is iuſtification aſcribed, bicauſe the ſame dependeth on Chriſt only, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> Chriſte only may haue al y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> glory, &amp; he alonly be our ſaluation
<pb facs="tcp:176431:17"/> and righteouſnes, as wée haue in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place declared more at large.</p>
            <p>But beefore wee proceede anie far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: let euerie man, I béeſeche yée, weigh with himſelf, how great and gréeuous this perſecution was againſt the firſte Church of Chriſte, and how that they which were not ſlayn, not<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>withſtandinge receaued great ſorowe, through the death, puniſhment, and torments of their brethren, that which Luke alſo hath not paſſed ouer with ſilence, wrytinge after this maner: <hi>The holly men caried foorth Steuen, and made great ſorrowe ouer him.</hi> What, and how great ſorowe, greife,<note place="margin">Actes. 8.</note> and miſerie did they féele, who although they were not ſlayne: yet were they ſpoyled of all their gooddes, driuen into baniſhment, and brought to extreame pouertie and beggerie?</p>
            <p>Heerewithall alſo, let euerie man conſider, what Church it was that ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fred ſo gréeuous perſecution, forſooth euen the moſt holly and moſte perfecte Church of al. For of this Church <hi>Luke</hi> witneſſeth, writinge: <hi>They were all
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:176431:17"/> filled with the holly ghoſte. And of al</hi>
               <note place="margin">Actes. 4.</note> 
               <hi>the multitude y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> beleued ther was one hart and one ſoule, and no man called anie thinge that hee had, his owne: but all thinges were common amonge</hi>
               <note place="margin">Actes. 2.</note> 
               <hi>them nether was there amonge them enie that lacked. Likewiſe: They continued euerie day with one accord in the temple, praiſinge God and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinge thankes beefore all the people.</hi> In this Church, Congregation, and fellowſhip, were the Apoſtels of our Lorde, and his threſcore and ten diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, <hi>Ioſeph of Arimathie, Barſabas</hi> or <hi>Barnabas, Nicodemus,</hi> with other woorthie men moe, but cheifly the holy and vndefiled virgin Marie, mother of the Lorde Ieſus Chriſte, with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe other vertuous and deuout we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, whoſe vertue and renoume is diſciphered in the Euangelicall hiſtory. In this Church there were no diuiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, no ſchiſmes, and the numbre of them that béeléeued was aboue fiue thouſande. To conclude, there was no Church in the Earth more excellent, holy, perfect, or more acceptable to God.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:176431:18"/>
            <p>Howbeit, god which ſuffred his owne<note place="margin">Wee muſte not aſk why God ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his chu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rche to bee perſecuted.</note> ſun to bée crucified, ſuffred alſo this holy Church to fall into ſutch afflictions, and ſo general a perſecution, as we haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared béefore. And who is now ſo wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked and curious, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> in reſpect of this per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution, dare ſtep foorth and diſpute a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God, and queſtion w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> him: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he ſuffred his dearly beloued frends to bée ſo gréeuouſly afflicted whiche had deſerued much better, and ſo many good &amp; godly perſons amonge whom chriſtes mother was one, whoſe moſt pure hart the ſharp ſword of ſorow and heauines had perced through? why likewiſe god gaue vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faithleſſe Iewes &amp; hipocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, ſo great power ouer godly, and iuſt men? why raught he not his helpynge hand to his Church, to help it, cauſing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> neither <hi>Steeuen</hi> ſhould bée ſtoned, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Church beinge ſpoyled of their goods be made poore, or baniſhed, nether they which liued in ſutch concorde togi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, with great ſorow, ſo miſerably bée plucked a ſundre, and ſcatred abroad? It pleaſed God it ſhould be ſo, who is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal wiſdom, &amp; doth no vniuſt thing.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:176431:18"/> And that which pleaſed God: pleaſed al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the holly Church, which nether mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moured, neither diſputed agaynſte the lord, but receaued perſecution willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and by the grace of God endured it paciently, knowyng and beléeuing, that God, who was omnipotent and merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, would ſo moderate the perſecution that it ſhould tende to the commoditie of the Church, as it alſo came to pas. In the ſame minde it béehoueth all the faythfull to bée in all maner perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and patiently to ſubmit themſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues to the pleaſure of God.</p>
            <p>Mutchleſſe héerby may the reaſoning of ſomme men take place, who gather out of perſecutions, that if the doctrine were true, and faith right: God would ayde them, and not deliuer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ouer in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their power, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> are altogether out of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> way concernyng doctrine and béeléefe. For in the perſecution of the primitiue church, theſe men, as apperteinyng to y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> body: had the victorie, whoſe faith was falſe, and they y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> were ſoundly perſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded ſuffred perſecution, were driuen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, &amp; ſlain, which ſlaughter &amp; calamity
<pb facs="tcp:176431:19"/> notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding, dyd nothing in damage the true faith. And in our age alſo the caſe ſtandeth none otherwiſe, neyther for the perſecutions which the Churche induereth, the faith and doctryne therof is leſſe to be regarded, or worſe therfore to be iudged. The true faith and doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pend vpon no victory, but onely vpon God, and his worde.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>Of the fourth Tragical</hi> Acte or perſecution, in which <hi>Saincte Iames the Apoſtle was</hi> ſlayne, and <hi>Peter</hi> caſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Priſon. <hi>Chapter.</hi> iiii.</head>
            <p>ABout the yeare of Chriſte. 45. <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rode</hi> ſurnamed <hi>Agrippa,</hi> ſunne to <hi>Herode</hi> the great, &amp; brother to <hi>Antipas</hi> moued y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fourth perſecution againſt the<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iames</hi> Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſlayne.</note> Churche, wherof <hi>Luke</hi> ſpeaketh in the <hi>Actes</hi> the. 12. Chapter. There he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clareth how <hi>Herod</hi> had decréed to mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt certen of the Churche, &amp; that he had alredy ſlaine with the ſword <hi>Iames</hi> the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:176431:19"/> brother of Iohn the Euangeliſt, (who alſo was one of the three whome the lord vſed moſt familiatly, and to whom hee opened his ſecretes) and not content with this cruell déed, procéeded farther, and call <hi>Peter</hi> into priſon to the intent to put him alſo to death.</p>
            <p>And becauſe theſe twaine were the cheefeſt amonge the Apoſtles: the whole Church was ſtrooken in great ſorowe and heauines for this perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and ſpecially <hi>Iohn,</hi> who was mutch greeued for his brothers death. The Church feared alſo, leaſt they ſhould leaſe their faithfull paſtor <hi>Peter,</hi> as they had doone <hi>Iames,</hi> wherfore <hi>Luke</hi> writeth, that dayly they powred foorth prayers vnto God for <hi>Peter,</hi> which prayers were not without effect. For the Angell of the lorde came into the priſon to <hi>Peter,</hi> and deliuered him out of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſouldiours hold, loſed his theines &amp; bandes, opened the iron gate, and ſet him at libertie in the open ſtreete, from whence by<hi rend="sup">•</hi> and by hee departed out of Ieruſalem.</p>
            <p>This great affliction the Church in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured
<pb facs="tcp:176431:20"/> pacientlye, neither murmured a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Chriſt, expoſtulatyng with hym why he gaue vnto <hi>Herod</hi> that wicked verlet, ſutch power againſt his dearly-beloued ones? why he ſuffred his whole Church, and ſpecially <hi>Iohn</hi> his beſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued of all the Diſciples, to be touched with ſuch heaueneſſe? why he deliuered not <hi>Iames,</hi> as he dyd <hi>Peter?</hi> they knew that God dyd nothing raſhly nor with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out cauſe, but euery thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g wel &amp; rightly. Wherfore, the faithfull in perſecutions muſt likewiſe be ſemblably perſuaded. For if euer men had nede to make their complaynt to God: then had they néede, neuertheleſſe there were heard no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>playnts, no murmurings, but earneſte and humble praiers. Wherfore in ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſitie, let the faithful flie vnto God in praier, requiring his grace y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> hée would gouerne al thing to y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> glory of his name and vnto our ſaluation, and whatſoeuer he doth that wée ſubmit our ſelues wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly to his holy will and pleaſure.</p>
            <p>Moreouer, no man in the Primitiue Church called the doctrine of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> Apoſtles into queſtion, becauſe <hi>Iames</hi> was ſlaine
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:176431:20"/> with the ſword, and <hi>Peter</hi> caſt into pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. For none of them ſaid thus: if the apoſtles doctrine were true &amp; iuſt: God would not haue ſuffered them to haue bin oppreſſed of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> kings, which erred in the faith, leadyng alſo a filthy, and wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked lyfe. Therefore at this day lyke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, the doctrine of the Goſpell is not to be doubted of, for that the teachers and followers therof, are by the Lorde delyuered ouer into the enemies hands of the Goſpell, and miſerably and cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by them intreated: for the truth not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtandyng is euerlaſting &amp; inuinci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. <hi>Paul</hi> in the ſame cauſe writeth, that he was afflicted for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſpel euen vnto hands, but y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> word of god was not bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d.</p>
            <p>The cauſe that ſtirred <hi>Herod</hi> to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church, was his owne peruerſe<note place="margin">2. Tim. 2.</note> minde, which lothed chriſt, &amp; his word. Moreouer, the <hi>Iewes</hi> gréedely thirſted the Apoſtles bloud, wherfore <hi>Herod</hi> to currie fauour with them: ſhed y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> bloud of the Apoſtles. This <hi>Luke</hi> witneſſeth in theſe words: <hi>And when he ſaw this</hi> (namely when he had ſlain <hi>Iames</hi> with y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſwoord) <hi>to be acceptable to the Iewes hee proceeded alſo to apprehende
<pb facs="tcp:176431:21"/> Peter, meaning after Eaſter to bringe him forth to the people.</hi> Like as in our age, many princes do perſecute the faithfull for none other cauſe, but that with their cruel butcherous Tragedies they might gratefie thoſe Fathers of <hi>Rome</hi> and their adherentes, who alſo vnſatiably do thirſt all their blood which cleaue only to Chriſte and his Goſpell, and ſet nought by, &amp; abhor their ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition, and Idolatrye.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>Of the. 5. tragical acte</hi> or perſecution, wherein Paule <hi>and the Chriſtian Church ſufferd</hi> many thinges, and the Apoſtles ended their liues full of afflictions, by ſheadyng their bloud. <hi>Chapter.</hi> v.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He fifte perſecution againſte <hi>Paule</hi> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Apoſtle continued ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny yeres, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Church alſo which beléeued the Goſpel partly for <hi>Paule</hi> w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whom they ſuffered, and partly for the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:176431:21"/> Goſpel of Chriſt abode ſundry troubles and afflictions, &amp; by that meanes was partaker of this perſecution.</p>
            <p>For when <hi>Paule</hi> had begun to preach<note place="margin">Actes. 9. 2. Cor. 12.</note> the Goſpel at <hi>Damaſcus,</hi> about the yere after Chriſte. xxxiii. and iourneynge through <hi>Arabya</hi> was retourned to <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſcus,</hi> and there diſputed earneſtly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Iewes: Aretas</hi> the King lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng watche at the Cittie gates, ſought hym to kyll hym, when the faithfull not beyng able otherwiſe to ſaue hym, let downe <hi>Paule</hi> by a Rope through the wall in a baſket, and ſo with great care and dillygence they kept him aliue.</p>
            <p>At <hi>Antioch</hi> alſo in <hi>Piſidia, Paule</hi> ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered<note place="margin">Actes. 13.</note> together a great congregatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Chriſt of <hi>Gentiles</hi> and <hi>Iewes,</hi> but the <hi>Iewes</hi> which would not imbrace Chriſt ſtirryng vp a perſecucion againſt <hi>Paule</hi> and <hi>Barnabas,</hi> draue them out of that Citie, and Region.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Iconium</hi> alſo, the <hi>Iewes</hi> agayne<note place="margin">Actes. 14.</note> mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ued a tumult againſt <hi>Paul,</hi> wherhe with his companion <hi>Barnabas</hi> were in forced to prouide for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues by flight. Alſo in <hi>Liſtra</hi> the ſame <hi>Iewes</hi> brought
<pb facs="tcp:176431:22"/> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> ſo far into hatred, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> being ſtoned &amp; drawn forth of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> towne as dead: yet chriſt raiſed him again to do him ſeruice At <hi>Phillippos</hi> in <hi>Macedonia Paul</hi> and his fellow <hi>Silas,</hi> were taken, ſcourged with rods, and caſt into a very ſtraight priſon, out of whiche notwithſtanding Chriſt deliuered him, that he might yet preach the Goſpell, to moe nations.</p>
            <p>Moreouer at <hi>Theſſalonica</hi> there was<note place="margin">Actes. 17.</note> agreeuous perſecution moued againſte <hi>Paul,</hi> wher he was conſtrained through helpe of the faithfull, to eſcape away by night. The lyke he ſuffred at <hi>Berroea.</hi> At <hi>Athens,</hi> the Philoſophers and wyſe men of this world, reprochfully termed him a trifler, rayled at hym, and moc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked<note place="margin">Actes. 18.</note> hym, as the like was done to the lord himſelf. Likewiſe in the famous citie of Gréece called Corinthe, hée was apprended and brought to the lieutena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes ſeate of iudgment and ſharply accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, but then alſo the Lorde deliuered him out of the power of his enemies.</p>
            <p>But what gréeuous thinges <hi>Paule</hi>
               <note place="margin">Actes. 19. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.</note> ſuffred in <hi>Aſia</hi> at <hi>Epheſus,</hi> are by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe recited in theſe wordes: <hi>I woulde not haue you ignoraunt, brethern, of
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:176431:22"/> the trouble and affliction which hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vnto vs in Aſia, how we were won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully greued aboue our power, that we were in diſpaire euen of lyfe. But we receiued a decree within our ſelues touchyng death, that wee ſhoulde not truſt in our ſelues, but in God whiche raiſeth the dead.</hi> In <hi>Luke</hi> alſo in y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> 
               <hi>Act.</hi> of the Apoſtles there is ſet forth a nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble deſcription of the tumult which was at <hi>Epheſus.</hi> Vpon occaſion of which tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mult there the faithfull remayned in great ſorow, heauines, and daunger, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo by reaſon of the continuall waite lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng and perſecutions, wherwith the vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>faithfull both <hi>Iewes</hi> and <hi>Gentiles</hi> perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted them. After ſo many daungers,<note place="margin">Actes. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> afflictions, and moſt greuous traueles, when <hi>Paule</hi> was arriued at <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> bringing w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> him a great, and ritch trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, whiche he had gathered as a dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue for y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> pouerty of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> citie, and relm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>: there againe y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> 
               <hi>Iewes</hi> raiſed a moſt wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſeditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; apprehending <hi>Paul</hi> ſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged him biterly wher he had bin vtterli deſtroyd, vnles the Tribune co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming in al ſpéede w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his ſouldiers had taken him out of their handes.
<pb facs="tcp:176431:23"/> This beinge doone: hée was by the tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bune brought into the Eccleſiaſticall <note place="margin">Act. 23.</note> court, where hée was alſo ſcourged, and vnworthely intreated. Afterward, bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the great treaſon of the Jewes being guarded with a ſufficient power of horſemen, and footemen hée was ſent from Jeruſalem to <hi>Caeſarea,</hi> vnto <hi>Foelix</hi> the lieutenaunt, Beefore whom when he came: the cheif of the <hi>Iewes</hi> accuſed him, layinge manie thinges to his charge, wherin al though hée could not bee fownd giltie: notwithſtanding hée was committed to indurance, wher hée remayned the ſpace of two whole yeeres. <note place="margin">Act. 25.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Moreouer, he was euelly delt with <note place="margin">Act. 2 7.</note> all by <hi>Feſtus</hi> alſo the new lieutenaunt who ſucceeded <hi>Foelix,</hi> &amp; after ward with other priſoners deliuered ouer vnto the Centurians and ſouldiours, imbarked, and with a longe and daungerous iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney brought to <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But <hi>Nero</hi> then reigninge at <hi>Rome</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Act. 28.</note> hée remayned agayne priſoner there two yeres. Some are of opinion that at this time he was ſlaine with the ſword
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:176431:23"/> by <hi>Nero,</hi> others thinke that hée was ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quited in iudgement by <hi>Nero:</hi> as hée himſelf witneſſeth in the ij. to Timoth. the .iiii. chapter, and béeinge ſo ſet at li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie, that hée departed directly intoo <hi>Spaine,</hi> as béefore hée had declared in the Epiſtle to the <hi>Romanes,</hi> that hée was deſierous to take in hand that iour<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ney. <note place="margin">Rom. 15.</note> And traueylinge through <hi>Spaine,</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> they ſay how hée came the ſeconde time to <hi>Rome,</hi> in the later ye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res of the reigne of <hi>Nero,</hi> and there was ſlayn with the ſworde at <hi>Neroes</hi> commaundement. But this wée leaue as vncertain: howbeit this is euident, wherin all doo agrée, that the moſt holly Apoſtle Paule was putte to death at <hi>Rome,</hi> vnder <hi>Nero.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The traueiles, afflictions, and ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drie calamities whiche for none offence <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Paules</hi> afflic<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cions.</note> hée ſuſtayned, but for Chriſt his woord, and the Churche, the Apoſtle himſelfe imputynge them to his enemies, and falſe Apoſtles: reciteth in a bréeif cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue in theſe woordes: <hi>Are they the miniſters of Chriſte? I ſpeake like a foole, I am more, in labours more abu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2. Cor. 11.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:176431:24"/> 
               <hi>in woundes ſurpaſſynge them, in priſon more commonly, in death</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Deut. 25.</note> 
               <hi>often. Of the Iewes I receaued fiue times fourtie ſtripes ſauynge-one, I was thriſe ſcourged with roddes, and once ſtoned, thriſe I ſuffred ſhipwrak night and day haue I beene on the deepe ſea. In iourneinge often, in da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unger of waters, in daunger of theues, indaunger of mine owne countriemen in daunger of the heathen, in daunger in the Citie, in daunger in the wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, in daunger in the ſea, in daunger amonge falſe brethren. In weerines and traueyle, in watchinge often, in hunger and thirſt, in faſtinge often, in colde and nakednes. Beeſide thoſe thinges which happen outwardly vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to mee, for the heape of them dayly riſeth againſt mee, which is to ſay, the care for all Churches of Chriſte.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now therfore, by ſo many afflictions which <hi>Paule</hi> ſuſtained, and by the vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory &amp; good ſucceſſe of his enemies, can it be gathered that <hi>Paules</hi> doctrine was erronious, or elſe God would haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended him, nether haue ſuffred him to
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:176431:24"/> haue bin ouer whelmed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſo many ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamities, and reproches? Shal wée ther fore; diſpute againſt god, whi he ſuffreth wicked me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſomutch to preuaile againſt the faithful, and his holy miniſters? or why he permitteth the ſacred Churche of Chriſte to ſuffre ſo mutch in it ſelfe, and in the faythful paſtor therof <hi>Paule?</hi> The godly men ſuffred all theſe things patiently and ouercame them, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued alwaies conſtant vnder y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> croſſe.</p>
            <p>The cauſe why the Iewes were ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to <hi>Paul,</hi> &amp; to y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> church: ſurely was none other then y<hi rend="sup">•</hi>, wherwith being be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mooued, they perſecuted Chriſt, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> apoſtles, as we haue declared before.</p>
            <p>Moreouer, hyſtories beare recorde, that the twelue Apoſtles in all their life <note place="margin">Al the apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles after afflictions were put to death.</note> time, and durynge the tearme of their adminiſtration in the goſpel: ſuſtayned gréeuous afflictions, and were all of them for Chriſte and his woords ſake, perſecuted, and put to death.</p>
            <p>Although all writers doo not agrée of their kinds of death, yet they al co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly affirme, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> thei were miſerably ſlain. <hi>Peter</hi> and his brother <hi>Andrew,</hi> were
<pb facs="tcp:176431:25"/> both crucified. <hi>Iames</hi> the elder, as wée haue ſhewen before, was béeheaded by <note place="margin">Peter and Andrevv.</note> 
               <hi>Herod</hi> ſurnamed <hi>Agrippa.</hi> Whoſe brother Iohn the Euangeliſt the béelo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iames</hi> the el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</note> diſciple of Chriſt, only of them al is <note place="margin">Iohn Euan.</note> reported to haue died a naturall death. Notwithſtandyng hée was apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and brought bounde out of <hi>Aſia</hi> to <hi>Rome,</hi> and conuented béefore <hi>Domitia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> th'emperour, and there, as <hi>Tertullian</hi> writeth, plunged ouer head and eares in hot boylinge oyle. But after that, the lorde graciouſly prouiding for him, this cruell déede nothing indamaged his life: hée was baniſhed into y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> Iſle <hi>Pathmos. Phillip</hi> was nayled to a croſſe, &amp; there hangynge: was ſtoned to death. <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thelmew,</hi> thei ſay, was by his enemies <note place="margin">Phillippe.</note> moſt horribly flayne, and afterward béeheaded. Otherſome ſay hée was <note place="margin">Bartelmew.</note> burnt. The enemies of Chriſte, thruſt Thomas through with a ſworde, and ſo, as it is reported, they dealt with <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew.</hi> Iames the younger, the paſtor &amp; <note place="margin">Thomas.</note> doctor of the church of Ieruſalem, was throwne downe headlonge from an <note place="margin">Mathew. Iames the leſſe.</note> high place, and afterwarde ſlayne
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:176431:25"/> beinge buffeted with ſtones vntill hée died. Likewiſe both Apoſtles, <hi>Simon</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Simon, and Iude.</note> and <hi>Iudas Thaddaeus</hi> ended their li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, beinge by the heathen ſlain in a certen temple of Idols. Some alſo ſay that <hi>Mathias</hi> was crucified, others ſay <note place="margin">Mathias.</note> hée was ſtoned, and béeheaded. Al theſe bare witnes of Chriſte, not with their mouth and doctrine only, but with ther blood alſo, and for the trueth of the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell which they preached, were conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to die with wel willing, and moſte valient courage.</p>
            <p>Now, for as mutch as all the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles were ſlayn by the enimies of God <note place="margin">Note.</note> who obtayned the ſouerainitye ouer them as apperteyninge to the bodye: ſhall wée therfore ſay that ſuperſtitions of Gods enemies were right, and the Apoſtles religion and doctrine falſe and erroneous? who ſhall accuſe God, by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hée deliuered not his ſeruantes from a reprochfull death but that hée gaue to the worſt men in the whole worlde, ſutch power agaynſt his holly Apoſtles? Who although they were miniſters of the trueth, and innocent
<pb facs="tcp:176431:26"/> men: yet were they put to death for the greateſt enemies of God, as malifac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours and wicked perſons, for ſutche were they accuſed to bée: and therefore, at this our age, in the lyke cauſe, wee muſt iudge ſo of their beléefe &amp; doctrine, who ar ſhamefully executed for chriſts ſake, as indéede the trueth ſtandeth in the ſight of Chriſte.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ <hi>Of the. 6. Tragicall</hi> Acte or perſecutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which was <hi>vnder Nero, and of the ſeuenth</hi> which was vnder <hi>Domitian,</hi> and of the eight vnder <hi>Vlpius Traian,</hi> Emperours. <hi>Chapter VI.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>PAulus Oroſius</hi> an olde hiſtorician, who liued in the time of <hi>Auſtine,</hi> and wrote vnto hym ſeuene bookes of Storyes, beginneth the recitall of the perſecutyon of the Chriſtian Churche, from the perſecution whiche <hi>Nero</hi> had moued, which hée accounteth the firſt whoſe order the later Hiſtoricians alſo
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:176431:26"/> inſued. And we lykewiſe, in deſcribing the Tragedies &amp; perſecutions commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted againſt the Church: wyll follow the ſame order, as conſequently they follow one another. But ſince it is manifeſt, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> the fiue aboue recited perſecutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, were before theſe, as the ſcriptures do ſhew, that which <hi>Oroſius</hi> maketh the firſte, we make the ſixt: although the matter be of no great importa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in this reſpect.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Oroſius</hi> writeth, that <hi>Nero</hi> firſte (that is to ſay among the <hi>Roman</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours) <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Nero</hi> perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuteth the Chriſtians</note> gaue forth commaundement, that at <hi>Rome,</hi> and in al other prouinces belonging to the Roman Empire, the Chriſtians ſhoulde bee moleſted, and ſlayne. And y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> this was his determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to roote oute the Chriſtian faith &amp; all Chriſtians whereſoeuer they were.</p>
            <p>The cauſes that moued <hi>Nero</hi> to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> Chriſtians are not ſo dilygent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye ſet downe by chriſtian hiſtoricians, as they are by prophane writers, <hi>Sue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonius Tranquillus</hi> in the lyfe of <hi>Nero</hi> and <hi>Cornelius Tacitus</hi> in the. 15. booke of the lyues of the Emperours. <hi>Nero</hi> y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> emperour was y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſinke of al beaſtly ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe,
<pb facs="tcp:176431:27"/> fulneſſe, chiefly of lechery, and vnſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able inceſt, defilyng himſelfe againſt al courſe of nature, ſo y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> in all Hiſtories of you ſhal not finde his match. This hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible wickedneſſe he openly committed at <hi>Rome</hi> without al ſhame, in ſight of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> 
               <hi>Senate,</hi> and people. But there was no man that durſte ſpeake againſt hym, mutch leſſe to reproue him, or aſſay to puniſh hym, but euery man winked at hym, the moſt filthy beaſt in the meane time doyng what he liſt.</p>
            <p>Wherfore, God being offended with the citie of <hi>Rome:</hi> puniſhed it with fire, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rome</hi> puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed with fire as So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome was.</note> as he did <hi>Sodome &amp; Gomorrha</hi> euen by <hi>Nero</hi> himſelf, when as for his <hi>Sodomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical</hi> beaſtlineſſe, hée deſerued to be bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned himſelf. And ſéeing <hi>Rome</hi> winked at his naughtineſſe, and did not y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> which it ought to haue done: the horryble <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domite Nero,</hi> cauſed the citie to be ſet on fire. For being certen places in the cittie wherewith <hi>Nero</hi> miſlyked, and the ſtreates and paſſadges there verye narrow: he cauſed the houſes to be ſette on fire, that after they were brent, they might be builded againe more faire, and
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:176431:27"/> ſumptious. He himſelfe beheld the fire out of <hi>Mecoenas</hi> tower, ſaying: that he much deſired to ſe the burning of <hi>Troy</hi> which he beheld now ſom what reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled by that burning of the citie, ſinging therwhiles the deſtruction of <hi>Troy,</hi> and delighting himſelfe with beholdyng the great fire. <hi>Suetonius</hi> reporteth, that from that time that <hi>Rome</hi> was firſte built, it neuer ſuſtayned ſo much hurte by fire: for it continued alwayes burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the ſpace of ſix dayes and ſo manye nights. The ſame is alſo diligentlye de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed by <hi>Tacitus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But when the fire through the wrath of God had brent farther then <hi>Nero</hi> had <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Nero</hi> impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the fire to Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans.</note> thought it ſhoulde, and indamaged the Citie with an vnrepayrable loſſe and hinderaunce, the citizens which had ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained ſo great harme, were very much moued, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ffended. Wherefore the Emperour <hi>Nero,</hi> to the intent that hee might put ouer from himſelf the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of the déede, raiſed a rumour among the commons, that this whole miſcheif was long of the Chriſtians, that they were aduerſaries to the Gods and Religon
<pb facs="tcp:176431:28"/> of the <hi>Romans,</hi> and wicked burners of cities and townes, who alſo in that ſort had defaced the citie. And that this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port might ſéeme to carie ſome trueth and auctoritie: hée caſt manie Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans into priſon, and examined them by tortures and tormentes, that they ſhould confeſſe how the citie was ſet on fire by them. And in dede there were ſome fownd, who not beinge able to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide tormentes, but rather wiſſhing to die: falſly accuſed themſelues &amp; other Chriſtians, confeſſinge that they had ſet the citie on fire.</p>
            <p>Wherfore immediatly, there was a proclamation publiſhed by the empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour againſt chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, in which it was commaunded, that in <hi>Rome</hi> and al pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinces thei ſhould be rooted out, as ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to the gods and religion of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>manes,</hi> and men practiſed in burning &amp; ſetting on fire. And this was the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> perſecution, and blouddy tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gedie. For ſome in reproche, and for a mockyng ſtocke, were ſowed into the ſkinnes of wild beaſts, as <hi>Tacitus</hi> wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth &amp; caſt vnto dogs to be torne. Other were brent, ſome <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ed and crucified,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:176431:28"/> and ſo deſtroyed with ſundrie and moſt cruel puniſhments, inſo mutch that (as <hi>Tacitus</hi> writeth) the common people of <hi>Rome</hi> were mooued w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> greate pitie to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them. But with <hi>Nero</hi> ther was no mercy, no end of torments. In this perſecution were ſlayne, as hiſtoricians do teſtifie, and we alſo haue declared be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: the Apoſtles <hi>Peter &amp; Paul.</hi> There be alſo numbred by Chroniclers many notable and godly men, whiche in this perſecution ſuffred gréeuous affliction, reproches, &amp; puniſhment of bitter death not at <hi>Rome</hi> only, but here &amp; there in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther prouinces of the <hi>Romane</hi> empire.</p>
            <p>Since therfore, this perſecution was <note place="margin">Wee muſt not diſpute with God.</note> firſt moued by <hi>Nero</hi> for a filthy &amp; hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible cauſe, who ſhall accuſe God for graunting ſuch power to a wicked, and <hi>Sodomiticall</hi> perſon, againſt ſo many thouſands of holy and innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t men, yea freinds of God? or why hee ſuffred the chriſtians to be brent for houſe burners and did not rather hale foorth <hi>Nero</hi> the true houſe burner and beaſtly <hi>Sodomit</hi> caſtinge him into the thickeſt of the people to bee torne in peces? when therfore, in our age, the lyke do happen:
<pb facs="tcp:176431:29"/> let all men humbly ſubmit themſelues to the power of God and his mightye hande, beare their croſſe with pacience which the Lord layeth vpon them, giue laud and praiſe vnto God, and conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye cleaue to his holy worde, whiche at <hi>Neroes</hi> time was alſo true and iuſt, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it was behouefull that the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſhould ſuffer afflictions, and <hi>Nero</hi> ouercome them, and haue power ouer them, with his prophane, and ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Relygion.</p>
            <p>After this, about the yere of our Lord 97. with intollerable and diuelliſh pride <note place="margin">Diuelyſhe pride.</note> 
               <hi>Domitian</hi> the Emperour ſet foorth him ſelf, ſunne to <hi>Veſpaſian,</hi> brother to <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,</hi> by whom the Citie of <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> was deſtroyd, the <hi>Iewes</hi> vanquiſhed in battle, and opreſſed. The ſame was not aſhamed to boaſt himſelfe to be God &amp; Lord, and would ſo be called and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped of al me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> which no Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour <note place="margin">Note.</note> required before him, he comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> they ſhould kiſſe his féete, wherin no Emperour followinge hym dyd the lyke, except <hi>Dioclecian</hi> onely, a cruell Tyrant, and a murtherer of holy men.</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:176431:29"/>
            <p>This <hi>Dominitia</hi> ſet a broch the .vii. perſecutions againſt Chriſtians, in the which many holy men were driuen in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to baniſhment, many flayne or ſpoyled of their goods, and troubled moſt bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> the Euangeliſt</note> Amongſt whom <hi>Iohn</hi> the Apoſtle and Euangeliſt was brought priſoner from <hi>Epheſus</hi> to <hi>Rome</hi> vnto the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, and there tormented. <hi>Flauia</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, and <hi>Domicilla</hi> of greateſt nobilitie in the citie, with diuers other mo, were by <hi>Domitian</hi> ſent into baniſhment. But Iohn afterward returned vnto <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſus,</hi> and there died in the yere of our Lorde. 102. after the paſſion of Chriſte, 68. and the third yéere of the reygne of <hi>Traiane</hi> the Emperour.</p>
            <p>After this, about the yéere of our lord. 110. <hi>Vlpius Traiane,</hi> a mightie and vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious Emperour, was the cauſe and authour of the eight perſecution againſt the Chriſtians, in <hi>Rome,</hi> and in other places vnder the Romaine Empire. Whiche thynge cheifly prouoked him, and other Emperours that came after him to perſecute the Chriſtians, bicauſe they thought good that there ſhould bee
<pb facs="tcp:176431:30"/> no Schiſme ſuffred in the empire, ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in religion, but that there ſhould bée one only religion receaued, whiche their forefathers had obſerued béefore time. Now that diſagréement in reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion nouriſheth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tentions and hatred a thing not to bée ſuffred in any empire Moreouer, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> they feared gréeuous cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, and puniſhments, if their gods were not woorſhipped after their accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomed maner, and therfore the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, bicauſe they hated their temples aulters, ſacrifices, images, and holly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayes, blamyng and diſdaynynge the religion of the <hi>Romanes:</hi> were in no wiſe to be ſuffred. Wherfore, if any ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamities ſhould chaunce to riſe in y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane <note place="margin">Read <hi>Cyp.</hi> againſt <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metri.</hi>
               </note> empire, as are troubles, dearth of corne, famine, warre, ſeditions, peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, diſeaſes, with other diſcommodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties: by and by y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> Romans burthened the Chriſtians with y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> cauſe of all theſe anoyances, for contemnyng their gods and religion, and doyng contrarie vnto the ſame. That they woorſhipped one God, acknowledgyng Chriſt alone the ſunne of God to bée the only ſauiour,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:176431:30"/> openly pronouncyng, that the Romane religion was falſe and of the diuel, that their faith in Chriſte was true &amp; right, nether that God ought to bée worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped with images and temples, ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and hollydayes, but in ſpirite and trueth, accordyng to his woorde.</p>
            <p>As for the Romans, and other nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons abroad in the worlde, they were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together addicted to ſuperſtitions, vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently ſheadyng their blood, leeſing their goods, and liues, in defence of their reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, exhortyng other firmely to retain y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſame. For they boaſted how they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> religion of their elders, which were no fooles but excellent wiſemen: Moreouer that there were many lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned men in their collegies of prieſts, &amp; that their beléef was confirmed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie notable wounders and miracles, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> whilſt they obſerued that religion they obtayned ſundry great victories, and y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> whole empire of al the worlde, attribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng al their good ſucceſſe and ſalftie, to their religion, which had remained ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nie thouſand yéeres, not béeyng ſo new and but thyrtie yéeres ould as was
<pb facs="tcp:176431:31"/> the chriſtian religion. That their Gods were friendly and liberall vnto them: helpyng them in ſutche ſorte, that they wanted nothynge, on the otherſide the chriſtians were poore and vnfortunate: wherfore they ſhould doo amiſſe if they erred the breadth of one heare, or ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the ſacrilegious enemies of their ancient and victorious religion. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, theſe cauſes which wee haue now recited, prouoked the <hi>Romane</hi> Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours to perſecute the Chriſtians. The cauſes of the perſecutions likewiſe in our age are not mutche vnlyke whoſo <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Traians</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution.</note> weyeth them both vprightly.</p>
            <p>Wherefore, in this perſecution mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by <hi>Traiane</hi> there was an vnſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able deale of Chriſtian bloud ſhed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> At <hi>Ieruſalem Simeon</hi> Byſhop of the citie, beinge an hundred and twenty yeares ould, was crucified. <hi>S. Ignatius</hi> alſo the ſeruant of Chriſte, and Diſciple of the Apoſtles, was brought from <hi>Antioche</hi> where he was Biſhop vnto <hi>Rome,</hi> caſt vnto wilde beaſtes, and by them torne in péeces. Their Tragedies were ſo cruel, their ſlaughters ſo great, the ſhea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:176431:31"/> of Chriſtian blood ſo horrible: that <hi>Plinie</hi> the ſeconde, a wiſe gentleman, and lieutenant to the emperour, wrate vnto the emperour, giuinge vnto the Chriſtians, a ſingulare teſtimonie of their innocencie. This epiſtle is to bée ſéene in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> booke of <hi>Plinies</hi> epiſtles. By which meanes the ſtate of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans was ſome deale the more at quiet.</p>
            <p>Yet in reſpecte of this perſecution which was great, and laſted longe time <note place="margin">God is iuſt and the faith true.</note> wherin were deſtroied many thouſand Chriſtians, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> Chriſtian religion ought not bée iudged falſe or worſe to bée eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>téemed of, or that the gentile and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane religion of the <hi>Romanes</hi> is righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and ſownd. For throughout the whole world, and in all ages the Chriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian religion is only true, righteous, and conſtant: nether hath God doone amiſſe, in giuinge the <hi>Ethnickes</hi> ſo great power againſt the faithfull. For by meanes therof, the Chriſtian faith is nothinge diminiſhed, nether by pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, nether by ſheadinge of blood: but it is rather increaſed in all partes of the worlde, wherfore it is not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb facs="tcp:176431:32"/> cauſe amonge our forefathers gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen into a prouerbe: the field of Chriſt is dungged and made frutefull with Chriſtians innocent bloud. Wherfore let vs al likewiſe now be of good hope in midſte of perſecutions, and ſheadinge of miſerable, innocent, Chriſtian blood.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>Of the. 9. Tragical acte</hi> or perſecution, which was <hi>vnder Antoninus Verus, with</hi> his brother <hi>Lucius,</hi> and what worthy men exhibited Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logies of the chriſtian faith vnto the Emperours. <hi>Chapter, vii.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THe yere of Chriſt, 170. and. 178. the Roman Emperours, <hi>Marcus An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toninus Verus,</hi> and his brother <hi>Lucius</hi> for none other cauſes then we haue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue recited: ſharply perſecuted al chriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians, that generallye were vnder the <hi>Romane</hi> Empire. This perſecution Hiſtoricians call the fourth, but I terme it the ninth. The exacte deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:176431:32"/> and at large therof, whoſo deſireth to beehold: let him reade the fourth, and fift bookes of <hi>Euſebius</hi> eccleſiaſticall hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorie. In this perſecution were ſlayn, not only many of the Chriſtian Church but alſo the moſte famous and renow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med doctoure of that age, who in tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching and writing, ſet frooth the chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an relygion, enlarged it, and defended it commendinge their doctryn with their moſt holly life, and bearinge wytnes therto with theyr owne blood. Among whom was <hi>Polycarpus,</hi> Diſcyple to the apoſtles, an extreme ould father, and miniſter of the congregatyon at <hi>Smyrna,</hi> whom they call the doctor of <note place="margin">Polycarp.</note> 
               <hi>Aſia,</hi> and father of the Chriſtians: alſo the holye and paynfull Miniſter of chriſt, <hi>Pionius:</hi> both theſe w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> many mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>notable chriſtians, were burnt Lyke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyſe <note place="margin">Pionius.</note> y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> moſt lerned and faythfull my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſters of Chriſt: <hi>Iuſtinius</hi> a philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher, and <hi>Iraeneus</hi> Byſhop of <hi>Lions</hi> in <note place="margin">Iuſtinus. Iraeneus.</note> 
               <hi>France,</hi> whoſe bookes in defence of the chriſtyan fayth, agaynſte all kyndes of errours and hereſies: are yet extant: were ſlayne wyth the ſword.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:176431:33"/>
            <p>But chifly at <hi>Lions</hi> and <hi>Vienna</hi> in <hi>France</hi> nigh the riuer <hi>Rhodanus:</hi> was very mutch cruelty and extremitie ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen. This perſecution is deſcribed by the miniſters of Chriſte dwellynge at <hi>Vienna</hi> and <hi>Lions,</hi> in an epiſtle vnto y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> brethren of the congregations of <hi>Aſia</hi> and <hi>Phrygia,</hi> let him read that liſt her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, <note place="margin">Phoianus</note> the foure firſt chapters of the firſte booke of <hi>Euſebius</hi> eccleſiaſtical hiſtorie: there among other thyngs, they declare how <hi>Photinus</hi> biſhop of Lyons, a wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie man, learned, and holly, and aboue foure ſcore and ten yéeres old, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore féeble of body, but valiant of minde and without all feare, was brought to the place of iudgement: of whom when there was required an accoumpt of his fayth, with a wounderfull courage hée profeſſed Chriſte and the Chriſtian faith: wherfore hée was by the raſhe &amp; furious people ſtroken, buffeted, ſpur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, &amp; without al regarde of age or cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyng, reprochefully abuſed, ſo y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> he was drawen backe agayne to the priſon for dead, where not longe after hée yéelded vp the ghoſt.</p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:176431:33"/>
            <p>In the ſame place, are ſingularly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> cruel torments, wherwith the holy men were long time torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted, as <note place="margin">Maturus. Sanctus. Blandina.</note> 
               <hi>Maturus, Sanctus,</hi> and <hi>Blandina,</hi> a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of ſingular courage &amp; conſtancy in the true faith, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Attalus</hi> borne of a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble race, in faith more noble. All theſe <note place="margin">Atalus</note> were ſlayne with moſt cruell and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall tormentes, bicauſe they would not yéeld one iote from the trueth.</p>
            <p>They write moreouer, how that the common raſkall multitude in this per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution was ſo ſauedge, cruelly pric<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked foorth with anger and rage: y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> they left nothyng vndone that appertayned to the moſt cruell and ignominious v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedge of them. For they would not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit the bodies of ſutch as were ſlayne in priſon, to bée honeſtly buried, but caſt them to dogges, who if they left any thyng, that they burned and threwe the aſſhes into <hi>Rhodanus:</hi> theſe turmen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours in the meane time criyng alowd, as it is reported, behold, the Gods haue reuenged themſelues on the enemies of the Ethnicke religion, where is now their god? what maner of faith and reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion
<pb facs="tcp:176431:34"/> is this, that ſpoyleth them thus of their liues? Thus thei reioiced, &amp; trium<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phed <note place="margin">Triumph<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng of the people.</note> like conquerours y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> had defended and confirmed their owne religion: and on th'other part, the Chriſtians remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in great ſorow, heauines, and daun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ger. Whoſo deſiereth to vnderſtande more of this matter, let him read it in <hi>Euſebius</hi> in the epiſtle aboue recited.</p>
            <p>Moreouer, there is ſet downe by <hi>Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mannus Contractus,</hi> in his chronicles, an whole catalogue of principall bleſſed martirs y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſuffred in this perſecution. Wherfore, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> which I haue often ſayd, I ſay againe: is there any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo ſimple and deuoyd of iudgment y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> dareth to ſay that the doctrine and religion of the holy Martyrs and witneſſes of Chriſte was falſe, bicauſe God deliuered them ouer into y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> handes of their enimies, gentils, and vnfaithful? ether y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> their doctrine &amp; religion was tru and righteous, bicauſe as apperteyninge to the body they van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſhed, ſlewe, and oppreſſed the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full? And who is ſo preſumptious that he will diſpute with God, why hée ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freth his dearly beloued Church to bée caſt down, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>roden vnder foote, with
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:176431:34"/> ſo many afflictions, and calamities?</p>
            <p>But in this age, &amp; the next following God through his grace, raiſed euen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> gentiles, worthie &amp; renowmed men, learned, holy, &amp; wel diſpoſed, who offred vnto y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> Roman emperours, to the Senate, &amp; lieutenants: bookes written w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> diuine inſtinct, perſpicuous, and wiſe wherin they declared the innocencie of Chriſtians, confeſſing the faith of chriſt praiſing, &amp; defendyng it, ſhewinge alſo, how falſly y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> chriſtians were charged w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> notorious crimes y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> were layde againſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. This kinde of writyng they terme Apologies. In which apologies, thei vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred ſuch conſtancie, and valientneſſe of minde: y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> thei durſt alſo to diſcipher, and diſproue, the errour &amp; vanitie of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> Eth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nick religion. I minde to ſet downe in this place, a catalogue and reherſal of al ſutch as wrote Apologies, &amp; I wil note alſo the time of doyng of al thoſe things out of <hi>Euſebius,</hi> y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> al men may perceaue how couragiouſly the Chriſtian reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion ſet foorth herſelf openly, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all feare, in midſt of perſecutions, gliſteryng therin as it were the ſunne, howbéeit there whiles the vnfaythfull
<pb facs="tcp:176431:35"/> perſecuted the ſame as hereſy &amp; deceite, and waſhing the Chriſtians in their owne blood.</p>
            <p>In the yere of Chriſt 119. <hi>Quadratus</hi> a graue and holy man, preferred an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pologye <note place="margin">Quadratus</note> or defence of the Chriſtians vnto the Emperour <hi>Adrian.</hi> After <note place="margin">sereous Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius.</note> whom, the yere of our Lord. 122. <hi>Sere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus Granius,</hi> one of the nobillytie of <hi>Rome,</hi> wrote alſo and Apologie to the ſame Emperour. Likewiſe <hi>Ariſtides</hi> a famous man, made meanes vnto <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ariſtides.</note> in the ſame maner. Al whoſe writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings preuailed ſo much with the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour: that he directed his letters vnto <hi>Minutius Fundanus</hi> lieuetenant of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">In the ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ. Hiſt. boke. 4. cha. 9.</note> commaundynge hym, that thence forward hée ſhould receiue no accuſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons againſt Chriſtians for their relygi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, vnleſſe they were accuſed of other crimes, and offences.</p>
            <p>Afterward, in the yere of our Lord 141. <note place="margin">Iuſtinus.</note> 
               <hi>Iuſtinus</hi> a Philoſopher, a man not only moſt renowmed at <hi>Rome,</hi> but alſo in other places: preferred an Apollogy for the chriſtians, vnto <hi>Antoninus Pius</hi> y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> Emperour. Which ſelfe ſame requeſt
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:176431:35"/> almoſt, <hi>Aſianus Appolinaris,</hi> byſhop of <note place="margin">Aſianus. Appolinaris.</note> 
               <hi>Hierapolis,</hi> and <hi>Milciades</hi> who alſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited their owne Apologies vnto <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toninus.</hi> But the Emperour <hi>Marcus Aurelius Antoninus Pius,</hi> in his letters ſent to the Lieutenantes of <hi>Aſia,</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded them that they ſhoulde in no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe moleſt the Chriſtians. The copie of this Epiſtle is to be found in the. 4. <note place="margin">Milciades.</note> booke, and. 13. Chapter of the eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Hiſtory. Beſides all this, <hi>Athena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goras</hi> a Philoſopher of <hi>Athens,</hi> wrote <note place="margin">Athenago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rar.</note> an Apology and defence of the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, vnto <hi>Marcus Aurelius Antoninꝰ,</hi> and vnto <hi>Lucius Aurclus Commodus,</hi> whiche defence is yet extant, both in Gréeke and Latine.</p>
            <p>At <hi>Rome</hi> alſo <hi>Appollonius</hi> a Sena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour, <note place="margin">Apollonius.</note> a noble gentilman and wiſe, being accuſed of the Chriſtian religion: wrote a worthy booke of our Religion, and of the innocency of the Chriſtians, and reade it in <hi>Rome</hi> in the Senate. Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtandyng hee was condemned to dye, the yere of our Lord. 188.</p>
            <p>Laſt of all <hi>Tertulian,</hi> about the yer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e <note place="margin">Tertulian.</note> of our Lord. 209. wrote a ſingular boke
<pb facs="tcp:176431:36"/> in behalf of the Chriſtians, wherin hée declareth their innocencie, and the folly of the Ethnick religion, and contrari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the trueth and excellencie, of the Chriſtian faith. This booke is yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maininge in our daies.</p>
            <p>By theſe and like reaſons it appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, that our true, auntient, &amp; vndoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Chriſtian faith, although y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> worlde contemne it, raile at it, and perſecute it: neuertheleſſe is the only true, and autenticke faith.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="8" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>Of the. 10. Tragicall</hi> Acte or perſecution, vnder <hi>Seuerus, and of the. 11. vnder Iulius Maximinus,</hi> of the. 12. vnder <hi>Traiane Decius,</hi> of the 13. vnder <hi>Valeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anus,</hi> and of the 14. vnder <hi>Aurelianus</hi> the Emp. <hi>Chapter. viii.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>ABout the yere of our Lorde Ieſus Chriſte. 204. <hi>Septimius Seuerus</hi> the Emperour, a prince of a firce diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, began ſharpely to perſecute the Chriſtian church. And in ſundry places in all prouinces of the <hi>Romane</hi> empire
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:176431:36"/> many woorthie men of the faithfull, were tormented and ſlayn, amonge all whom, as cheif, is numbred <hi>Leonidas,</hi> father of the moſt renowmed doctour <hi>Origen.</hi> Whoſe goodes after his death were all confiſcate, his wife and childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> amonge whom was <hi>Origen,</hi> brought to extreme beggerie. At <hi>Carthage, Perpetua,</hi> and <hi>Faelicitas</hi> were caſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to wilde beaſtes and by them torne in péeces. And manie ſutch like accidentes chaunced in other places.</p>
            <p>After this, <hi>Iulius Maximinus</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> Church of Chriſt. The ſame commaunded y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſpecially the doctours and biſſhoppes of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> Chriſtians ſhould <note place="margin">Note.</note> bée ſought out, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> thoſe w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> their ſermo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s and preachings ſeduced the ſimple peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and mooued tumults in the empire: and therefore y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> they ought to be put to death y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> peace and quie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nes might be re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtored in y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> empire, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſubiects quight diſcharged from y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> troubleſom doctrine. There were ſlaine in this perſecution very many miniſters of the congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, among who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as cheif ar numbred moſt worthy me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Pa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>philus &amp; Maximus
<pb facs="tcp:176431:37"/> Origen</hi> alſo at the ſame time to the far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther comfort of the Church, wroate a <note place="margin">Origen,</note> booke of martirdome, where hée ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth that true Chriſtians ought open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to profeſſe with their mouth, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe in their déedes, the faith which they haue receaued, and if occaſion alſo ſhal ſerue: to bear witneſſe therof with their owne blood. At the ſame time ſprange vp the froward hereſie of the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Helcheſaites</hi> hereſie.</note> 
               <hi>Helcheſaites,</hi> who taught that it was ſufficient to retaine the true faith in a mans hart and that it ſkilled not if a man were in enie daunger, to denay the ſame with his mouth: Although this doctrine doth openly repugne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the doctrine of the Goſpell and Apoſtles, as is to bée ſéene the .x. of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew,</hi> and .x. to the <hi>Rom.</hi> This perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution conteinued thrée<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> whole yéere, duringe which time there was mutch precious, and innocent blood ſhedde.</p>
            <p>Afterwarde, the yere of Chriſte 252. or accordinge to the ſupputation of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther 254. <hi>Traianus Decius</hi> the empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour perſecuted the Church yet farre more cruelly, ſending a broade through
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:176431:37"/> out all the empire moſt vehement, and bloodie edictes. And this is the twelueth perſecution of the Chriſtian Church, which diſtroyed manie excellent and worthie men. For there were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>layn in this perſecution <hi>Sixtus</hi> byſſhop of the Congregation at <hi>Rome,</hi> who was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>headed, &amp; <hi>Laurence</hi> his deacon broyled vpon a gridiron as <hi>Prude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tious</hi> writeth by whom alſo is deſcribed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> martirdom of bleſſed <hi>Hyppolitus,</hi> who was torne in ſunder by wylde horſes. <hi>Babilas</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo byſſhop of Antioche was then ſlayn, a very famous man, and a noble mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of Chriſte. This <hi>Babilas,</hi> deſiered <note place="margin">Babilas</note> that the chaine wherwith he was lead vnto execution, might bée buried with him for an ornament, and delight vnto him <hi>Serapion</hi> beinge firſt hacked with <note place="margin">seradion.</note> manie woundes and ſtabbed through, at the laſt was caſt downe headlonge from the top of his owne houſe. <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charius, Alexander &amp; Epimachus:</hi> were burnt. Manie virgins moſt ſingularly with vertues adorned were moſt mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerably tormented and at length cruely ſlayn, as <hi>Appollonia, Eugenia, Vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toria,
<pb facs="tcp:176431:38"/> Theodora, Anatholia, Ruffina</hi> and manie moe. There is extant in <hi>Euſebius</hi> in the ſixte boke of his eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticall hiſtory, the 13. chapter, the Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of <hi>Dioniſius</hi> Biſſhop of <hi>Alexandria</hi> writen vnto <hi>Fabianus</hi> of <hi>Antioche,</hi> wherein he reciteth the bleſſed Martirs which ſuffred martirdome in <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dria</hi> vnder <hi>Decius.</hi> Likewiſe in <hi>Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mannus Contractus</hi> in his cronicles, is to be found a longe Catalogue of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirs that in diuers places of the Roman Empire, ſuffred vnder <hi>Decius.</hi> In fine in this twelfe perſecution vnder <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cius,</hi> it is not able welnigh to be recited what plenty of precious and holy bloud of innocent Chriſtians was ſhed, and many notable men beſids made away.</p>
            <p>This cruell perſecution was ſcarce fully finiſhed: whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> immediatly y<hi rend="sup">•</hi>. 13. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan about y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> yere of Chriſt. 260. at com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement of the Emperour <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerianus.</hi> In whiche perſecution were beheaded two of the chief doctours of the Chriſtian church, in <hi>Italye, Cornelius</hi> biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> &amp; in <hi>Affrica, Cyprian</hi> byſhop of <hi>Carthage.</hi> There be alſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:176431:38"/> moe numbred in the cronicles, that at the ſame time receaued the crown of martirdom. At whiche time, the moſte cruel puniſhment of flawing was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly vſed againſt chriſtians, to proue if by that meanes they would bée redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced from the chriſtian to y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> Ethnick be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léefe: but it was in vaine.</p>
            <p>I cannot in this place paſſe ouer, but <note place="margin">Martirs prouoked with plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uolt.</note> I muſt make ſome bréef reherſal of ſuch thinges as are written of theſe perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions vnder <hi>Detius,</hi> and <hi>Valerius,</hi> by Sainct <hi>Ierome</hi> in the lyfe of <hi>Paule</hi> the firſte Eremite, who reporteth that the perſecutors ſtudied not onely to defile the innocencie of the chriſtians through dread, &amp; practice of ſuch puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts and torturs as y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> lyke had not bin heard be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: but alſo by prouocation of luſt and pleſure. For when they could not ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw them w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> torments, they tempted them w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> pleaſures, to cauſe them to fall, offring vnto them bewtifull wemen y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſhould allure them to lechery: In which place he ſheweth of a certen martir that bit of his toung betwene his teth, &amp; ſpet it in his fine miks face, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> he might be ſo
<pb facs="tcp:176431:39"/> deliuered from her. At the ſame time Paule the Eremit fled into the wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and liued a ſolitary life in a certen den, vnto whom beefore hée died came Saynct Antonie. And theſe twayne were the firſt beeginners of Eremites life, that is to ſay, of thoſe that lead ther liues in wilde and deſert places, as though it were out of the worlde, a life full of hardnes and ſhapnes, laboringe with their handes, and vſinge great ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinencie. <hi>Saint Ierome</hi> writeth that <hi>Antony</hi> died the yéere of Chriſte. 661. and in the .xv. yeere of his owne age. And out of this fountaine in proceſſe of time, ſprange <hi>Monkerie,</hi> which the <note place="margin">Origin all of Monkes Friers, and heremites.</note> holy Church of Chriſte knew not at all when it was moſt excellent, and pure. Béeſides that this life hath no warrant nor commaundement from the woorde of God, and is nothinge elſe but an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uention and deuiſe of men that were a fraide.</p>
            <p>And like as in thoſe former perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, they indeuored to pluck the chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians from the trueth, through alure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes of pleaſure: ſo likewiſe in our
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:176431:39"/> age many are carried awaye from the true faith and confeſſion thereof, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter knowledge of the trueth they are wrapped in errours through pleaſures honours, glory, ritches, prefermentes, gret offices, fat benefices as they terme them, or great reuenewes of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> church.</p>
            <p>The yeare of our Lorde Chriſt. 273. <hi>Valerius Aurelianus</hi> obtayned the Empire, whom Hiſtoricians make the Aucthour of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi>. ix. perſecution, which ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording vnto our accoumpt is the. 14. This <hi>Aurelianus</hi> at firſt beginnyng of his raigne, was gentle and friendly to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, but towards th'ende he changed his conditions: and through perſwaſion of naughty perſons, ſuffred himſelf to be abuſed, fully determinyng with him ſelfe to perſecute the Church of Chriſt. <hi>Euſebius</hi> teſtifieth in the 7. boke, and. 26. Chapter, of his eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call hiſtory, vnto whom alſo <hi>Oroſius</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gréeeth, that he rather intended to exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute this perſecution, then fully accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed the ſame. Howbeit the Church at that time was in great peril &amp; heaue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, but when contrary vnto expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb facs="tcp:176431:40"/> the Emperour was taken away: the perſecution ceaſed, and became no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinge.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="9" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>Of the greeuous woful</hi> and long tragicall Acte or <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution, being in number the.</hi> 15. vnder the Emperours <hi>Dioclecian</hi> and <hi>Maximian,</hi> wherein innume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Chriſtians were mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tired and ſlayne. <hi>Chapter. ix.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>NOne hath written more dillygent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Euſebius</hi> biſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarea.</hi>
               </note> of the perſecution of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours <hi>Iouius Dioclecian,</hi> and <hi>Hercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius Maximian</hi> then <hi>Euſebius</hi> in the laſte booke of his eccleſiaſticall hiſtorye. For he lyued at that time, &amp; behelde the doyng of many things whereof he wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth. Wherefore the full and true diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of theſe matters muſte be bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed of him, which although it be ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible: yet is it there withall pleaſant, &amp; profitable to be read. As for me I mean but breifly to touch y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> chiefeſt poyntes.</p>
            <p>The Chriſtian Churche enioyed
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:176431:40"/> peace and tranquillitye a fewe yéeres, from the raigne of <hi>Aurelian,</hi> vnto the xix. yéere of the raigne of <hi>Dioclecian</hi> and <hi>Maximian,</hi> about the ſpace of. 28. yéeres. For the Chriſtians had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly their Churches, and godly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations and méetinges together, profeſſing and exerciſing their relygion openly without any feare: wherein al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo they had the aſſiſtance of lieutenants of prouinces euery where, vnto whom the Chriſtian Relygion was knowne, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd many of great power in the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours Court, as namely <hi>Dortheus</hi> and <hi>Gorgonius,</hi> who being Chriſtians: aided and defended them of their owne religion. The Chriſtians alſo in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gining of this peace and quietnes agre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed very well together, were feruent in y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> worſhipping of God, and of holy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation, and therefore the number of the faithful increaced very much, ſo that it was néedefull to enlarge their Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and places of common prayer.</p>
            <p>But in proceſſe of time, that feruent <note place="margin">Abuſe of peace.</note> loue of Relygion began to waxe colde, and ther aroſe diſſentions &amp; contentions,
<pb facs="tcp:176431:41"/> cheifly amonge biſſhops and doctours, who beinge addicted to ſtrife &amp; vnquiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: fell ſore at debate amonge them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, handlynge their controuerſies, whereby the people were nothing ede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied: wherfore, the Lorde taking away his hand from his people: ſuffred y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> faith leſſe Gentiles to lay their handes vpon his Churche, to ſcoure away the ruſte which daily increaſed more and more. And this is the .xv. perſecution of the Church which <hi>Oroſius</hi> calleth y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> tenth.</p>
            <p>At the béeginning of this perſecution the Lord dealt verie gently, not giuyng the reigne and bridle immediatly to the perſecution, and ſuffringe the Churches to be deſtroyd: but the onſet of the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution was béegun by the ſouldiours. And doubtles vnto this purpoſe apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teineth that which is written by <hi>Otho Friſingenſis</hi> in the. 3. book and. 45. chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, ſpeakinge of bleaſſed <hi>Mauritius.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mauritius.</note> Who marchyng forward into <hi>Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie,</hi> vnder <hi>Maximian</hi> with his legion of men which were all Chriſtians, go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge againſt the <hi>Bacharides,</hi> whome <hi>Eutropius</hi> termeth <hi>Bongarides,</hi> a trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſome
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:176431:41"/> and ſeditious kinde of people, to bring them to dutie and quietneſſe: &amp; when the armie had paſſed the <hi>Alpes,</hi> and was arriued into the country of the <hi>Veragri,</hi> whiche at this day they cal the lower, <hi>Valleſia:</hi> there <hi>Maximian</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded his ſouldiours to ſacrifice to the Gods, that they might obtaine good fortune, and victorie againſt their enemies. Then <hi>Mauritius</hi> anſwered, that hée would not ſo doe, nor the reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dew of Chriſtians that were vnder him, franckly profeſſinge himſelf &amp; his company to be Chriſtians, for whom it was not lawful to do ſacrifice to y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> gods. Wherefore, they were firſt craftely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided, and ſome ſent to <hi>Solodoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na, Colen, Santum,</hi> and abroad vnto other places for defence ſake diſperſed. Laſt of all, the greater part of the legi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on whiche remayned with <hi>Mauritius</hi> neare vnto <hi>Octodorum,</hi> whiche is at this day called <hi>Martenacum,</hi> and <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaunum,</hi> whiche is nowe called by the name of <hi>S. Maurice:</hi> which was ſlain by y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> heathen ſouldiours. <hi>S. Ierome</hi> repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, that the expedition againſt the <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaudae,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:176431:42"/> was in the yéere of Chriſte, 290.</p>
            <p>I cannot, nor I ought not in this place <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Foelix</hi> and <hi>Regula.</hi>
               </note> let paſſe to make mencion of <hi>Foelix</hi> and <hi>Regula</hi> being <hi>Germans,</hi> who were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo of <hi>Mauricius</hi> companie: both theſe &amp; diuers other moe, whoſe ſeruice it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed God that he woulde vſe to preache Chriſt to the Gentiles: by flight eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped from the ſlaughter at <hi>Octodorum,</hi> and firſt they came to <hi>Glarona,</hi> and ſo along the Lake were brought vnto the moſt auncient citie of <hi>Zuirick,</hi> in which at y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> time y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> 
               <hi>Ethnick</hi> idolatry floriſhed, wher they preached ſimply the Chriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian relygion, and as wée haue ſhewed in the beginning of this booke, purely &amp; faithfully without any aditions of man. The ſame they approued valientlye, and at length confirmed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> their bloud. For after manie, and diuerſe torments they were ſlayn with the ſworde by <hi>Decius</hi> the <hi>Romane</hi> lieutenant that dwelte in the caſtle of <hi>zuirick.</hi> And theſe moſt holly <hi>Germans,</hi> haue left vnto vs the moſt holly and precious treaſure of the Goſpell, and Chriſtian
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:176431:42"/> fayth. Theſe our Apoſtles, or rather teachers, ſent vnto vs from heauen, are farre more auncient then y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> counſailes. Theſe liued and taught, and are bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledly departed this life, béefore the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſticall Churche was eſtablyſhed in forme and manner as it is: for at theyr time there was not that Papacie which afterwarde enſued: there were then no Images in Churches, there was no ſacryfice of Mas, no inuocatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſaints, no Munks, no inſtitutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s or fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dations of Abbeies, for they lyued in thoſe yeres after Chriſte whiche wée haue before noted, ſo that the Chriſtyan fayth hath contynued amongſt vs, and alſo the auntient Congregation of <hi>Zuirick</hi> aboue. 1270. yeares, whiche I praye God alwayes with his grace to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue.</p>
            <p>But when this loſſe whiche the Churche had ſuſtayned, and this token of the wrath of God againſt his people had mooued but fewe in the Churche to repentaunce, the more parte remay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge careleſſe and impenitent, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes procéedynge farther in theyr
<pb facs="tcp:176431:43"/> vnthankefulneſſe: God alſo increaſed the correction, ſuffryng the Churche to bée oppreſſed with a moſte ſharpe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution. For in the .xix. yéere of <hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clecian,</hi> which was the. 306. after the birth of Chriſte, in the month of March &amp; euen on Eaſter day, were publiſhed euery where edictes from y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> emperours <note place="margin">Edictes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians.</note> againſte the Chriſtians, wherin was charge giuen, that Churches and O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratories of the Chriſtians ſhoulde bée plucked downe to the grownd, the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles and all bookes of holly ſcripture burned, and whoſoeuer of the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans hée were that were in any honour office, and dignite ſhould bée diſgraded and made imfamous, with many other commaundmentes of that ſorte.</p>
            <p>Shortly after, it was commaunded by another edict from the emperours, that in euery place the byſſhops and miniſters of the Church, ſhould bée ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended and conſtrained to do ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice to the Gods, &amp; if anie ſpake againſt it: they ſhould be enforced therto, or ſlaine. Héerevpon enſued a miſerable and cruell ſlaughter. For the chriſtian
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:176431:43"/> byſhops, doctours, and miniſters of the Churches, were thicke and thréefolde led and drawn to the temples of Idols to do ſacrifice: and manie times thoſe that lead them mooued with certein compaſſion: exhorted them whom they lead, to holde their peace, and if they woulde but diſſemble as though they dyd ſacrifice: they woulde then lette them departe. But they declared with a loude voyce, that they neither had Sacrificed, neither woulde Sacrifice, but that they were the ſeruantes and miniſters of Chriſte, wherfore vnac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed and new tormentes, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe tortures and puniſhments were laid vpon the Chriſtians, in execution wherof: the tormenters and officers were more wery in appliyng, then the Chriſtians in ſuffringe them. For they through thée goodnes of God, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinnued conſtant in the Chriſtian faith vnto death: notwithſtandinge certen, through feare and greatnes of paine and torment: renounced their faith, to the wounderfull ſorowe and greif all the godlie.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:176431:44"/>
            <p>At <hi>Nicomedia</hi> in <hi>Bythynia,</hi> when <note place="margin">Done at <hi>Nicodemus.</hi>
               </note> the emperours commaundement and proclamation was openly ſet abroade and both emperours at that preſent ſoiurned at <hi>Nicomedia,</hi> a certen noble citizen and of great dignitie in that city rent downe the emperours edict and tore it all to péeces, wherfore with out delaye hée was brought vnto the empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours. Who after that hée had confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed that hée was a Chriſtian, and that whiche hée had doone hée did it on a fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent zeale: hée was deliuered vnto the hangemen and Iurmagantes, who tormented him with ſundrie torments vntill hée died. But amonge the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragious tormentes wherewith they martyred him, there neuer appéered any one ſygne of ſorrowe in his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenaunce.</p>
            <p>At the ſame tyme were tormented and ſlayne the chéeife Prynces and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles of the Emperours houſeholde, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monge whom <hi>Peter</hi> after ſundrie vex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ations and tortures, was layde vpon a Gridyron, and roaſted, with this moſte cruell kynde of deathe, endynge
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:176431:44"/> his lyfe. Lykewyſe <hi>Dorotheus,</hi> and <hi>Gorgonius,</hi> Gentilmen of the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours Chamber, after the bitter taſte of ſundrie tormentes: were laſte of all hanged.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anthimus</hi> alſo byſſhop of <hi>Nicomedia</hi> was at that time ſlayne with the ſword and with him a great numbre of city<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens, as ſhéepe followynge their ſheap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard through tormentes and death, with a moſt conſtant faith.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Nicomedia</hi> at that time, there a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſe <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Nicomedia</hi> the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace burned.</note> a great fire ſuddeinly within the kinges palace, as who ſhould ſay that God ment to puniſhe the extreame crueltie of the emperours and the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then people which had burned, and broi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led ſo manie innocent, and godlie men. But the ſame chaunced which befell at <hi>Rome</hi> in the time of <hi>Nero,</hi> for like as hée imputed the cauſe of burninge the citie vnto the giltleſſe Chriſtians, bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge cauſe therof himſelfe: ſo theſe em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours publiſhed new commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, wherby they ſtrayghtly char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> the Chriſtians ſhould bée extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> fier, &amp; ſword in euery place.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:176431:45"/>
            <p>In <hi>Syria</hi> likewiſe, the faithfull Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours, <note place="margin">Perſecuci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in <hi>siria.</hi>
               </note> noble and vnnoble, men and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, younge and ould, were drawen by heapes into priſon, in ſo mutch that the priſons and common places of the citie were full of priſoners, and but few men there were that walked abroade, the place reſemblyng the ſhew of a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorne wilderneſſe. Wherof when the Emperours were aduertiſed: they willed that ſutche as would do ſacrifice to the gods ſhould bée releaſed, the reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dew that continued in the chriſtian bée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léefe, ſhould bée put to death with moſte cruell kindes of tormentes.</p>
            <p>The people of <hi>Tyrus</hi> alſo, in the land <note place="margin">In <hi>Tyrus.</hi>
               </note> of <hi>Paleſtine,</hi> whole flockes as it were of men and women, in places of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon reſorte for ſhewes, were thrown vnto wylde beaſtes, and when the wild beaſtes were more gentyl towards the Chriſtians then the men, neither forced vpon them to teare them, yea, rather teare their kéepers and maiſters that egged them to others: notwithſtanding theſe faithleſſe tyrants crueller then all beaſtes, ranne vpon the miſerable chriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:176431:45"/> woundyng them, ſtabbyng them and cruelly without all pittie murther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng them.</p>
            <p>A ſtrainge kynde of crueltye alſo the vngodly in <hi>Egipt,</hi> and <hi>Thebais,</hi> practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed againſt the faithfull, wherwith they <note place="margin">In <hi>Egipe.</hi>
               </note> ſlew infinite numbers of them. They vſed in certayne places to bend downe two Trées, and to bynde the faithfull vnto eche trée by the legge, then to let them riſe agayne, and ſo tearyng the men in péeces. And <hi>Vſpurgenſis</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porteth, how at the ſame time, in one monethes ſpace were ſeuentéene thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand men martyred, and ſlayne.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Euſebius</hi> in the. 9. and. 10. Chapters of the, 8. booke, deſcribeth the ſtrange tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and puniſhments of many chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians which he himſelfe dyd beholde a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monge whom he mentioneth one <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leas</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Phileas.</note> a worthy man, who was a Martir himſelfe, and had wroten of Martirs.</p>
            <p>There was alſo in <hi>Phrigia</hi> a certen famous Citie, wherein all the people, <note place="margin">A wofull deede.</note> higheſt and loweſt, young and old, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed the Chriſtian faith. The ſame Citie the Emperours army beſeidged
<pb facs="tcp:176431:46"/> round about, and ſet it on fire, burninge therin all that euer was, as well men as goodes, that there was not one that eſcaped Beſides there are many other cruell tortures, and puniſhmentes reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſame boke of <hi>Euſebius,</hi> wherby infinit multitudes of chriſtians wer ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecuted to death, &amp; made away in <hi>Arabia Cappadocia, Meſopotamia, Alexa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dria Antioche,</hi> and lykewiſe in <hi>Pontus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But after that theſe bloudthirſtie dogges, <hi>Dioclecianus,</hi> and <hi>Maximianꝰ</hi> departed from the empire, there ſuccée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in their place other tyrantes, <hi>max<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entius</hi> ſunne to <hi>Maximian, &amp; Galerius Maximinus</hi> who perſecuted the church noleſſe cruelly then theyr prediceſſours did, neither made they any ende, or mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, or meaſure of puniſhing, ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge <note place="margin">Dorothea,</note> or ſheadinge of blood. <hi>At Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dria,</hi> a noble &amp; honeſt virgin. <hi>Dorothe,</hi> was by <hi>Maximinus</hi> ſpoyled of all her goods &amp; with other virgines alſo whiche would not conſent to his filthie luſt: tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented, and ſlayne. At <hi>Rome, Sophro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia</hi> wife to the gouerner of the cittie choſe rather to die with her owne hand <note place="margin">Sophronia.</note>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:176431:46"/> then to bée defiled by a beaſtly tirant.</p>
            <p>By this Tyrant very many chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans were driuen into exyle, puniſhed, and ſlayne as <hi>Euſebius</hi> copiouſly decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth in thenéeinth and laſt booke of his ſtorie. Howbeeit the moſte famous a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them all are thrée miniſters of Chriſte, and his Churche: <hi>Syluanus</hi> of <hi>Tyre, Peter</hi> of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> and <hi>Lucia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> 
               <note place="margin">siluanus. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>etrus. Lucianus.</note> of <hi>Antioche,</hi> who had traueiled very mutch in the ſcriptures, as <hi>S. Ierom</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porteth. Theſe woorthie men, not only by their teachinge and writinge: but alſo by their bloud and death haue borne teſtimony to y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> chriſtian faith, and haue cleaued vnto chriſt conſtantly to death.</p>
            <p>This cruell and rare kinde of perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, continued from the yeere of Chriſte. 306 vnto the yere. 320. that is to ſay about .xv. yéere in the whole. For in the yeere of Chriſte. 321. <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinus</hi> the emperour in the .x. yéere of his reigne, gaue peace and reſt to the miſerable, torne, and almoſt oppreſſed Church: &amp; indéede, from the time that Chriſte ſuffred his paſſion vnto that preſent: there was no perſecution more
<pb facs="tcp:176431:47"/> cruell, or that continued longer then this, wherin notwithſtandinge the Church through faith preueiled, ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>threw, and caſte downe al falſe religion and Idolatrie.</p>
            <p>But that I may returne vnto the accuſtomed talke whiche I haue vſed <note place="margin">Chriſtian Relygion.</note> before this, in the diſcourſe of moſt perſecutions, is there anie man I bée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſéech you, which dareth avoutch that the Ethnick religion of the <hi>Romanes,</hi> was therefore iuſt and true, bycauſe the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane</hi> emperours defended and enlar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged the ſame, caſtinge downe, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filinge the faith of the Chriſtians with their owne blood moſt cruelly, &amp; bicauſe the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> obtained proſperus ſucceſſe againſt the Chriſtians, the Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s the mean ſeaſon taſtinge none other but the croſſe afflictions, miſeries, and moſt cruell death? And who is hée now, that will diſpute with God, why hée ſuffred ſutch naughtie knaues, and wicked varlets with ſo many and diuerſe kyndes of ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamities, moleſt and trouble ſutch men as were dearely beloued vnto him? Who will de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aunde whether hée did
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:176431:47"/> well or ill, ſince God doth no vniuſte thing? But hée proueth his ſeruantes with the croſſe and afflictions, like as Gold and Siluer are by woorkmen tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the fier. This the faithfull know very well, and therfore if our wretched and impatient fleaſh do mooue any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary thoughtes (as it often chanceth:) immediatly they ſuppreſſe them. And <hi>Saint Peter</hi> ſaith: <hi>humble your ſelues</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2. Pet. 4.</note> 
               <hi>vnto the mightie hand of god, and hee will exalt you when hee ſeeth his time and caſt all your cares vpon him for it is hee that is carefull for you.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="10" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ <hi>Of the. 16. Tragicall</hi> Acte or perſecution, vnder <hi>Iulian the Emperour, &amp; of the</hi> 17. vnder the Emperour <hi>Valens,</hi> alſo of the. 18. vnder <hi>Genſerick</hi> and <hi>Hunerick,</hi> Kinges of the <hi>Vandales. Chapter. X.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>FRom the tenth yéere of the reigne of <hi>Conſtantinus Magnus,</hi> the church of Chriſte enioyed peace and tranquillity, when as within xxi. yéeres (for ſo many
<pb facs="tcp:176431:48"/> yéeres are accoumpted from the tenth yéere of <hi>Conſtantine</hi> vnto the. 31. which was the laſt yere of his reigne) it encrea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed more then at any other time ſince the natiuitie of Chriſte.</p>
            <p>But not longe after the death of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Abuſe of peace.</note> the learned teachers, and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of the Churches, vnthankfully abuſed their peace, minglynge many contentions, and cauilles with y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſimple doctrine of their religion, and mutch diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agréeinge, and contendinge amonge themſelues: they drew the ſimple peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple from the vnitie of the Church into ſundry ſectes, and pluckyng them from the pureneſſe and plaineſſe of the true faith, with their doubtfull doctrine: they filled their heades with ſundrie alterca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. At which time ſprange vp the blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemous <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Arrius</hi> here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſye.</note> doctrine of <hi>Arrius,</hi> who affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med that our Lorde Ieſus Chriſte the ſunne of God was not of one eſſency or béeinge with the father, nether very, and eternall God. With this poyſon at that time, <hi>Conſtantius</hi> one of <hi>Conſtantinus</hi> ſunnes, was infected, for <hi>Couſtantinus</hi> left béehind him thrée ſunnes, béetwéen whom he deuided the empire: <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinus</hi>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:176431:48"/> the ſecond: <hi>Conſtantius,</hi> &amp; <hi>Conſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s</hi> This <hi>Conſtantius</hi> was offended w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the true &amp; faithfull miniſters of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> Churches which withſtood the doctrine of <hi>Arrius,</hi> and ſent them into exile. But he perſecu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted moſt veheme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly Bleſied <hi>Athanaſius</hi> and with him many m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, wherof ſome he <note place="margin">Athanaſius.</note> threw into moſt ſtrait priſons, greuouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly afflicting the faithful, as is declared at large in the eccleſiaſticall hiſtory. This perſecution béegan aboute the yéere of Chriſt: 343. but bicauſe <hi>valens</hi> y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, who was alſo difiled w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the heréſie of <hi>Arrius</hi> renued this perſecution: wée will atribute them both to the <hi>Arrians</hi> comprehendinge them vnder the name of <hi>Valens</hi> perſecution.</p>
            <p>God chaſtiſed his Church for conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, falling out, diſagréements, &amp; ſciſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, not only in this Arrian perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but alſo in an Ethnick the like wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>of it ſuffred many before the reigne of <hi>Conſtantinus,</hi> as wée haue hether to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared. For the emperour <hi>Iulian</hi> oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed himſelf ſharply againſt the Church of Chriſte, laboring to bring it back vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the aun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ient ſuperſtitions of the gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, about the yéere of Chriſt 366.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:176431:49"/>
            <p>This <hi>Iulian</hi> was at the firſt a Chriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian, and a reader in the holy Catholick <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iulians</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoltyng.</note> Church, but when he had falne into ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance and frindſhip with certayne Philoſophers, and chiefly with <hi>Liba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</hi> the Sophiſt: he began by litle and litle to fall from the Chriſtian faith, and at laſt receiued the relygion of the <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles</hi> againe, wherin he became ſo blind and hard harted: that he waſhed awaye the Baptiſme of Chriſt: yea he was ſo farre poſſeſſed by the Diuell, that he v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed very much Magicall arts, applying his whole ſtudye vnto ſutch thinges as were pleſant, &amp; exceptable to the diuell.</p>
            <p>But after that he came to the empire, hauing obtained a great victorie againſt the <hi>Almaynes</hi> nigh to the citie <hi>Strauſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brough</hi> of whom he ſlew. xxx. M: with all his power hée bent him ſelfe againſt the chriſtian religion. The temples of Idoles which <hi>Conſtantinus</hi> had ſhutte vp, and in which vpon paine of death he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded that none ſhould do ſacrifice: <hi>Iulian</hi> ſet them open agayne, and ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficed in them vnto Idols, and gaue all men leaue to ſacrifice. So y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:176431:49"/> religion and Idolatrie verie mutch increaſed vnder him: and ſutch <note place="margin">Gentiliſme encreaſed.</note> as in the time of <hi>Conſtantinus</hi> had hid themſelues, hopyng that ſhortly there would come ſoome change: brake then abroade into light, and violently aſſaul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Chriſtians. The emperour him ſelfe, ſpoyled the Churches, and the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of the Churches, of all their priuiledges, immunities, liberties, and dignities, which <hi>Conſtantinus</hi> had gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen them. Hée forbid alſo the Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s all ſchooles, that they ſhould not learne poetrie, oratorie, nor philoſophie: mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninge therby to make them vnlearned, that they ſhould not bée able to confute the Ethnick relygion, out of the booke of Ethnick writers. Himſelf alſo wroat certen bookes againſt the Chriſtian re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, wherto verie well anſwered. <hi>S. Syrillus,</hi> byſhop of <hi>Alexandria.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Moreouer, he termed Chriſtians diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daynfully <note place="margin">Chriſtians termed Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lileans.</note> 
               <hi>Galileans,</hi> and Chriſt himſelf the <hi>Galilean.</hi> He dyd not only confiſcate the goods of the Church: but alſo layde great tributes, and exactions vpon the chriſtians: there withall alſo mockyng,
<pb facs="tcp:176431:50"/> and floutyng them ſaying, that theyr God, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> is to ſay our Lord Ieſus Chriſt forbid them to heape vp treaſure, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundyng them that whoſo tooke from them their coate: they ſhould giue hym their cloak alſo. So y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> he both ſpoyled, &amp; flouted the Chriſtians, and whatſoeuer trouble or reproche hée put them vnto he ſayd how they ought to beare it wyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyngly and patiently, for ſo their Chriſt taught them to doe.</p>
            <p>And lyke as <hi>Conſtantinus</hi> the great, tooke away the Images of the Gentile <note place="margin">The Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged.</note> Gods out of the Romane enſigne or ſtandard, placynge in the ſtead of them a white croſſe: ſo contrarywiſe <hi>Iulianus</hi> reſtored the Images of <hi>Iupiter, Mercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie,</hi> and <hi>Mars,</hi> that the Chriſtians wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping th'enſigne, and bowing them ſelues before it, ſhoulde ſéeme to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip the Gods. Likewiſe all that were appoyncted to warfarre, and receiued their natiue or rewarde, muſt caſte a grayne of frankincenſe into the fire vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the Aulter, and ſo worſhippe the Gods.</p>
            <p>This thing troubled hym very much <note place="margin">A francke confeſſion.</note>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:176431:50"/> For when certen Chriſtian ſouldiours had vnaduiſedly done the ſame, &amp; way<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng the matter more dyllygently, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceued what they had done: of their owne motion they came vnto the Emperour, and caſting away their donatiue in his preſence, cryed aloude ſaying that they were Chriſtians, and woulde continew in the Chriſtian fayth, that whiche they had done they dyd it vnaduiſedlye, wherein they had gréeuouſlye offended, wherefore they preſented there theyr bodies vnto hym that they might ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer for that, wherein their handes had offended. Then the Emperour com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded that they ſhoulde all bée lead away to execution, &amp; bée beheaded. But when they were gone out of his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence: he chaunged his minde, &amp; pardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned their liues: notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding he made a law, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> thencefoorth no chriſtian ſhould bée admitted to warfare, or into y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours court, or vnto any be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ch of iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or any other kind of preferment.</p>
            <p>In euery place alſo of the Roman em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, Chriſtians were reprochefullye dealte withall, pitifullye tormented
<pb facs="tcp:176431:51"/> and ſlaine, amongſt whom is reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bred an antient man, and a notable miniſter of Chriſt, <hi>Marcus</hi> byſſhop of <hi>Artehuſa.</hi> The ſame in former, and more happie times, had deſtroied y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> temple of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> gods at <hi>Arethuſa,</hi> by reaſon whereof <hi>Iulian</hi> hated him, perſuading w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the citizens y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> they ſhould conſtrain him to build vp the temple againe, which béeing impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for him to do: they required that at the leaſt wiſe he would contribute ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what to the charges. But when he had anſwered that hée would not giue them the valew of one farthinge: hée was by them moſt miſerably, and cruelly, and <note place="margin">Although he were ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ritche.</note> to their great ſhame tormented, and put to death.</p>
            <p>Likewiſe renownied men, and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie miniſters of Chriſte were marty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, as <hi>Gregorie</hi> of <hi>Alexandria, Euſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bius, Nectarius, Zenon, Baſilius Ancy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranus,</hi> and <hi>Cyrillus</hi> Deacon of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> church of Ieruſalem. At <hi>Heliopolis</hi> manie vertuous virgins were brought naked into the Theater, and afterwarde their bellies cut vp and ſtuffed full of oates and barly, and caſt to ſwine to bée torne.</p>
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:176431:51"/>
            <p>In <hi>Meroe</hi> a citie of <hi>Phrygia,</hi> thrée honeſt citizens, <hi>Macedonius, Theodu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus, &amp; Tacianus,</hi> when as the day before, the cheif officer of the citie had ſet open a temple of Idols, whiche had vntyll that time bin ſhutte vp, to th'eintent there ſhould now be ſacrifice done in it, in the night entring into it they plucked down the Idoles, and brake them. But when this iudge and chief officer <hi>Amatius</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to haue tormented ſundry Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans whereby hée might come to know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge who had broken the Idols: theſe thrée comming vnto the iudge, deſired him not to torment any man for brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng the Idols, for they were the doers of it. Wherefore they were taken and roſted a great while, &amp; at length burnt. In the ſame perſecution <hi>Artemius</hi> lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant of egipt, bicauſe he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtantly pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>feſſed y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> faith of Chriſt: was ſpoyled of al his goods, &amp; in the end loſt his head: y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> like wherof many good, and honeſt men ſuffred. whoſo deſireth a more large de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of theſe things: let him read y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> 6. booke of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> Tripartite hiſtory, alſo the hiſtories of <hi>Ruffi. Theodo.</hi> and <hi>Sozo.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:176431:52"/> Moreouer, <hi>Iulianus</hi> to y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t he might <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iulian</hi> ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the <hi>Iewes</hi> build the Temple at <hi>Ieruſalem.</hi>
               </note> moleſt the Chriſtans, whom hée could not compell to the Gentiles religion: he gaue licence to the miſerable Iewes, to returne to Ieruſalem, there to aſſemble themſelues togither and to build a tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and to frequent their ſacrifice, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſinge vnto them his aſiſtance for the better accompliſhinge the ſame. But after that a great multitude of them was gathered togither out of al nations and had prepared ſtuf for their preſent buſines, erected ſcaffoldes to woork vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and partly had digged their foundations and partly layd them, being buſie about their buildinge: béeholde, a great earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake ſhooke the foundations, and caſt them downe: there flamed alſo an hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible fier out of the verie foundations, and a ſtrange and terrible tempeſt ouer threwe the ſcaffoldes, ſhakinge downe what euer they had builded, and ſlew a great multitude of the Iewes. There was alſo a terrible boule of fier tu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bling there about all the day longe, whiche hindred and indamaged them verye mutch: and wheras béefore the Iewes,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:176431:52"/> and Gentiles triumphed, inſulted ouer, and threatned the Chriſtians, <hi>Cyrillus</hi> biſhop of Ieruſalem, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> great grauity &amp; conſtancie forewarned them out of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niell</hi> the prophet and the Goſpell, that it <note place="margin">Dan. 9. Mat. 24. Luk. 21.</note> was not poſſible y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> they ſhould ſacrifice héere, or elſe build vp y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> Iewiſh temple. So y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> they, which before this diſperſion or ſcattryng, had in deriſion y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> miniſter of chriſte: after ſo great miracles of god were altogether quailed &amp; diſcouraged.</p>
            <p>But after y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> 
               <hi>Iulian</hi> was ſlayn in battel agaynſt the <hi>Perſians,</hi> which was in the yéere of chriſt. 367. there was quietnes agayne reſtored to y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> Chriſtians, which notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinued not long. For <hi>Valens,</hi> w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his brother <hi>Valentinian,</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>taining th'empire: was ſeduced by the <hi>Arrians:</hi> &amp; although his brother <hi>Vale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian</hi> were ſound in the Chriſtian faith, yet hée neuertheleſſe about the yéere of thriſte. 371 began to perſecute the godly chriſtians, intending to bring them to y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> 
               <hi>Arrian</hi> hereſy. But y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> church conſtantly withſtoode him, wherfore the faithfull and Catholicke biſhops, were by him ſent into baniſhment, and many of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tormented and finally ſlayne.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:176431:53"/>
            <p>Since therfore at that time, there reig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ſuch tirranny in euery place, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> miniſters of the churches &amp; other faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full men, were nowher in ſalftye, but were commonly reprochefully intreted ſpoyled, plucked out of their houſes and ſtayne: at length the Church decréed to ſend ſome notable embaſſedge vnto the Emperour, complaynyng of their iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and requiryng his maieſties cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency, helpe, and protection. To which purpoſe were ſent. 80. of the chiefeſt, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> their countinaunce, and credit might be the greater. Who when they were com to <hi>Nicomedia</hi> to the Emperour, &amp; had exhibited their ſupplication: the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour was greuouſly mooued againſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> yet diſſemblyng his anger, charged pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uely <hi>Modeſtus</hi> one of his ſeruants that he ſhould deſtroy al thoſe byſhops. But becauſe hée doubted, leſt if they ſhoulde be openly executed, the people might chance to raiſe a tumult: they were all imbarked in a Ship, as yf they ſhoulde be ſent into baniſhment. And when the Ship was come into the mideſt of the déepe ſea: the mariners ſetting it on fler
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:176431:53"/> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues eſcaped away in boates thus in one Ship were. 80. holy ſeruants of<note place="margin">80 Legats miſerably brent.</note> God conſumed with fire. Which moſt cruell tragedie and impious fact, ſtroak the Church of God into moſt greuous, ſorowe and heauineſſe.</p>
            <p>But who ſo is delighted to vnderſtand the moſt firce Barbarouſnes, and moſt outragious tragedies, &amp; heinous mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, which haue bin co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted againſt the holy faithfull of Chriſt: let him read the. 7, booke of the Tripartite hiſtorye, and the fourth of <hi>Socrates,</hi> and <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doretus,</hi> where theſe thinges are ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foorth at large. I omitte in this place to ſet out the perſecution of <hi>Athanaricus</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Athanaricus</hi> King of the <hi>Gothes.</hi>
               </note> King of the <hi>Gothes,</hi> whome others call <hi>Athalaricus.</hi> Hée perſecuted the Chriſtians about the yéere of Chriſte, 373. whereof ſome he flewe, ſome hée baniſhed. But becauſe ſome reporte, that they whiche ſuffred theſe thinges were <hi>Arrians:</hi> therefore I thought it not conuenient to recken this among the perſecutions of the holye Catholick Churche.</p>
            <p>Howbeit after that the <hi>Vandales</hi> had
<pb facs="tcp:176431:54"/> poſſeſſed <hi>Affrica</hi> driuyng the Romans thence, about the yéere of Chriſt. 443. being then peace throughout all the em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyre: <hi>Genſerick</hi> King of <hi>Vandales</hi> and Lord of <hi>Affrica,</hi> being infected with the<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Genſerick</hi> King of the <hi>vandals.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Arrian</hi> hereſie, as were <hi>Conſtantinus,</hi> and <hi>Valens</hi> the Emperours, intended to enforce the chriſtians to the <hi>Arrian</hi> he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie, whervpon there began a bloudy, and butcherly ſlaughter. For he ſhut vp the Churches of the faithful, and ſpoiled the Miniſters, whereof many hée killed with hunger, and to be ſhort: he left no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing vndone whatſoeuer before him <hi>Dioclecian,</hi> and <hi>Maximian</hi> the moſt cruell tyrants, had practized againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faithfull. Whom notwithſtanding hée could not enforce to reuoult, for all their moſt greuous, and cruell puniſhments.</p>
            <p>After <hi>Genſerick,</hi> there ſuccéeded him both in his kingdome and tyrrannie, his ſunne <hi>Honorius,</hi> in the yéere of Chriſte, 476. who perſecuted alſo the Chriſtians moſt cruelly for the profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the trew faith. The whole ſtorie of this perſecution is deſcribed by <hi>Vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor</hi> byſſhop of <hi>vtica,</hi> which liued in thoſe
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:176431:54"/> bloody times. After <hi>Honoricus,</hi> there ſucccded in the kingdome <hi>Gundamun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus,</hi> in the yéere of Chriſte, 484. who likewiſe as his prediceſſours did: perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted the Chriſtians. The like after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward<note place="margin">To whome <hi>Fulgentius wroat.</hi>
               </note> alſo did <hi>Traſimundus</hi> the yéere of Chriſte. 503. by whom were at one time. 220. byſſhoppes baniſhed into <hi>Sardinia:</hi> but <hi>Hildericus</hi> ſunne to <hi>Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimundus,</hi> recallinge them home again out of exile, reſtored them to their chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches in the yeere of Chriſte. 523. This <hi>Hildericus</hi> was a good prince, &amp; ſound in the Chriſtian religion, but in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> yéere of Chriſte. 530. he was by <hi>Gilimer</hi> take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by a trayn and caſt into priſon, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prochefully vſed. Howbeit <hi>Gilimer</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyed the crowne not longe, but was by <hi>Belliſarius</hi> (as <hi>Procopius</hi> reporteth) a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the yéere of Chriſte. 535. van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſhed and ſtain, with whom the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of <hi>Vandales</hi> alſo toke his ende. This perſecution vnder the <hi>Vandales</hi> continued in <hi>Affrica</hi> about fouerſcore yéeres.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="11" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:176431:55"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Of the 19. Tragical acte</hi> or perſecution which was the <hi>longeſt, and moſt greeuous of all</hi> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vnder <hi>Machomet,</hi> which the <hi>Sarra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cens</hi> and <hi>Turkes</hi> haue mantayned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt the Churche of Chriſte. <hi>Chapter. xi.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>BY meanes of theſe perſecutions, which wée haue heatherto declared which are to bée accoumpted as certen Chaſtiſement, and corrections of God, few in the Church were brought to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny repentance or amendment, but ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny became rather the worſe: for ſundry hereſies and ſchiſmes, as namely of the <hi>Macedonians, Neſtorians, Pelagians</hi> with diuerſe other aroſe, increaſinge more and more, the recitall whereof were now to tedious: by occaſion wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>of gréeuous contentions, troubles, and diſagréement fell out not only amongſt the learned: but alſo amongſt the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon people and the vnlearned ſort, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinge occaſion of great and outra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious diuiſions in religion ouer all the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:176431:55"/> Eaſt. Béeſides, in the weſt the byſſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> wickedly aduaunced himſelf and his Church aboue al Churches and miniſters of Churches throughout all Chriſtianitie, and that expreſly againſt the holy doctrine of the Goſpell, and the writinges of <hi>Gregory</hi> the pope. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore while matters continued in this ſtate, God ſuffred his Churche to bee touched with moſt ſharpe troubles, and oppreſſed with greeuous perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
            <p>For in the yéere of Chriſte. 613. was<note place="margin">The begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the falſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Macho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met.</hi>
               </note> firſt knowne, and béecame famous in <hi>Arabia</hi> the wicked hypocrite, and moſt craftie verlet <hi>Machomet,</hi> whom ſome terme <hi>Muhammat:</hi> the ſame from his youth vpward was a merchant, but af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward hée boaſted that he was a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet ſent from God. There had ioyned themſelues vnto him certen wicked and ſtubberne Iewes, and alſo one <hi>Sergius</hi> a munke, an apoſtata and an heretick: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i whoſe aduice and ayd, he deuiſed a new lawe, which hée called <hi>Alcoranus,</hi> for<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Alcoran</hi> what it ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifieth.</note> this woord <hi>Alcoran</hi> ſignifieth a mingle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mangle of lawes. In whiche hee erred
<pb facs="tcp:176431:56"/> directly from the ſcriptures of both teſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tamentes, wherin are ſet downe the true lawes preſcribed by God, béeſide whom wée haue no néede of anye other booke of lawes: howbeit <hi>Machomet</hi> hath ſet foorth a new and peculiar lawe to his <hi>Sarracens, Turkes,</hi> and all that ſhall hereafter béeléeue in him, which law of his, is in very déede a miſerable feined deuiſe, impure, falſe, and full of filthy fables, that it was great meruell how wiſe men could giue credite to ſuch abſurde, and doubtfull trifles. Howbeit therin appeareth the dreadfull wrath of God againſt al ſuch as ar not contented w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the doctrine of Chriſt, &amp; the holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures: for it followeth deſeruedly, that al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> are not contented w<hi rend="sup">e</hi> the truth to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léeue<note place="margin">Iohn. 9. 2. Theſ. 21.</note> it, afterward they giue credit vnto lies, &amp; ar ſhamefully deceued, &amp; ſeduced.</p>
            <p>In this his law, <hi>Machomet</hi> the diuel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh and falſe prophet, hath inſtituted,<note place="margin">The whole ſumme of the turkiſhe religion. God.</note> and diuiſed a new religion, altogither repugnant to the faith of Chriſt. He ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ther is one God maker of heauen and earth whom onlie we muſt adore and call vpon, and that wée muſt not worſhip or honour any other
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:176431:56"/> Gods, Idols, or Images, whiche the <hi>Sarracens</hi> and <hi>Turkes</hi> doo hate excée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly. But hée doth not acknowledge according to the effect of the holly ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, the diffrence of the perſons in one and indiuiſible ſubſtance of Godhoode, the Father, the Sunne and the Hollye ghoſt, but hée impugneth, and raileth at<note place="margin">Chriſte.</note> the bleſſed Trinitie. Likewiſe, hée con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth that Chriſt was a great prophet borne of the holy and vndefiled virgin, who was taken alſo vp into heauen, but as for that poynct which is peculiar to the true and liuelye faith: hee doth not confeſſe that Ieſus Chriſte is the euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtinge ſunne of God, very God and man, the only mediatour of God and men who being crucified &amp; ſlayne for our ſake, aroſe again from y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> dead, &amp; ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth on y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> right hand of god, being of one power w<hi rend="sup">e</hi> the father in heauen. Theſe things he blaſphemeth and impugneth deneing y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> chriſt was crucified where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he teacheth alſo erroniouſly touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing remiſſion of ſins, which onli we ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine by faith in chriſt which was cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied,<note place="margin">Remiſſion of ſinnes.</note> ye he is altogether ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of faith &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:176431:57"/> iuſtification by faith in Chriſt, deuiſing<note place="margin">Faith and iuſtification</note> ſundrie woorſhippinges and meanes to attayne ſaluation, namely by faſtinge praying, giuinge of almes, ſuſtaininge many &amp; great labours, ſuffring mutch trouble, valientlye fightinge for the <hi>Machometan</hi> religion, and dyinge in batteill. Hée is alſo of opinion that a man may fulfill the law, and demerite ſaluation by his owne woorkes: hée<note place="margin">Workes.</note> hath his Moonkes &amp; Prieſtes, in whoſe merites hée repoſeth the hope of his ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation. Hée confeſſeth the reſurrec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion<note place="margin">Eternall lyfe.</note> of the bodie, but hée ſpeaketh alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether carnally and impurely of felici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, as though in Paradiſe wée ſhoulde enioye bodely pleaſures, meat, drincke, beutie of the body, as if it were in the bleſſed Ilands called <hi>Beatorum inſulae,</hi> or elſe in a certein <hi>Vtopia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hée deſpiſeth the Euangelicall and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolicall<note place="margin">Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, rites, and Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes.</note> doctrine, as hée doth alſo our holly aſſembles and congregations, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundynge all that béeléeue in him to bee circumciſed after the Iewiſh ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, nothyng regarding our Baptiſme: hée raueth and rayleth at the ſacrament
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:176431:57"/> of the body and bloud of Chriſt, and al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fourme and ordre of the Lordes ſupper which was inſtituted and appointed by Chriſte: hée contemneth all chriſtian v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedges, and hath inſtituted peculiar con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations, temples, rightes, and cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies: hée commandeth the ſixt day of the wéeke, which we cal Friday, to bée<note place="margin">Holydayes.</note> kept holiday: he apointed faſting daies &amp; purging with water: hée commaunded them to pray fiue times in a day: he for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid<note place="margin">Prayers</note> to pray vnto ſaincts &amp; creatures, but vnto God only, which is trueth in déed: but hée teacheth to pray vnto others be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide Chriſte. Sutch praiers are not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable vnto God, bicauſe they are not made through Chriſte, through whom wée pray vnto God our father in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen,<note place="margin">1. Iohn. 2.</note> wherat hée mocketh. But S. Iohn ſaith: <hi>Who ſo hath not the Sun, hath</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matrymo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uorcement.</note> 
               <hi>not the Father:</hi> Hée altogether propha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth holly matrimonie: for vnto men hée giueth licence to marie as many wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues as they liſte, and that which is iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and diſhoneſt, to forſake them w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out cauſe at their pleaſure, and diſcretio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Hée forbiddeth them after the Iewiſh
<pb facs="tcp:176431:58"/> maner to eate ſwynes fleaſh, hée debar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth them alſo from wine, howbeit the ritcher ſort haue deuiſed certen coſtlye kinds of drinks, wherby they beco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe drunk then w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wine. And this is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> doctrine of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> diuell, wherof <hi>Paul</hi> intrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth in the firſt of <hi>Timothy,</hi> the. 4. chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. And whatſoeuer I haue ſayd of the <hi>Machometan</hi> faith: the ſame ar al to be vnderſtood of the Turkiſhe religion or ſuperſticion, which at this day is vſuall among the <hi>Turkes.</hi> And as for theſe thinges, I haue reported them verye bréeflye, that thoſe that knowe not the Turkiſh religion: may haue a brief ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract, not of the whole relygion: but of the chiefeſt poynts, and opinions therof.<note place="margin">The wrath of God.</note> Now through indifferent view of theſe things which we haue recited: who doth not vnderſtande that through the moſte gréeuous yet moſt iuſte wrath of God, the world is by him moſt ſharply puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, ſince y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> he hath ſuffred ſo abſurde, filthy, &amp; wicked relygion to take place? and here withall, let vs alſo beholde and weigh, what a cruell and continuall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution which indureth alſo to this day,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:176431:58"/> this impiou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and <hi>Machometan</hi> faith hath raiſed againſte the holly Church of Chriſte, and the true faith.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Machomet</hi> that falſe prophet and<note place="margin">What the <hi>Sarracens</hi> were.</note> murdrous ſeductour of the worlde, had perſuaded his <hi>Sarracens,</hi> that they are the true children &amp; heiers of <hi>sarra</hi> wife to <hi>Abraham,</hi> and that in reſpect therof: béelonged vnto them all the promiſes made vnto <hi>Abraham,</hi> namely that his ſéede ſhould rule all the world, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hée exhorted the <hi>Sarracens</hi> that ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng weapon in hand, they ſhould valy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently aſſay to poſſeſſe al the kingdoms of the world as their owne inheritaunce.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Sarracens</hi> were a barbarus and rough people of <hi>Arabia,</hi> whiche before that time were called <hi>Agareni,</hi> the ſame receauinge ſtipende of the Romanes, fought vnder them in the warre againſt the <hi>Perſians.</hi> But when hée which bare the name of generall, &amp; had the charge of the army in geuing them their pay, had reprochefully called them dogs, ſaying: who ſhal giue mony enough to this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of dogs: thei reuoulted fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> Roma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, and beinge perſwaded by <hi>Homer</hi> their
<pb facs="tcp:176431:59"/> cheifteine: they choſe <hi>Machomet</hi> to be<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Machomet</hi> is made King.</note> their prince, ſpeciallye ſince he had per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded them that they ſhoulde not bée called <hi>Agareni</hi> of <hi>Agar</hi> the handmaide, but rather <hi>Sarraceni</hi> of <hi>Sarra</hi> the lawful wyfe, by reaſon whereof, as it is ſayde, they were the Lordes, and heirs of all kingdomes. Theſe things were done in the yéere of Chriſte. 623. But this ſeditious, murderous, and wicked vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laine <hi>Machomet,</hi> ſo ſoone as hée had ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned the Empire: began to enlarge and ſet foorth his abhominable religion with the ſword, and to enforce men to receaue it, perſecutyng alſo and oppr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the true Chriſtian faith. And for the better ratefiyng hereof, hée continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in this trauaile the ſpace of. 9. yéeres vnto the yéere of our Lorde. 632. Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to al that would follow his relygion he promiſed felycitie, glory, Empire, vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tori, ritches, and after this life the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of Paradice. And by this menes he gat vnto him great multitudes of men, ſpecially when at the beginning things proſpered ſo wel with him, for why, the common people followeth good fortune
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:176431:59"/> victory, and ritcheſſe: hatinge as mutch the croſſe, and perſecutions. Hée willed them moreouer to perſecute all ſutch as ſpake agaynſt, and reprehended the <hi>Alcoran.</hi> Wherfore many reuoulted from the Chriſtian faith, and all vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and true Chriſtians were oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with gréeuous perſecutions: &amp; this was y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> begi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ning of the <hi>Sarracens</hi> king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. After the death of <hi>Machomet,</hi> the <hi>Sarracens</hi> called their chief princes <hi>Amiras,</hi> which as ſome ſaye, ſignifieth as mutch as the name of Emperour. Whoſe names, and moſt famous con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtes, are deſcribed in hiſtories vnto the yéere of Chriſte, 870. They made many great warres: and fought ſundry battailes, and obtayned conqueſtes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> Emperours of <hi>Conſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinople</hi> and other kinges and princes. They ſubdued <hi>Perſia, Babilon, Syria,</hi> the citie of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> and gat ſundry great vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toryes in <hi>Aſia,</hi> and <hi>Affrica,</hi> in whiche places they terme their Princes <hi>Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dans,</hi>
               <note place="margin">souldanes.</note> or <hi>Sultans,</hi> and <hi>Caliphas,</hi> that is to ſaye chiefe Princes, and Capitaines in battaile. The <hi>Sarracens</hi> haue made
<pb facs="tcp:176431:60"/> irruptions into <hi>Italy, Spaine,</hi> &amp; <hi>France,</hi> ſpoiling all y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> euer they could, waſting, burning, &amp; bearing away innumerable ſpoiles. But how miſerably y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> Church of chriſt was torne in péeces, how much chriſtian blood ſhed in ſo many prouin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces duringe the ſpace of ſo many yéeres it is impoſſible to ſet foorth in woordes. For at length y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> 
               <hi>Sarracens</hi> were driuen out of <hi>Spayne</hi> by <hi>Ferdinande</hi> y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> great, the yere of Chriſt 1487 &amp; out of <hi>Affrica</hi> they were expulſed the yéere of Chriſte 1517. but the Turkes ſuccéeded in their place, for <hi>Selimus</hi> emperour of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> turks ſlew, and draue y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> 
               <hi>Sara.</hi> out of <hi>Affri.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hervnto alſo apperteineth that miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable<note place="margin">The holye warre.</note> ſlaughter, wherin there was an vnſpeakable déele of blood ſheden, which is commonly called the Holly warre, wherin the Chriſtians went about to recouer Ieruſalem, and the holly ſepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher of the Lorde, out of the <hi>Sarracens</hi> and <hi>Machometans</hi> handes, whereby they brought none other thinge to pas but béeinge not able to obtaine the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulcher: they haſtned the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues to their owne graues and deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; through
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:176431:60"/> their vnfortunate warre, brought the miſerable Chriſtians of the Eaſt into hatred, great daunger, and perſecution, ſo y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> welnigh, they loſt all y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> was remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninge. But to the intent that this great gréeuous, longe, and cruell perſecution which the <hi>Sarracens</hi> haue exerciſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Chriſtians, may bée the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter knowen: I mean to declare y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> whole diſcourſe of the warre.</p>
            <p>In the yéere of Chriſte, 1. 84. there<note place="margin">The origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall of the <hi>Sarracens</hi> warre.</note> came out of the Eaſt, a certen Anchor, whom hiſtoriographers do call <hi>Peter</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Heremite. The ſame filled the eares of princes and men of all other ſortes, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring vnto them the miſerable ſtate of the Chriſtians in the Eaſt, whom y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> 
               <hi>Machometan Sarracens</hi> oppreſſed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wofull tyranie, and verie mutch moleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: wherfore that it was right néedfull for the Chriſtians in the weſt, to haue ſome care ouer them, and gatheringe an armie both to ouercome the <hi>Sarracens,</hi> and releaſe the Chriſtians. Shortly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>vrban</hi> y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ii. being Pope, and ſchollar to <hi>Gregory</hi> the ſeuenth called togither a counſel at <hi>Claromo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t</hi> in France wherin
<pb facs="tcp:176431:61"/> it was decréed, that the chriſtians with<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Claromont.</hi> counſell.</note> all their power ſhould make warre vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the <hi>Sarracens,</hi> take <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> and the holy Sepulcher, and ſo delyuer the Chriſtians from their tyrrannye. This counſell was pernicyous and hurtfull to the Chriſtian commonwealth, and had the very ſame end with the counſel which is deſcribed in the firſte booke of Kinges, the laſt Chapter. For al things were vnfortunate, and the Chriſtians were not only not releaſed from the ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannie: but moſt part of them ſlayne, &amp; afterward oppreſſed, and afflicted more gréeuouſly then before. And albeit ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny holy and good men, vpon a vertuous zeale yéelded themſelues and conſented to the warre: yet lacked it the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Gods worde, whiche ſhoulde haue commaunded them to take <hi>Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem</hi> and the holy Sepulcher from the <hi>Sarracens,</hi> and to take in hande ſo great and dangerous a warre. For although they atchiued ſundri noble aduentures, and poſſeſſed manye places: yet was there no conſtant Fortune as to holde that which they had take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or to eſtabliſh
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:176431:61"/> peace for the oppreſſed chriſtians. The byſhops alſo in their counſells touching this warre gaue but euell counſell vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Princes, and many other godly chriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians, as they haue done alſo in manye other matters. Other deceits and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles which wer annexed hereto, for bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uytie ſake I omit at this preſent. The <hi>Claromont</hi> counſell was holden the yéere of Chriſt. 1095.</p>
            <p>After the <hi>Claromont</hi> counſel immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atly<note place="margin">The. 1. ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedition.</note> began <hi>Peter</hi> y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> heremits war, who ledyng foorth w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hym certen thouſandes which voluntarely offred themſelues in this expedition: marched through <hi>Hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gary</hi> into <hi>Aſia,</hi> but atchiued ther no noble exploit worthy of memorye. And this was the firſt vnluckie iourney.</p>
            <p>Shortly after two raſhe and trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome<note place="margin">The. 2. ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedition.</note> prieſtes, whom Hiſtoricians call <hi>Volcomar,</hi> and <hi>Goddeſchar,</hi> hauynge gathered an vnfit multitude of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon people: began the ſecond expeditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> into <hi>Aſia.</hi> But when they were come into <hi>Hungarie</hi> ſpoylyng althynge, reb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng, and vſing themſelues diſordinatly, ſo y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> the <hi>Hungaria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s</hi> iudged them worſe
<pb facs="tcp:176431:62"/> then they vnbeléeuyng <hi>Sarracens,</hi> they gathered an army, and ſlew thoſe lewde<note place="margin">The 3. ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedition.</note> pilfring varlets.</p>
            <p>In the yere of Chriſt. 1096. <hi>Godfree</hi> and <hi>Baldwine</hi> of the famile of <hi>Bullein,</hi> Dukes of <hi>Lorraine</hi> tooke in hande the. 3. expeditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> into <hi>Aſia.</hi> Theſe gathering an army of a hundred thouſande horſemen, &amp; three hundred thouſand footemen: tooke many cities of <hi>Aſia,</hi> and Ieruſalem alſo. <hi>Vrſpurgenfies</hi> reporteth, that ther was ſo much blood ſhed there, that in the very temple the bloude was aboue the hooues of the Horſes. The yéere of Chriſt. 1119.<note place="margin">Ieruſalem taken</note> the citie of Ieruſalem was taken by the Chriſtians, and made head of the newe kingdome of Chriſtians in the Eaſte, wherof duke <hi>Godfree</hi> was created king. The ſame reigned one yéere, after who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuccéeded ſeauen Kinges in order, which reigned in all about one hundred yéere &amp; in the yéere of Chriſte. 1189. all things were loſt agayne which they had taken.<note place="margin">The. 4. expedition.</note>
            </p>
            <p>After that tidings were come out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Eaſt, how Ieruſalem was taken, and a new kingdome eſtabliſhed many were pricked forward to take their iourneie
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:176431:62"/> thyther hoping for ritches, &amp; kingdomes. Wherfore in the yéere of Chriſte. 1101. <hi>William</hi> duke of <hi>Poicters,</hi> w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. 100000. men tooke in hand y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy warfare. And this was. y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 4. expedition, which was not alſo very proſperous, for there returned home again not many mo then a M. me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Although Ieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was thus taken by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chriſtians: notwithſtanding y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>Sarracens</hi> ceaſed not from war: but vrged them ſo ſharply y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> they wer enforced to ſu foraid, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as <hi>S. Bernhard</hi> abbot of <hi>Clarauallis</hi> ioyned himſelf in this vnlucky war, and taking diuers iournies in hand exhorted<note place="margin">The. 5. expedition.</note> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chriſtian princes to take this war vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, and at length brought to pas y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>Conrade</hi> the 3. being emperour, <hi>Ludo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uick</hi> kinge of France. <hi>Friderick</hi> duke of <hi>Sueuia, VVelphus</hi> duke of <hi>Bauaria</hi> with many other princes moe, with great power béegan this expedition: but theſe alſo profited nothinge, for their ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie dyinge in ſundrie places in forrein countreys, the princes ſcarſly returned in ſafety. This great expedition was made in the yéere of our Lorde. 1147.</p>
            <p>Afterward Ieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was taken, as we
<pb facs="tcp:176431:63"/> haue ſaid béefore, by a very great power of <hi>Sarracens,</hi> with an vnſpeakable loſſe and ſpillyng of Chriſtian bloud. Which heauie tidinges béeinge arriued in the weſt: forthwith there béetooke them vnto armour, <hi>Friderick Barbaroſſa</hi> the emperour, <hi>Philippe</hi> kinge of <hi>France, Rychard</hi> kinge of England, and with them many princes moe. Theſe tooke in hand the. 6. expedition into the eaſt,<note place="margin">The. 6. ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedition.</note> the yéere of Chriſte. 1189. With an excéedinge great power, who notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandinge brought nothing to paſſe but this only, that the noble prince <hi>Friderik</hi> the emperour fell into a riuer and was drowned, the armie for the moſt part died with ſicknes, the reſidew whereof the numbre was not great, returned home miſerably.</p>
            <p>After this ther apoynted again a new<note place="margin">The. 7. ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedition.</note> and which was the. 7. expedition, two moſt puiſaunt princes, the kinges of <hi>Fraunce,</hi> and England, in the yéere of Chriſte. 1191. and came into <hi>Aſia,</hi> wher léeſinge a great multitude of men: they were conſtrayned to leaue Ieruſalem to the <hi>Sarracens.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="81" facs="tcp:176431:63"/>
            <p>In the yéere of Chriſte. 1198. <hi>Henrie</hi>
               <note place="margin">The 8. ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedition.</note> ſunne to <hi>Friderick Barbarossa,</hi> béegan the viii. expedition into <hi>Syria:</hi> but at the firſt receauinge a foile: hée returned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine without doinge any thinge.</p>
            <p>After all theſe expeditions: Pope <hi>Innocentius</hi> the 3. a craftie &amp; preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious<note place="margin">The <hi>Late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ran</hi> coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell.</note> man, went about afreſh to beegin this warre, caulinge at <hi>Rome</hi> a great counſell, ſuch as hath not bin ſéene thée like, in the yéere of Chriſt, 1215. but hée died in the midſt of this buſines, after whom ſuccéeded <hi>Honorius</hi> the 3. who with no leſſe diligence applied the ſame matter, feigninge, like a falſe prophet, that hée had ſeene a viſion, and that it was ſaid vnto him by Saint <hi>Peter</hi> that in the time of his reigne: Ieruſalem ſhould bée recouered. Wherfore, the ninth expedition was taken in hand to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes <hi>Ancon,</hi> whiche once was <hi>Pto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomais.</hi> Then was taken <hi>Damniata,</hi> yet with more loſſe then profit vnto our men, which was taken the yéere of Chriſte. 1222. and loſt the next yéere fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowinge. To be ſhort, there was almoſt nothinge gotten by the warre, for euery
<pb facs="tcp:176431:64"/> thinge had but litle good ſucceſſe.<note place="margin">The. 10. expedition.</note>
            </p>
            <p>In the yéere of Chriſte. 1228. <hi>Fride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricke</hi> the ſeconde Emperour of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> name, a wiſe, noble, and victorious prince, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertooke the tenth expedition into <hi>Syria,</hi> where vanquiſhynge his enemies: hee tooke certayne principall Citties among which alſo hée wanne Ieruſalem. But<note place="margin">See howe the Pope helpeth the Chriſtians.</note> whilſt this good prince maketh warre agaynſt the Infidels: Pope <hi>Gregorie</hi> the .ix. inuaded <hi>Apulia,</hi> and tooke his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue kyngdome and countrey, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore contrary to his intent and purpoſe, hée was enforced to take peace with the <hi>Soldane,</hi> and ſo departe. Which déede of the Pope, <hi>Abbas Vrſpurgenſis,</hi> in his chronicles doth woorthely blame moſte ſharply.</p>
            <p>Afterward, in y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> yéere of Chriſt. 124<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Ludouick</hi> king of Frau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, with his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers<note place="margin">The 11. ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedition.</note> 
               <hi>Robert</hi> and <hi>Charles,</hi> lead foorth an armie paſſing wel appointed into <hi>Syria:</hi> where hée founde no better fortune then others before him had done. For <hi>Robert</hi> was ſlayn, &amp; <hi>Charles</hi> taken by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>Soldan</hi> the army diſcomfited, and the kynge <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>douicke</hi> hardly eſcaped with a few. And
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:176431:64"/> this was the .xi. vnhappie expedition.<note place="margin">The. 12 expedition.</note>
            </p>
            <p>In the yéere of Chriſte, 1270. Kynge <hi>Ludouicke</hi> lead foorth an armie againe into <hi>Affrica</hi> againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>Sarracens,</hi> which maketh the xij expedition, but there a ſickneſſe inuadyng the army: the kynge himſelf w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> one of his ſunnes died, for hée caried thrée foorth with him into battel, &amp; a few of the people returned home ſalfe.</p>
            <p>Although in this warre, which was firſt kindled by <hi>Peter</hi> the Heremite, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwarde proclaimed by the <hi>Claromont</hi> counſell, and ſucceſſiuely mantayned by meanes and prouocation of <hi>Popes,</hi> there was no conſtant ſucceſſe, ſo that it was manifeſt vnto all men that God would bleſſe it with no proſperous preueile: and ſéeinge that Ieruſalem was loſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne, and the ſtate of Chriſtians in the Eaſt was béecome moſt miſerable from whom by reaſon of the warres, perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions were not taken away, but rather augmented: notwithſtandinge theſe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunate Byſſhoppes, with this vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable effuſion of Chriſtian bloode, were not ſatiſfied, neyther coulde bée broughte to yéelde or relent at theſe
<pb facs="tcp:176431:65"/> perpetuall and great diſcouragementes For <hi>Gregorie</hi> the x. callinge a great counſell at Lions, in the yéeare of our<note place="margin">Counſell at Lyons.</note> lorde. 1272. went about to renewe the warre, but all in vaine, for ſo mutch as therby manie had ſuſtained ſutch and ſo manie miſeries, and calamities both of body, and goodes. And <hi>Matthaeus Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merius</hi> in his Cronacles writeth: How that many thouſandes of Chriſtians be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſlayn in <hi>Syria</hi> by the <hi>Sarracens,</hi> the reſidew for feare departed the cuntrey: whiche was doone the yéere of Chriſte 1291. about whiche yéere <hi>Paulus Aemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius,</hi> and the French Chronacles do re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, that this holy or rather vnhappye warre, was ended, which continued in all. 196. yéeres, whereof the like is not heard of in any hiſtory. And this warre vnto the great damage and oppreſſion of the Chriſtians, was firſt kindled by <hi>Peter</hi> an vnknowne heremit (of whom<note place="margin">vrſpurge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſis. pag. 240.</note> many boaſt verye mutch, others not without cauſe haue doubted whether he were a man or any thinge elſe I know not what, many haue ſaid that he was a diſſemblinge hypocrite) holpen by the
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:176431:65"/> Counſell and prelates, and this mutch is ſufficent to haue ſpoken of the <hi>Sarra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cen</hi> perſecution, Wherfore let vs now come to the Turkiſhe.</p>
            <p>The perſecution of Turkes, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with<note place="margin">Originall of Turkes.</note> they haue moleſted the Chriſtians is in ſome reſpect ioyned and coupled with the <hi>Sarracen,</hi> makinge it more gréeuous and cruell: And the Turkes are a people of <hi>Tartaria,</hi> whiche in the yeere of Chriſte. 764. brake forth of their owne confines through the gates <hi>Caſpiae,</hi> &amp; planted themſelues in <hi>Aſia</hi> who firſt ſeruinge vnder the <hi>Sarracens</hi> for wagies: afterward increaſinge their power by good ſucceſſe in warres, about the yéere of Chriſte. 1051. they created them princes amonge themſelues, who perpetually haue afflicted, and perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the poore Chriſtians, for they alſo had then receaued the <hi>Machometan</hi> religion.</p>
            <p>It is not to bée doubted, but that God hath ſent this cruell, and ſuperſtitious nation of Turkes for a ſcourge vnto the Chriſtians. For like as in the tyme of <hi>Salomon,</hi> when as he fell from the lawe
<pb facs="tcp:176431:66"/> of God, and ſuffred his wiues to build temples vnto Idoles: there ſprange vp and increaſed enemies againſt him, and all the kingdome: ſo likewiſe amonge the Chriſtians, when Pope <hi>Boniface</hi> the. 8. committed many thinges repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to the Chriſtian religion, bringing in the <hi>Iubilee</hi> of the Iewes, which was<note place="margin">The popes <hi>Iubilee.</hi>
               </note> aboliſhed by chriſt, wherby the redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion through Chriſte was no litel déele diminiſhed: at the ſame time in the yéere of our lord, 1300. ſprang foorth that ſharp rodde, namely <hi>othomannus</hi> prince of the Turkes, who at the béeginninge was but a ſhéepheard. From this ſprange out<note place="margin">Original of <hi>Othoman</hi> the firſte Prince of Turkes.</note> all the princes, and emperours of the <hi>Turkes</hi> which hetherto haue obtayned the empire, perſecuting the Chriſtians with vnſpeakable harmes, waſting, and deſtroying whatſoeuer y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>Sarracens</hi> had left, and haue eſtabliſhed ſutch a king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome: as hath deſended and enlarged it ſelf (alas therwhile) with impregnable force againſt all power. <hi>Othomannus</hi> hath amplyfied his kingdome large and wyde, wounderfully indamaginge, van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſhynge, and murtheringe the
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:176431:66"/> Chriſtian Gréekes, which were vnder the empire of <hi>Conſtantinople.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After the death of <hi>Othomannus,</hi> there<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Orchannes</hi> the. 2.</note> ſuccéeded him in the <hi>Turkish</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire his ſunne <hi>Orchannes,</hi> in the yéere of our Lorde, 1328. The ſame enſued his fathers ſteppes, gréeuouſly afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge the Chriſtians, hée béeſiedged the Cittie <hi>Nicea,</hi> whiche when the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour of <hi>Conſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinople</hi> would haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered from ſiedge: the armie of the Chriſtians was miſerably ſlayne, the Cittie yéelded, and the Chriſtians moſt truelly dealt with all.</p>
            <p>In the yéere of our Lorde, a thouſand thrée hundred and fiftie, <hi>Amurates</hi> the firſt of that name, thirde prince of the <hi>Turkes,</hi> ſuccéeded his father <hi>Orchannes.</hi> Who ſendyng an armie ouer the Sea: tooke the cities <hi>Hadrianopolis, Seruia,</hi> and <hi>Bulgaria,</hi> whom when the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Amurates</hi> the. 3.</note> princes aſſaide to driue away, were alſo with their armies ſlaine by the <hi>Turkes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Baiazetus</hi> the firſt, fourth Prince of<note place="margin">Baiazetus. 4.</note> the <hi>Turkes,</hi> béegan to reygne in the yéere of our Lorde. 1373.
<pb facs="tcp:176431:67"/> The ſame hath vnſpeakabli in damaged the Chriſtians: and among other things he beſieged <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> very hardly y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpace of eight yeres. And when y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> had deſiered help of other chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s: <hi>Charles</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>. 6. king of <hi>France, Sigiſmund</hi> of <hi>Hungary, Iohn</hi> Duke of <hi>Burgundy, Rupert</hi> Duke of <hi>Bauaria</hi> with other princes, ſent him aid gathering an army of. 80000. me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. But all theſe vpon <hi>Michaelmas</hi> day were by the Turkes ſlayne at <hi>Nicopolis,</hi> in the yéere of Chriſt 1395.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Machomet</hi> the fift prince of Turks,<note place="margin">Machomet. 5.</note> in the yéeare of our Lorde 1399. came vnto the Empire. He vanquiſhed <hi>Sigiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mund</hi> Kyng of <hi>Hungarie</hi> in a battle at <hi>Columbeciu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> &amp; very mucth indamaged the Chriſtians, in the yéere of Chriſte, 1409.</p>
            <p>Afterward in the yéere of Chriſt 1416<note place="margin">Amurates. 6.</note> 
               <hi>Amurates</hi> the. 2. was created the ſixte Prince of the Turkes. The ſame made war with <hi>Laudiſlaus</hi> king of <hi>Hungarie</hi> and <hi>Polande,</hi> when <hi>Laudiſlaus</hi> through the help of God vanquiſhing <hi>Amurates,</hi> enforced him vnto conditions of peace,
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:176431:67"/> verye neceſſarye and profitable for the Chriſtians. This peace was confirmed by an oth: at whiche time the ſtate of Chriſtians was in good caſe ouer the Turkes, had not Pope <hi>Eugenius</hi> the 4. vnluckely troubled all. Who ſending <hi>Iulianus Caeſarinus</hi> in embaſiedge into <hi>Hungarie:</hi> perſwaded <hi>Ladislaus</hi> the King that hée was not bound by the othe whiche hée made to kéepe peace with the Turke, for that no man ought to make peace with Infidels or heretickes, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> othes and promiſes made vnto them are not to be perfourmed. There were alſo diuers other which prouoked y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> king <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſlaus</hi> that he ſhoulde vſe and employe this happye ſucceſſe whiche God had ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen him againſt the Turkes, vnto the commodytie of the Chriſtian common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, that the Turke was nowe in great feare, and troubled at that preſent with warre by the <hi>Carmani,</hi> wherefore that it were an eaſie matter to vanquiſh him. With theſe perſwaſions this yong Prince, this vertuous and well mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng King, breakinge the peace, viola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge his othe, made warre vppon the
<pb facs="tcp:176431:68"/> Turkes, and pitched his tentes betwen <hi>Danubius</hi> and <hi>Adrianopolis,</hi> neare to<note place="margin">The re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>iurie.</note> the Citie <hi>Varna.</hi> Againſt whome came foorth <hi>Amurates,</hi> acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panied with four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcore thouſande men, greatly blaming the periurie of the Chriſtians, and their breakyng of the peace, where hée ſlewe the young king which had bin deceiued by other, with many moe princes and noble men, and as <hi>Platina</hi> witneſſeth in the life of <hi>Eugenius</hi> the. 4. in that battle were ſlayne, 3. C. thouſand Chriſtians. The battle was fought vpon <hi>S. Martins</hi> éeuen in the yéeare of Chriſte. 1444. Who ſo deſireth to reade a larger deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cription of that wofull calamitie: let him peruſe the <hi>Hungarian</hi> hiſtorie of <hi>Anto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius Bonfinius,</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 6. booke of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 3. <hi>Decade.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But <hi>Amurates</hi> not being ſatisfied w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this victory: immediatly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uaighing his army into <hi>Greece,</hi> ſlew the Emperour of <hi>Conſtantinoples</hi> brother with all his power, and waſted <hi>Peloponeſus</hi> with fire and pilledge: and ſutch Chriſtians as were reſerued from the ſlaughter: he lead away into moſt miſerable ſlauery. And this was the great good prouiſion
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:176431:68"/> and commoditie, whiche the counſell of the bloody and periured Pope <hi>Eugenius</hi> purchaſed to the Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>After theſe calamities and gréeuous<note place="margin">Machomet the. 7.</note> perſecutions: yet were there greater miſcheiues, which by the iuſt iudgment of God oppreſſed the Chriſtians. For in the yéere of Chriſte. 1450. <hi>Macho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met</hi> the ſeconde Sunne to <hi>Amurates</hi> was made the ſeauenth Prince of the Turkes. The ſame for the valientneſſe of his déedes was ſurnamed the great, and called the firſt <hi>Caeſar</hi> or Emperour of the Turkes, becauſe hée tooke awaye valiently by force that Empire whiche<note place="margin">The firſte Emperour of Turkes.</note> from the time of <hi>Conſtantinus</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great, the ſpace of. 1121. yéeres had continued vnder the dominion of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Chriſtians, and brought it in ſubiection vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Turkes.</p>
            <p>For in the yéere of our Lord. 1453. he<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Conſtantino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple</hi> taken.</note> beſiedged <hi>coſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinople</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> head of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, w<hi rend="sup">e</hi> a great power. And whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he had beſiedged it y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpace of 50 continual dais, &amp; aſſaulted it w<hi rend="sup">e</hi> munition, at le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 29 day of May, he increaſed the aſſault w<hi rend="sup">e</hi> al his force fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> morning vntill moſt part of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dai were ſpent, &amp; at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> length took it.
<pb facs="tcp:176431:69"/> Héere nowe it cannot bée recited, with what ſauadge crueltie, wantoneſſe, pride and diſdayne the barbarous Turkes v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the miſerable Chriſtians without al mercy. <hi>Conſtantinus</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Emperour who was preſſed and troden to death by the multitude of men, béeing ſought out and haled from the reſidew of the dead carca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes: had his head ſtrocken off, which bée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng ſet vppon the point of a ſpeare, was carried about in deſpight &amp; deriſion of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. Some report alſo y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ther were 40000. Chriſtians ſlayne, CLM. carryed away into captiuytie and ſould. The exact diſcription of this moſt miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable calamiti, and vnſpeakable perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: is to be found in <hi>Nauclerus</hi> hiſtori.</p>
            <p>Alſo <hi>Ioannes Auentinus</hi> a writer of<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Machomets</hi> great victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries.</note> hiſtories, reporteth that this wicked <hi>Machomet</hi> ſurnamed the great, beſides the two Empires of <hi>Trapezunce</hi> and <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> tooke away moreouer from the Chriſtians. xii. famous King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, and 200 famous Cities. Alſo in the yéere of Chriſte 1469. hée made an irruption into <hi>Styria,</hi> and béeſiedged the citie <hi>Graecium:</hi> whereby ſuch feare in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaded
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:176431:69"/> y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> chriſtians, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> from <hi>Saltzbrough</hi> which ſome ſuppoſe of olde to bee called <hi>Iuuania,</hi> vnto <hi>Monachum,</hi> in <hi>Bauaria,</hi> they fled in ſuch haſt: that they regarded not their Children whiche fell out of the wagons and Chariots by the waye. The ſame at that time they called the Turkiſh flight.</p>
            <p>In the yéere of our Lord God. 1481<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Baiazet. 2.</hi> ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond emper<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>our of Tur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kes.</note> 
               <hi>Baiazetes</hi> was created ſeconde Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of the Turkes, and the eight prince from <hi>Othoma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nus.</hi> Theſame perſecuted alſo the chriſtians cruelly, and brake in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Wallachia,</hi> &amp; <hi>Hungarie,</hi> where néere to the riuer <hi>Morana</hi> vanquiſhyng the Chriſtians: in reproch and diſpight cut of the noſes of all the priſoners which he had taken: He made warre alſo againſt the <hi>Venetians,</hi> ſendynge foorth againſte them <hi>Scender</hi> a <hi>Baſsa</hi> into <hi>Frioll,</hi> who ſacking and ſpoylyng farre aboute carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed away many Chriſtians captiue, of whome thrée hundred thouſande were moſt pitifully ſlayne at the ſhoare of the riuer <hi>Tiliauentum.</hi> Many thinges alſo moe haue bin commited cruelly againſt the Chriſtians by this moſt barbarous,
<pb facs="tcp:176431:70"/> and Turkiſhe Tyraunt <hi>Baiazete.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the yéere of our Lorde. 1512. the. 9<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Selimus. 3.</hi> Emperour.</note> prince of the <hi>Othomanni,</hi> and the third in order of the Turkiſh emperours <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limus,</hi> began to reigne. The ſame quite deſtroid the <hi>Sarracens</hi> &amp; <hi>Mammaluces</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundyng that their laſt <hi>Sultan To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mombeius</hi> moſt ignominiouſly ſhoulde bée hanged, which was done the. 13. day of Aprill, in the yéere of our Lorde. 1517. when hee had taken <hi>Alcharyus</hi> or <hi>Memphis</hi> the greateſt and moſt famous Citie of <hi>Egipt.</hi> And by this meanes the Turkiſh Princes obtayned thrée excée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng great Empires, to wit, of <hi>Trape<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zunce, Conſtantinople,</hi> and <hi>Egypt:</hi> and ſo continuallye the Rodde or Sworde which God hath prepared againſte the Chriſtians is fortified and increaſed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Solimannus</hi> ſuccéeded his Father <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limus</hi> in the Empire in the yéere of<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Soliman. 4.</hi> Emperour.</note> Chriſte. MDXIX. béeinge the tenth Prince, and fourth Emperour of the Turkes. The ſame tooke <hi>Bellogradum</hi> or <hi>Alba Graeca,</hi> a paſſing ſtronge Citie and the key of all <hi>Hungary,</hi> which was in the yéere of Chriſte. MDXXI.</p>
            <pb n="88" facs="tcp:176431:70"/>
            <p>After this in the yéere of our Lord. 1523 hée béeſiedged the Ile of <hi>Rhodes,</hi> and<note place="margin">Rhodes.</note> compelled it to yéeld. Then afterwarde in the yéere of Chriſte, 1526<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> hée diſcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fited and ſlew <hi>Ludouick</hi> kinge of <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garie</hi> with all his armie. Againe, in the yéere of our lorde. 1529. hée brought an army into <hi>Auſtria,</hi> &amp; béeſiedged <hi>vienna</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vienna.</note> the head of the cuntrey, which although hée obtayned not yet hée woundrouſlye indamaged the Region, with fier, ſpoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linges, murther, and captiuity of many thouſand Chriſtians, whom hée caryed thence. Beeſides this, in the yéere of Chriſte. 1537. hée ouercame the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans againe in <hi>Hungarie,</hi> and did them verie mutch harme. After whiche in the yéere of our Lorde. 1541. hée tooke<note place="margin">Buda.</note> 
               <hi>Buda</hi> the Metropolitan Cittie of all <hi>Hungarie,</hi> and alſo the whole countrey. But bicauſe all theſe thinges are freſſh in the memories of men, whiche were done within fiftie yéeres, I thought it ſufficient only to touch them and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pete them: For it is not vnknowne what greate harme hée did, and what autragies hée committed in <hi>Hungarie</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:176431:71"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:176431:71"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:176431:72" rendition="simple:additions"/> about the time that he dyed, which was in the yeere of oure Lorde M. D. lxvi. when he tooke <hi>Ligethum,</hi> where either hee ſlew or caried awaye as priſoners<note place="margin">Lige<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> moſt part of the Chriſtians, whiche in deede were verie manie.</p>
            <p>And now laſt of all, what the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans haue to looke for at the handes of <hi>Selimus</hi> the .ii. ſonne to <hi>Solimannus</hi> the<note place="margin">
                  <hi>selimus. 5.</hi> Emperour.</note> xi. Prince of the diſcent of <hi>Othomannus</hi> and the fift Emperour of the Turkes, who bega to reigne in y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> yeere of Chriſt M. D. LXVI. the experience it ſelfe hath taught in the yéere of our Lorde, M. D. LXX. in which he tooke the noble Kingdome of <hi>Cypres,</hi> ſlaying manye thouſand Chriſtians, whom he had tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented and then ſlaine: or carying the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> awaye into perpetuall, and moſt cruell ſeruilitie.</p>
            <p>I ſuppoſe that in this place, manie<note place="margin">Note.</note> will marueile at this reherſall of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>Sar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racenicall,</hi> and <hi>Turkish</hi> perſecutions, which are not of opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> themſelues that they ſhould be accompted among perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutions: but rather amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g warres, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the reaſon and nature is farre other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:176431:72" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſions are not excuſed that were infected with errours: Semblably in theſe <hi>Sar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racenicall</hi> and Turkiſh warres, I haue applied the name of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> Chriſtian churche (like as I admoniſhed in y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> béeginning of this booke) vnto all thoſe that are called Chriſtians, whom the Turks for y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes ſake do perſecute by reaſon of an hatred which they beare to the chriſtian faith: although many do much want of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſimplicitie, and puritie of the Chriſtian religion: neither by any meanes therby are the errours of the Romiſh Churche excuſed.</p>
            <p>The thinges which firſt incenſed the<note place="margin">Motions vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to theſe per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſecutions.</note> 
               <hi>Sarracens</hi> and <hi>Turkes,</hi> to commit theſe furious cruell tyranycall Tragedies, theſe warres, &amp; perſecutions: was cheif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Diuell himſelfe, who is excée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingely delyghted with ſheadynge of mans blood: ſecondly the hatred of the trew Chriſtian faith, and a gréedye de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſier to rule farre and wide: couetouſnes to hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e vp ritches, and to liue ſumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoppes theretelye: alſo a zeale and <hi>Rome,</hi> Pope, Cache wicked and falſe which be now at th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>met,</hi> with other
<pb facs="tcp:176431:73"/> cauſes which her after ſhalbée declared.</p>
            <p>And this mutch I thought bréefly to ſet downe, concerninge the <hi>Sarracenical</hi> and Turkiſh perſecutions. And it is to bée wiſſhed, that all thoſe which are Chriſtians and would ſo bée named: woulde ſoundly &amp; ſurely acknowledge, that this gréeuous tyrany of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Turkes, is a very true perſecution, laid vpon vs from aboue, to ſée if haply men would bée brought vnto wiſdome, wherby to embrace erneſtlye the pure doctrine of Chriſte, ſtudeinge more to lead a Chriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian life then hetherto they haue doone: for ſurely vnleſſe wée do ſoe: wée muſt néedes looke for farre woorſe.</p>
            <p>But now in theſe <hi>Sarracenicall</hi> and Turkiſh perſecutions, to returne vnto that whiche wée haue often admoniſhed béefore: I aſke this queſtion, if ther bée any man of ſo ſmall or froward diſcreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that dareth avouche that the <hi>Macho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metan</hi> religion is true, and the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an falſe: bycauſe y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> followers of <hi>macho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met</hi> in euerie place haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> among per<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> oppreſſinge the Chriſmo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g warres, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſly railinge at nature is farre other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:176431:73"/> And who dareth deney, that all theſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligions, and Churches which Saynt <hi>Paule</hi> the Apoſtle conuerted to the faith of Chriſte, are now ouerturned, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed by that filthie, and horrible <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chometan</hi> beaſt, and that the moſt impi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, &amp; froward faith of <hi>Machomet,</hi> yea rather that lotheſome abhomination is there eſtabliſhed: And who is ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptious, and deuoyde of all religion, that bicauſe God of his iuſt iudgement permitteth the Turkes to commit ſo manie thynges, which hée coulde eaſely prohibite: will therefore diſpute with God, and demaunde of him, wherfore hée ſuffreth ſo mutch bloud to bée ſhedde, ſo many thouſande Chriſtians to bée ſlayne? How hee can abyde ſo manie vnſpeakable calamities, miſeries, and afflictions of the godly, and that ſo many hundred yéeres? And why rather hee diſtroyeth not with Thundre and light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diffe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> from Heauen, the impure, and Churche of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ire of the Turkes, or ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoppes thereo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to gape and ſwallow <hi>Rome,</hi> Pope, Car<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> abhomination? But which be now at this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e and great cauſes
<pb facs="tcp:176431:74"/> why God, who is true, holy, and righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, ſuffereth and permitteth all theſe thinges. Furthermore, long ſithens hée<note place="margin">Dan. 2. Mat. 24. Luk. 21.</note> foretolde by <hi>Daniell</hi> the Prophete, and Chriſte himſelfe prophiſeth in the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, that the laſt perſecution before the later Iudgmente, ſhoulde bée ſo ſharpe and great: that there was neuer the like vpon the earth ether heard, or ſene. And I am of opinion, that the final iudgment and the redemption of all the faithfull, &amp; glorious clarification, and bleſſed rewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, is not far of from vs. Lorde Ieſus Chriſte, take pittie vpon thine aflicted Church, and vouchſaue to comforte and helpe it in this latter cruell, and moſte rare kinde of perſecution.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>Of the. 20. and laſt Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gical</hi> Act or perſecution, which <hi>the Bishops of Rome haue moued</hi> and practized againſt the Chur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> of Chriſt, certen hundred<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Chapter. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>
            </head>
            <p>THe Papiſtical pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> next to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="92" facs="tcp:176431:74"/> much the more daungerous: how much the leſſe it was to bée looked for, and ſo much the more cruell: becauſe it is prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized by thoſe who of all other oughte moſte to bée ſéekers of peace and quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and ſutch as would bée accoumpted moſt ſoundeſt in relygion, and moſt hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyeſt of all other in the Church, as vnto whom Chriſte hath giuen all power in the Church, that in matters of faith they may rule all thinges accordinge to their pleaſure, and to bée the head and vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall paſtours, ouer the Catholick church of Chriſte. For all men knowe, what titles the Pope, and all his ſpirituall perſons do boaſte of.</p>
            <p>But in the béeginninge of this booke, wée haue declared that there bée ſundrie vnderſtandynges and diſtinctions, not onely of faith, and Religion: but of the Church alſo, ouer which the vngodlye ſéeke to rule. There is alſo very great difference béetwéene the auntient Churche of <hi>Rome,</hi> and the firſte Biſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoppes thereof: and the Churche of <hi>Rome,</hi> Pope, Cardinalles, and byſhops which be now at this day.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:176431:75"/>
            <p>The antient Byſhopes of the Church<note place="margin">The firſte Biſhops of <hi>Rome</hi> were Martirs.</note> of <hi>Rome,</hi> whiche lyued and ſate there from the yere of Chriſt. 70. vnto y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> yere 314. and during the time of <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the great were in number. 32. who wer all faithfull in their callyng, profitynge the Churche by teachinge, and otheir meanes, and for chriſte and his Goſpels ſake were martyred and ſlayne. They medled not at all w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ciuill gouerment there was no Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> no ſenat of ſcarlet Cardinalles, no guarde for the body, no other ſuperfluities, which now adayes are frequented by Popes. Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of credit do confirme this ſame, ſuch as were not writen in flatterie of the Popes. Alſo the name of Pope at that time was not proper onely to the Byſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoppe of <hi>Rome:</hi> but other Biſhoppes alſo abroade in other Prouinces were called by the ſame name. For <hi>Aure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius</hi> and <hi>Ciprian,</hi> Byſhops of <hi>Carthage Ambroſe</hi> Byſhop of <hi>Millaine,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Byſhops in other places, were alſo called Popes. And lykewiſe Saincte <hi>Ierome termeth</hi> S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> whiche was Byſſhop of <hi>Hippo,</hi> in certen E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtles
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:176431:75"/> by the name of Pope. For this<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Papa,</hi> or Pope, what it ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifieth.</note> woorde <hi>Papa</hi> Pope, in the <hi>Syracuſian</hi> tounge ſignifieth as mutch as this word <hi>Pater</hi> a Father, as <hi>Suidas</hi> teſtifieth. For it behooueth the Miniſters of the church to be faithfull fathers of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 4.</note> as Sainct <hi>Paule</hi> writeth.</p>
            <p>Moreouer, amonge all the Byſhops of <hi>Rome</hi> from <hi>Conſtantinus</hi> the great, and Pope <hi>Sylueſter,</hi> vnto <hi>Gregorye</hi> the firſte which were in number, xxxvi. ther was not one within compaſſe of. 280. yéeres, that vſed y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> pompe, pride, maieſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and power, which the Popes vſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomably now now a daies. Their<note place="margin">The aunti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Popes aucthoritie.</note> aucthoritie was great amonge other Churches and Byſhops, becauſe for the moſt parte they were learned and ſkil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full men, neither infected with hereſies as ſome other Byſhops in other Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches were, but principally: becauſe thei were Miniſters of the ſame Churche whiche the Apoſtles planted at the bée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginninge,<note place="margin">Apoſtolick Sea.</note> which was therfore called the Apoſtolick Churche, and the Apoſtolick ſeate, and Sainct <hi>Peters</hi> Chaer. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit the title, and name of the Apoſtolick
<pb facs="tcp:176431:76"/> ſeat was not giuen only to the <hi>Romane</hi> Church: but vnto other Churches alſo, namely Ieruſalem, and <hi>Antioche.</hi> And this woord, ſeate, ſignifieth not a iudgment ſeat, or a princes throne: but an eccleſiaſticall preachers pulpit. So<note place="margin">Tertul. de preſcript. hae<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>reſ.</note> that our forefathers in the ould time ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the aboue named churches, Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like ſeates of the Apoſtolicke doctrine, bycauſe the Apoſtles taught in thoſe pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and from thoſe Apoſtolick Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, the Apoſtolick doctrine ſtretched foorth vnto other Churches, aſwell farre as nere. Wherfore thoſe places in which is not the Apoſtolick doctrine, can not glory of the Apoſtolick ſeat, although in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>déed it were ther many hundred yéeres béefore. For there is alſo a ſeate of the Diuell, as Saynt Iohn declareth in the 2. Chapter of the Reuelation.</p>
            <p>But in the time of Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> the firſt, whiche was within. 300. yéeres after the birth of Chriſte, the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> was ſo farre from the dominion which now it obtaineth: that <hi>Gregorye</hi> very vehemently with ſtood Iohn, which was biſſhop of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> who
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:176431:76"/> ambitiouſly ſought to haue cheif place, and ſuperioritie in the Church, &amp; would alſo bée called vniuerſal byſſhop. Which title, notwithſtandinge and greater to, the byſſhops of <hi>Rome</hi> do vſe at this day: but <hi>Gregorie</hi> ſaid that this was a Deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh pride, and the malice of <hi>Antichriſte.</hi> Hée that luſt let him reade the fourth, &amp; ſixte books of Saint <hi>Gregories</hi> Epiſtles touchinge this matter.</p>
            <p>Howbeit not longe after the death of<note place="margin">Fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce the Romiſh church recei<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued her power.</note> 
               <hi>Gregory, Bonifacius</hi> the 3. vſurped that title, which was graunted vnto him by <hi>Phocas</hi> the emperour, a naughtie and wicked man. For <hi>Otho</hi> byſſhop of <hi>Friſingen</hi> a writer of Cronacles, in the v. booke, and eight Chapter: reporteth how Pope <hi>Bonifacius</hi> the 3. had obtained of <hi>Phocas</hi> the Emperour, that by his aucthoritie, power and commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the Churche of <hi>Rome</hi> might bée cauled, and alſo bée indéede, the head of all other Churches. <hi>Beda</hi> alſo wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the ſame. And <hi>Vrſpurgenſis</hi> ſaith: that <hi>Rome</hi> ought to bée mother of all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Churches.
<pb facs="tcp:176431:77"/> 
               <hi>Nauclerus</hi> writeth: that al other Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches in the worlde, ought to obey the Churche of Rome, and the Biſhop ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. Wherby it may bée eaſely perceaued how that this decrée of <hi>Phocas</hi> the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, whom all Hyſtoricians do verie mutch reprooue: was no decree or inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of the Apoſtles, made by <hi>Peter</hi> or <hi>Paule.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Sea of Rome béeyng exalted af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter<note place="margin">How the Byſhoppes of <hi>Rome</hi> v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurped.</note> this maner: the biſhops which conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently enſued, began more &amp; more to buſie and medle themſelues with ciuile matters, neither ſought they only for power, and dominion: but deuiſed how they might plucke their necks from the emperours iuriſoiction, and extol them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues aboue them, how they might chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge &amp; bryng in ſubiection vnder them, their prouinces, peoples, and maieſtie. But in y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> meane ſeaſon they quight for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got their ſubmiſſion and duty, departing far wide from thence, &amp; became altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther<note place="margin">Popes roſe againſt Em<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>perours.</note> vnlike vnto y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> firſt biſhops of Rome At length the matter proceeded ſo farre: that they durſt boldly withſtande y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours, and riſe agaynſt them, for euen
<pb facs="tcp:176431:77"/> ſo Gregory the .ij. and Gregory the .iij. Popes of Romes, oppoſed themſelues a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Leo</hi> the .iij. and <hi>Conſtantine</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> .v. emperours. For theſe calling certen cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, vnto which there aſſembled a great numbre of learned men, and biſhops of <hi>Aſia, Grecia,</hi> and other regions, they ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gued the controuerſie of Images: name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, whether it were lawfull to haue and to woorſhip the Images of Chriſte, and the holly ſaincts in the Churches of the Chriſtians. Whereas at that time it was concluded, and confirmed out of the holy ſcriptures, and doctrine of the aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient fathers, that Images ought not to be worſhipped, nor to be ſuffred in chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, but to bée taken away wherſoeuer they were founde. But after that th'em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours had giuen foorth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundment to the Popes, and vnto other vnder the Roman Empire, that all of them accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng to the woord of God, and the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning therof diſcuſſed in this preſent cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeil, ſhould take downe th'images out of their Churches: ſutch was the preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Popes, that béeyng called to y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> counſel: they neither appered, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde
<pb facs="tcp:176431:78"/> by their owne aucthoritie, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandement of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours:<note place="margin">Anno Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni. 739.</note> they called peculyer Counſels of <hi>Italian</hi> Byſhops, wherein they decréede y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> Images ought bée to retained in chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and more worſhipped then euer they had bin before. Nether preſumed they onely thus farre: but withdrue the Emperours ſubiectes from due obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence towards hym, excommuncaityng the Emperours themſelues withoute cauſe, raiſing morouer tumults &amp; great feditions, wherein the Emperours lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenantes and debites were ſlayne, as namely, <hi>Paulus</hi> at <hi>Rauenna:</hi> and <hi>Mau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritius</hi> with <hi>Adriane</hi> his ſunne in <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pania.</hi> And by this meanes all dutifull<note place="margin">Emperour of <hi>Conſtant.</hi> by Popes driuen out of <hi>Italy.</hi>
               </note> ſeruice, and obedience was denied to the Emperours, &amp; they were driuen from the gouerment of <hi>Italye.</hi> But by what right, the Popes brought theſe thinges to paſſe by their practizes: euery man that is indued with common ſence, and hath any knowledge of iuſtice, mai ſoone vnderſtand. Al theſe things were doone w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in. 30. yéeres after y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> yere of our lorde 724, or nere therupon, vnto the yéere of our Lorde. 754</p>
            <pb n="96" facs="tcp:176431:78"/>
            <p>In the yéere of our Lorde, 750. Pope<note place="margin">an honeſt practiſe.</note> 
               <hi>Zacharie</hi> the. 1. of that name, tooke vpon him te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>porall matters, &amp; began to medle with the ciuill gouerment, &amp; aſſiſted to depoſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> king of France fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his crowne and to place another in his rowme. For through his help and counſell, <hi>Hilderik</hi> king of France of the antient familie of <hi>Merouingi,</hi> was depoſed from y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> crown, and <hi>Pipine</hi> of the familye of <hi>Charles,</hi> thurſt into his place.</p>
            <p>But ſhortly after this great benifite of the Popes: <hi>Pipine</hi> brought an army of Frenchme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> into <hi>Italy</hi> againſt <hi>Eſtulphus</hi> king of <hi>Lumbardy,</hi> when hauing taken in war the greater parte of the cuntrey, hée gaue it for reward vnto pope <hi>Steuen</hi> the ſecond, and then firſt <hi>S. Peter</hi> obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned an inherita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, who béefore y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> time, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſpace of. 700. yéeres: neuer had any: and although y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> 
               <hi>Conſtantius</hi> y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> emperour ſent Embaſſadours vnto <hi>Pipine,</hi> that hée would not alienate the Prouinces of the Romane Empire: yet notwithſtanding <hi>Steuen</hi> the Pope gladlye receiued thoſe Prouinces, peopls, and ciuill gouerment whiche certenly <hi>S. Peter</hi> would neuer haue doone, foraſmuch as hee refuſed the
<pb facs="tcp:176431:79"/> charge ouer the poore. Actes the vi.</p>
            <p>The Popes followinge thereafter, immitated the déedes of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which went before, nothinge lyke the déedes of the Apoſtles. For <hi>Hadriane</hi> the Pope, lykewiſe receiued all thoſe thinges wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyngly which <hi>Charles</hi> ſurmamed the great, King of Fraunce, gaue vnto him when he had vanquiſhed and ouercome the Lumbards, and taken priſoner <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderius</hi> their King. But <hi>Leo</hi> the third attempted more. For he tooke vpon him the aucthoritie ouer all the Empire, which then appertayned to the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> and crowned <hi>Charles</hi> Emperour of <hi>Rome</hi> withoute<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Charles</hi> made Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour by the Pope.</note> the knowledge and conſent of the law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Emperours, when as then, as <hi>Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merius</hi> accompteth, the weſt had lacked their owne Emperour the ſpace of. 330. yéeres.</p>
            <p>The yéere of Chriſte 860. Pope <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholas</hi>
               <note place="margin">Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours ſwere to the pope.</note> the firſte ruled the ſea of <hi>Rome,</hi> a paſſinge ambitious man inſtitutinge ſundry thinges not appertayning to the gouerment of the Church: but to confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation and eſtabliſhinge of the popiſhe
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:176431:79"/> tyrany. Firſt that no prince, no not the emperour himſelfe, ſhould bée preſent in the counſeiles of the Clergie. Alſo that no lay man ſhould ſet in iudgment ouer a clarke, or eccleſiaſticall perſon. Moreouer that the Popes decrées and ſentences, ought to bée iudged by no man: yea, that the Pope is ſubiect vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to no ciuile power, bicauſe he is God. Reade <hi>Antoninus Titul. xvi. Paragra. 9.</hi> and likewiſe in the decrées, in the 76. and. 28<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> diſtinction.</p>
            <p>Afterward in the yéere of Chriſt. 962. the Popes of <hi>Rome</hi> grue vnto ſo great power: that when <hi>Otho</hi> the. 1. emper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our of that name, came vnto <hi>Rome,</hi> hée muſt néedes take an othe vnto Pope Iohn the xii. that hée would defende the inheritance of <hi>Peter,</hi> &amp;c. Reade the. 63. diſtinction which béeginneth: <hi>Tibi Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine Ioanni.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But in the yéere after the birth of our Lord &amp; ſauiour Chriſt. 1000. the tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of Popes againſt y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> emperours brak foorth into light: for caſting away their yoke from their neckes: they béegan fréely to bear rule at their owne pleſure
<pb facs="tcp:176431:80"/> nothinge regardynge any Magiſtrate, yea bringynge Princes, kynges and Emperours into ſubiection vnder them and compellyng to obey them, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe through deceit and couen, bryng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge them to the bent of their bow. For I pray you what horrible tragedies and turmoiles did pope <hi>Gregory</hi> the ſeuenth ſtirre vp againſt <hi>Henrie</hi> the fourth?</p>
            <p>For, not only hée excommunicated him and intreated him moſt diſdainfully: but alſo diſcharginge his ſubiectes, princes, and nobles that were vnder the empire from their othe and allegeance: raiſed a ſedition againſt him, cauſing an infini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie deale of blood to bée ſhead. Who ſo is diſpoſed: let him reade this moſt cruell and ſtrange hiſtorie, in the yéearlye re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordes of <hi>Ihon Auentine,</hi> and in other hiſtoricians.</p>
            <p>Pope <hi>vrbane</hi> the .ii. which ſuccéeded<note place="margin">vrban. 2.</note> 
               <hi>Gregorie</hi> in the ſea of Rome, his verie true and vndoubted Diſciple, in the <hi>Claromont</hi> counſell was cauſer of the moſt cruell warre, which the Chriſtians made againſt the <hi>Sarracens,</hi> wherof we haue ſpoken béefore. Béeſides, hee pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoked
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:176431:80"/> 
               <hi>Conrade</hi> the prince of Italye to rebell againſt his father the emperour <hi>Henrye</hi> the fourth, which was a deede altogither againſt nature.</p>
            <p>Likewiſe <hi>Paſchalis</hi> the .ii. egged the<note place="margin">Paſchalis. 2.</note> ſunne <hi>Henrye</hi> the v. againſt his father <hi>Henrye</hi> the fourth, and thriſe accurſed him tauſinge the byſſhoppes of <hi>Ments,</hi> and <hi>Coleine,</hi> &amp; wourmes, in his palace of <hi>Ingelheim</hi> by force to turne him out of his imperiall ornamentes, diſgrading the good ould emperour, and adorninge therwith his ſunne Henrye the fifte. If anye man can bée delighted herewith: let him read this wofull hiſtorye, in his <hi>Saxonie</hi> of <hi>Albertus Crantius</hi> the fir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> booke, the xx. chapter.</p>
            <p>The ſame <hi>Paſchalis</hi> was troubleſom alſo vnto the emperour <hi>Henrye</hi> the fift, and was the cauſe of mutch bloodſhead, and all only for the donation and gift as they call them of certein eccleſiaſticall benefices, and prefermentes, which vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to that time the emperour had alwayes, and now the Pope went about forcibly to take them away.
<pb facs="tcp:176431:81"/> But that which hée could not bringe to paſſe the ſame afterward <hi>Calixtus</hi> the. 2 aſſaid, nether relented vntill hée had ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away from the emperour the ſame right of donation of ſpirituall prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes. Wherof <hi>Abbas Vrſpurgenſis</hi> hath writen diligently. Theſe thinges were doone in the yéere of our lord God 1122.</p>
            <p>But the Popes of Rome were not<note place="margin">Popes op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe the emperours.</note> contented with this: but the later ſorte haue inſued the trade of their prediceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours, touching wickednes and miſcheif in perſecutinge the emperours. For af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward they béecame gréeuous vnto them, neuer makinge an ende of curſing ſeditions, warres, and perpetuall fraud and deceipt, vntill at length they had op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed the wéerie emperours, and exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted their ſeate aboue theirs, placinge themſelues in power and ſuperioritie aboue all other. Who ſo deſireth to haue<note place="margin">2. Theſ. 2.</note> a ſounde, and perfect knowledge of theſe matters: let him reade the ſtorye of <hi>Fridericus Barbaroſsa,</hi> and thoſe thinges which the Popes <hi>Adrian</hi> the fourth, and <hi>Alexander</hi> the thirde, practized againſt
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:176431:81"/> him, of which the later moſt preſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly trode vpon the Emperours necke with his foote. Alſo what <hi>Caeleſtinus</hi> the fourth wrought againſt Henry the firſt. Let him alſo there béeholde with what arrogancie, pride, and inſolencie, Pope Innocentius the third, a loftie and bould Preiſt, vſed againſt Philip the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour. But ſpecially let it bée well conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, what the popes <hi>Honorius</hi> y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> third. <hi>Gregorie</hi> the .ix. and <hi>Innocentius</hi> the. 4 committed wickedly, and deceiptfully a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Fridericke</hi> the ſeconde, a notable and moſt excellent Emperour, &amp; a man indued with moſt ſingular giftes, whom moſt vnworthely and reprochfully, they troubled &amp; afflicted, as they did likewiſe his ſunne, <hi>Conradus,</hi> the fourth emper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our of that name.</p>
            <p>Theſe contentions, perſecutions, and moſt cruell and perpetuall warres, bée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twéene the Popes and the emperours: continued. 181. yéeres béeginning in the time of <hi>Gregory</hi> the 7. vnto the enſtau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linge of <hi>Alexander</hi> the fourth, and vnto the yéere of our lord. 1256. About which time writers of hiſtories, &amp; Cronacles,
<pb facs="tcp:176431:82"/> do make an <hi>Interregnu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> or ſpace while none ruled, which indured the terme of xvii. or xviii. yéeres, vnto the election of<note place="margin">Anno 1271.</note> y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> emperour <hi>Radulphus</hi> of <hi>Habſpurge.</hi> And although in the meane time certen princes were choſen, as <hi>Alfonſus,</hi> and <hi>Rycharde,</hi> wherof the laſte tooke vpon him the charge, and gouerment of the empire: yet all theſe princes were ſo terr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fied with daily moleſtations, and deceites, wherwith y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Popes had hether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to troubled the emperours, that no man would willinglye take the empire vpon him, ſince euerie man euidently béeheld that by poſſeſſion therof hée could obtaine no quietnes nor profit, but only damage<note place="margin">Kinge of <hi>Rome</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </note> and vexation. For although <hi>Germanye</hi> had the title of the <hi>Romane</hi> empire: yet Rome was not the head of their empire, but of the Pepes &amp; if that haply through their great charge, trouble, and payne leadinge an armie into Italye, they had by force poſſeſſed the citie: ſo ſoone as they were returned again into <hi>Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye,</hi> the Pope by and by repoſeſſed the ſame.</p>
            <p>Moreouer, the kinge or emperour of
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:176431:82"/> the <hi>Romans,</hi> receiueth no great com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moditie<note place="margin">Se <hi>Theodor Nyem</hi> of ſciſmes. 3. booke 43. chap. and <hi>sleidan. de Monar. Pag. 120. 171. 172.</hi>
               </note> nor reuenue out of the <hi>Romane</hi> Empire, ſo that vnleſſe hée haue other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyſe prouiſion, and liuinge of his owne hée is ſcarce able thereof to mayntayne his port, and dignitie. Yea, and béeſides this: the Popes haue moleſted, and gone about to take awaye by force of armes, their patrimonie whiche haue taken vpon them the Empire there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. Wherfore, princes that were of wealth and ſubſtance, haue not eaſely bin perſuaded to take the Empire vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon them. And <hi>Radulphus</hi> Erle of <hi>Habſpurge,</hi> when as hée accepted the election: yet could hée neuer bée perſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to goe to Rome, to receaue the Crowne of the Empire, for hée al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes aunſwered, that hée was af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid by the example of manye whiche haue gone to Rome, wherof but fewe haue returned agayne. And that hée might cléerelye diſcharge himſelfe from that <hi>Cerberus:</hi> hée caſt into his mouth <hi>Romandiola,</hi> whiche vnto that time béelonged to the empire.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:176431:83"/>
            <p>The Popes of <hi>Rome</hi> haue vſed ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry ſtrange practizes, to bereue kinges and Emperours of their power, and to extolle themſelues aboue Kinges and Princes, or rather to caſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> downe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their féete. Their chiefe power con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted in excomunicatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or hauing exco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated<note place="margin">Excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication.</note> any Prince: they withdrue the ſubiectes from obeying him, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horted them to raiſe tumultes, and fall away from him: moreouer they egged ſubiectes and ſeruantes to rebel againſt their Lords, &amp; Maiſters ſhamefully diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charging them from their Loialtie and oth, vnder this title &amp; pretence, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> there ought no honor, nor obedience be ſhewe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or vſed vnto excomunicate perſons, nor<note place="margin">The popes Legates.</note> oth kept towards them. Then ſent they abroad into all Prouinces ſubtile men, Legates with Bulles or Letters, and w<hi rend="sup">e</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apoſtolick power, as they terme it, through whoſe meanes they bread ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drye conſpiracies, partly with the Biſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops of the Prouinces whom they put in minde of their dutifull obedience to the Sea of <hi>Rome,</hi> partly with Princes of the Empire, and with all other that
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:176431:83"/> were of ani power, or aucthority. Thus hauinge gotten certen of thoſe in their faction, and raiſing a diſſention amonge the people, the next was that there muſt a new Emperour, bee choſen: and then fell they together by the eares whiche héeld with the old Emperour, and they which tooke part with the new. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon many horrible, &amp; wofull miſeries<note place="margin">Warres and ſediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> haue enſued, as ciuill warres, ſeditions, murthers, burnings, and generally all kindes of calamities: wherwith the good Emperours ſomtimes béeing wearye, many times ouercome by force: haue bin conſtrained to geue place and abide theſe thinges, and in the meane while the Popes haue with more arrogancye and bouldneſſe aduaunced their head. Al theſe thinges may bée ſéene as it were in a Mirrour, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hiſtories of the empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours <hi>Henrie</hi> the fourth. <hi>Henrie</hi> the. 5. <hi>Frederick</hi> the firſte, and <hi>Frederick</hi> the ſeconde, and others, whome wée haue béefore named. And ſo at length the Popes haue ouercome and béecame ſtronge, as <hi>Daniell</hi> writeth, but not by their owne power.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:176431:84"/>
            <p>Béeſides this alſo, they haue vſed the<note place="margin">Counſelles</note> benifite of counſelles vnto the confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and preſeruation of their kingdom. For in thoſe dayes they made them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues rulers of the counſelles, vnto whiche they called men of their owne faction, who in no poynt would gainſay the Pope. And becauſe that of oulde times ſutche counſelles as then were holden by moſt godly and learned men, were of great aucthoritye: they were alſo verye mutch regarded of all men which the moſte hollye father (for ſo hée was ſuppoſed to bée) with his adherents had concluded in their aſſemblies. And thus vnder the title of counſelles: the Popes mightely brought their driftes to effect.</p>
            <p>There was alſo a newe deuiſe, and<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cruciata</hi> or <hi>Croyſados.</hi>
               </note> ſuch a one as the like hath not bin heard of before, inuented in the <hi>Claromont</hi> counſel, vnder Pope <hi>Vrbane</hi> the ſecond which by a new name they called <hi>Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciata:</hi> or <hi>Croysados.</hi> They preached the Croſſe, but farre otherwiſe then dyd the Apoſtles. For they preached the Croſſe of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, namely, how
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:176431:84"/> that through his Croſſe and Paſſion, wée are clenſed from our ſinnes, and by Faith obtayne eternall felicitie. But the Popes <hi>Cruciata</hi> or <hi>Croyſados,</hi> was a certein kinde of Alarme. For the preachers of this <hi>Cruciata,</hi> exhorted the chriſtians to ſigne themſelues with the Croſſe, (lyke as ſouldiers in warre for a ſigne or token, doo weare white or red ſkarfes) and that they ſhould march in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Eaſt againſt the <hi>Sarracens,</hi> as we haue ſhewed before. And they preched that they whiche were ſigned with the Croſſe in this warfare: obtayned indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gencies, that is to ſaye, remiſſions of ſinnes, and if they were ſlayne in battle: ſhould be partakers of eternall felicitie.</p>
            <p>Afterward, theſe ſuborned preachers<note place="margin">Mendican<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Friers.</note> of the Popes, not onely preached the croſſe againſt the <hi>Sarracens:</hi> but alſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Chriſtians, namely againſte the Emperours, whome the Pope had proclaimed to bée hereticks, &amp; generally againſt al y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> would not adore the pope, &amp; obey all his commaundements. And by this ſhift, the Popes haue gathered very great and well apoynted armies almoſt
<pb facs="tcp:176431:85"/> withoute any charge, obtayning their power, wealth, and greatneſſe wherun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to they bée nowe growne, by verye force.</p>
            <p>But in this matter the foure orders of begging or mendicant Fries haue doone the Popes verye good ſeruice, whiche firſt béegan in the time of Pope <hi>Innocentius,</hi> and <hi>Honorius,</hi> both the. 3. of that name, which kinde of people the Chriſtian Churche wanted the ſpace of MCC. yéeres, and that with more quietneſſe and commodytie then hath ſince the time of their béeginninge, and approbation enſued. Howbeit in prech<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge and ſettyng foorth of the <hi>Cruciata</hi> or <hi>Croyſados:</hi> the <hi>Dominican</hi> Friers haue taken moſt paine, who by preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng this <hi>Cruciata</hi> or <hi>Alarme,</hi> obtayned the name of preaching Friers. Whom<note place="margin">Preachyng Friers.</note> the Popes in conſideration of their paines and dillygent ſeruice: haue in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued with Priuiledges, and honours, and loued them more tenderly then the reſtdue. Of whoſe trauile employd to the pleſure, and furtherance of the pope many thinges might be written.</p>
            <pb n="103" facs="tcp:176431:85"/>
            <p>At length the ſtate of Chriſtianytie proceeded ſo farre, after the time of the<note place="margin">The Pope vaunteth himſelfe to be Empe.</note> kinges <hi>Radulphus,</hi> and <hi>Adulphus,</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>Albertus</hi> the firſte, in the yéere of Chriſte. 1300. that the Pope vaunted hymſelfe to be Emperour. For at the ſame time, <hi>Bonifacius</hi> the. 8. brought in agayne the yéere of <hi>Iubilee,</hi> which was abrogated by the Apoſtles. <hi>Actes</hi> the. 15 Chapter, promiſing forgiueneſſe of ſins vnto all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> would come to Rome: vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt day of which <hi>Iubilee,</hi> being ador<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in his po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tificalrobes: he came abroad ſhewing himſelfe as Pope to all men, &amp; bleſſing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people: the next day he came foorth in his Emperiall apparell, openly declaring that the Empire and Papacie together with all ciuill and eccleſiaſtical power, were in the popes hands. Theſe things are written by <hi>Albertus Crant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zius,</hi> in the eight booke, 26. Chapter of his <hi>Saxonie.</hi> The ſame Pope alſo ſet foorth <hi>Decretals,</hi> whiche are called the <hi>Decretals</hi> of <hi>Bonifacius</hi> the eight, where in muche more impudentlye hée challengeth all power to the Popes.</p>
            <p>This power or rather tirannie, and
<pb facs="tcp:176431:86"/> intollerable arrogancye, not longe after <hi>Bonifacius: Iohn</hi> the twenty and two,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> the. 22 againſt the emperour <hi>Ludou. 4.</hi>
               </note> put in practiſe, and declared towardes <hi>Ludouick.</hi> For he moſt reprochefully miſuſed him, excommunicated him, caſt him into gréeuous warres, cauſinge an vnſpeakable deale of mans bloud to be ſhead, throughout all <hi>Germanie.</hi> Theſe thinges are deſcribed dilligently, and at large, by <hi>Iohn Auentine</hi> in the ſeuenth booke of the yeerely recordes of the <hi>Boi:</hi> whiche I declare for this intent, that who ſo deſireth to haue an exacte know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of theſe thinges: may know wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to finde it.</p>
            <p>Moreouer, in the reigne of <hi>Ludouick</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Zurick</hi> excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated.</note> the fourth, as alſo before, vnder <hi>Fride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick</hi> the ſecond, the Citie of <hi>Zurick</hi> bée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it tooke part with the Emperours againſt the Pope, keeping alwaies their oth and allegance towardes hym: ſtood many yéeres excommunicated, whiche was not withoute great hinderance of the commonwealth, although ſince that time it hath againe bin indued with ſundrye priuiledges, and honours. At which time the firſt ground and founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:176431:86"/> of the <hi>Swicers</hi> league, through the gifte of God was layde moſt happely, <hi>Ludouick</hi> the Emperour moſt largely and liberally graunting to the ſame, and fauoring the <hi>Swicers,</hi> whom I pray god to bleſſe, and kéepe, and defend moſte mercifully.</p>
            <p>Nowe perhaps you wyll aſke mée, whether theſe Actes of the Popes and Emperours, and the increaſe of the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh power and aucthority, doo any thing appertaine to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> perſecutions againſt the churh, wherof at the beginning we pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to write? yea indeede, altogether, &amp; ſurely moſt properly they appertaine to the ſame. For in aſmuch as the firſt biſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops of <hi>Rome</hi> perſecuted no man, but themſelues ſuffred perſecution, &amp; were Martires, and thoſe whiche next follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed were moſt parte of them holye and faithfull doctours, ſubiectes to the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours and ciuill Maieſtrates, and ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led ouer no Prouinces nor Peoples ſo that none of them were Princes, and the later Popes in theſe laſte times ſtirred vp moſte gréeuous perſecutions within the circute of Chriſtendome:
<pb facs="tcp:176431:87"/> it is expedient to know by what means and maner, how, why, and when, the ſtate of the byſſhops of <hi>Rome</hi> was ſo ſhamefully deformed and chaunged, that the later Popes béecomminge ſo farre diffrent from the firſt byſſhops: béecame Lordes of kinges, and emperours, and cruell perſecuters of them. Now ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, ſo many moſte cruell and ſharpe warres, which the Popes béeing aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to ſo great power haue ſtirred amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g Chriſtians, in which ſutch aboundance of Chriſtian blood hath bin ſhead: maye they not rightfully be reckned amongſt the perſecutions of Chriſtians? For like as abroad they haue bin ſticklers of moſt gréeuous warres vnto the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans againſt the <hi>Sarracens</hi> and Turkes, as wée haue declared béefore: ſo haue they bin alſo at home aucthours of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutions, troubles, and deſtruction to Chriſtians. Doth not this verie well de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue the name of a perſecution, when as Chriſtian emperours, with ſuch as duetifully obeyd his heſtes, ar by Popes vexed and waſſhed with their own blood diſcourteouſly dealt withall with wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons,
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:176431:87"/> and warlike torments, which, as we haue ſhewed béefore out of hiſtorys, many yéeres with infinite ſpillinge of blood, were moſt cruelly and tyranni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally committed? But in the midſt of ſo many calamities, the wofull kinges and emperours perpetuallye ſuffringe affliction, and miſerie: at length they and theirs quayled, and gaue ouer, and the Popes béeinge conquerours: trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phed, and althinges hapned accordinge to their deſier, and ſo they eſtabliſhed their power, that they might ſtand heer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after in awe of no man, but rule at their pleaſure without all controulement.</p>
            <p>And in very déede, theſe are not vnlike vnto <hi>Daniels</hi> prophecy, wherin hée hath left thus written: While the vngodly are a growyng: there ſhall ariſe a king with an impudent face, which ſhall vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand darck ſayinges, and his power ſhal encreaſe but not in his own ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth and hée ſhal deſtroy aboue meaſure, and all that hée goeth about ſhal proſper, and hée ſhall deſtroy the valient and holly people. And through his craftines, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit ſhal proſper in his hand, and hée ſhal
<pb facs="tcp:176431:88"/> magnifie himſelfe in his hart, and in his proſperity hée ſhall confound many. Yea hée ſhall riſe vp againſt y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> prince of prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, but hée himſelfe ſhalbée deſtroyed with out hand. <hi>Daniell</hi> the .viii. Chap. But if I would here declare y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vnſpeka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble deal of mans blood, which by means<note place="margin">Warres for <hi>sicill,</hi> and <hi>Naples.</hi>
               </note> of Popes hath bin ſhead in <hi>Sicile, Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples,</hi> and <hi>Apulia:</hi> ſurelye the recitall would bée ouer longe. For, from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> time of <hi>Innocentius</hi> the. 4. vnto <hi>Clemente</hi> the vii. y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpace of. 284. yéeres: ſumtime the <hi>Germans,</hi> afterward the <hi>Frenchme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> again the <hi>Spainiards</hi> againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>French<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,</hi> then a freſh the <hi>Germans</hi> againſt them, then againe the <hi>Frenchmen</hi> and <hi>Hungarians</hi> were by Popes called to ſutch and ſutch kingdomes, and ſutch and ſutch peoples were at warre, and by them ſet togither by the eares. All which troubles are diligently ſet downe by hiſtoricians.</p>
            <p>Moreouer, through the immoderate,<note place="margin">Popes ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers of faith and the Church.</note> and vnlawfull power or rather tyranny of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> Popes, no leſſe alſo by other mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, blooddy perſecutions and murthers haue riſen. For after that, as wée haue
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:176431:88"/> ſhewen béefore, they had mightely vſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped vpon all Eccleſiaſticall and Ciuill iuriſdiction, and power alſo ouer coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelles: then might they afterward inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute and ordeine all ordres of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Church the doctrine of faith and religion, rites and cuſtomes in the Churche, at theyr owne will and pleaſure. And hereof aroſe perſecutions. For who ſo euer reſiſted: thoſe they cried out vppon for heretickes, and vnder that pretence perſecuted them. And this ſame (bée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the warres of the Popes) I terme properlye the Papiſticall perſecution agaynſte Chriſtians, and the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Churche, whiche was mooued againſte the godlye and faithfull onely for their faithes ſake, as it was ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time in the primitiue Church. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, like as at the beeginninge, the firſt faithfull were perſecuted by the Emperours of Rome: euen ſo towards the ende of the worlde, the faithfull of the latter times do ſuffer perſecution by the Popes of Rome. But vndoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedlye the Lorde will come ſhortlye to iudge both the quick, and the dead.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:176431:89"/>
            <p>But to the end that this matter may the better bée vnderſtoode, and for the more exact knowledge therof: it cannot<note place="margin">Errours crept into the Church</note> bée denied, that many errours and abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes not now firſt, but ſumwhat béefore haue crept in and haue bin receaued in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Church, ſo that through continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of time: they haue growen into cuſtome. Which thinges with manie o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther moe, in proceſſe of time are confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and cheifly by the Popes forced vpon men, and by ſubtile practiſes but ſpecially by the ſwoorde inlarged, and preſerued: in ſo mutch that many per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceauynge the errour, yet durſt not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly withſtande it: for they ſaw well, that they might not ſo do without daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of their owne bloud. But cheifly in theſe later times this cuſtome hath pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueyled, which I wil now recite.</p>
            <p>In the dayes of the emperours <hi>Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tharius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Originall of the <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non</hi> law. <hi>Gratianus.</hi>
               </note> and <hi>Conrade</hi> the .iij. or as other ſome ſay of <hi>Fridericke,</hi> about the yéere of Chriſte. 1130. <hi>Gratianus Bononienſis</hi> a Munke of the order of <hi>Benedictus,</hi> ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered together the ſentences of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, fathers, and popes, touching ſundry
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:176431:89" rendition="simple:additions"/> matters apperteinyng to religion &amp; the Church, and ſetfoorth that work abroad which is commonly called <hi>Decretum,</hi> or Decree. After <hi>Gratianus,</hi> certein po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes, as <hi>Gregory</hi> the. 9. <hi>Bonifacius</hi> the, 8 <hi>Clemens</hi> the. 5. &amp; <hi>Iohn</hi> the. 22. following the example of <hi>Gratianus:</hi> haue gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red alſo, &amp; with y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> help of certein munks and Doctours: they patched together ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences and iudgements of Popes, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernyng rites, and inſtitutions, and bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſes apperteinyng to Churches, and eccleſiaſticall orders. The ſame are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Decretales,</hi> and <hi>Extrauagantes,</hi> and were added vnto <hi>Gratianus Decretum,</hi> and all of them togither do make the body of the Canon law. This law bée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to bée taught in ſchooles, which all other followed in doing the like in their<note place="margin">Scholes, and Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſities vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der the pope</note> eccleſiaſticall iudgmentes, and admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Church. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y which menes Schooles and vniuerſities whiche are called the Schooles of lawes &amp; Canons came vnder the Popes iuriſdiction, wherein the ſcholars, Maiſters, and Doctours, muſte take an othe to bée o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient vnto the Pope, and the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of
<pb facs="tcp:176431:90"/> Rome, or vnto ſutch as are obedient vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, or againſt his lawes, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Yea this matter hath proce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded ſo farre: that the emperours alſo, as well as all other byſſhops, muſt take an othe vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Pope. The fourm of which Othe: is extant in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Decrées, &amp; Decre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals.<note place="margin">Swere to the Pope.</note> And by this meanes the Pope hath made ſubiect, bound, &amp; béeholding vnto him: al ſortes, and orders of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Church.</p>
            <p>Héereunto oppertaineth, that at the ſame time with <hi>Gratianus,</hi> not longe af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter, accordinge to the ſupputation of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, about the yéere of our Lorde. 1172.<note place="margin">Peter Lum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bard.</note> 
               <hi>Peter Lumbard,</hi> whom they call mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of the ſentences, wroat, and ſetforth 4. bookes of the Chriſtian faith and doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, which were receaued into the Schooles, as was the body of the lawe: ſo that like as <hi>Gratianus</hi> is aucthour of the <hi>Canoniſtes,</hi> &amp; doctours of the Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifical lawe: ſo <hi>Peter Lumbard</hi> is aucth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our of the ſcholaſticall diuinitie. For the Doctours of thoſe times, and cheiflye mendicant friers, read <hi>Lumbardes</hi> ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences openly in ſchools, and haue writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten vpon the ſame, as <hi>Albertus, Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas, Bonauenture, Scotus,</hi> and many
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:176431:90"/> other. And according vnto theſe ſenten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: they ordred the doctrin of faith, and all other affaires of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Church. At which time the Chriſtian doctrine was won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully torne &amp; cut into ſundrie queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, wherof they co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly diſputed and argued in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcholes and holy ſermons, or rather ſkoulded, wherby the Chriſtian doctrine, béecame altogither vnlike vnto<note place="margin">Agreement of the Church.</note> th'auntient Apoſtolike ſinglenes, &amp; inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gritie. Althings were referred and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iected to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſea of Rome, and y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> pope vnto whom al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Canoniſtes, &amp; diuines were bound by an othe. And this is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> conſpira<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cie of the clargie, which they cal &amp; vaunt to be the conſent of al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church, in faith, &amp; doctrine. Howbeit in veri déed it is none other but this conſpiracy which we haue héere recited. Wherfore, out of this fountaine and welſpryng, flowed y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous papiſticall perſecution againſt the Chriſtian Church. For whoſoeuer miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liked with the Popes Monarchie, and conſpiracy of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> clergy, which they terme conſent and agréement of the church, and did not ſpeake althinges according to the intent of the Canoniſtes, and Theolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtes: vpon thoſe they ran in flockes,
<pb facs="tcp:176431:91"/> and through the Popes helpe, and aſiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of the ſeculer arme: they procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med them euerywhere hereticks, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted, and oppreſſed them. Touchyng which purpoſe, in the <hi>Decretals</hi> there is extant a decrée of Pope <hi>Lucius</hi> the third the effect whereof is this. Whoſoeuer<note place="margin">A popiſhe decree.</note> thinke otherwiſe of the Sacramentes then the holy Church of <hi>Rome</hi> thinketh and lykewiſe, all whom the Pope ſhall condemne: let them be accoumpted for heretickes, and excomunicate perſons. Ther is added alſo an explication how the ciuill Magiſtrate ſhall procéede a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſutch, which if hée wyll not doe: how they ſhall procéede againſt the diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient Maieſtrate. The thirde booke the ſeuenth Title of Heretickes, Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, <hi>Ad abolendum.</hi> To aboliſh. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Hereunto accorded the counſell, which<note place="margin">Counſelles do conſent.</note> as wée haue before admoniſhed, the Popes had vnder their owne power, for by occaſion of them they haue alwayes kept their conſent and agréement, and all that euer reſiſted the ſame: thoſe haue they oppreſſed, put to flighte, or quight rooted out. For whatſoeuer
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:176431:91"/> were decréed in the counſelles: the ſame muſt be brought to effect, &amp; immediatly put in execution, whereunto all Maieſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trats wer bound, and as many as were able to beare armour.<note place="margin">The ſum of papiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call counſel.</note>
            </p>
            <p>In the yéere of our Lorde, 1215. Pope <hi>Innocentius</hi> the third, held a great coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell in <hi>Lateran</hi> at <hi>Rome:</hi> the manner and forme of the indiction, <hi>Abbas Vr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpurgenſis</hi> hath expreſſed in his Cro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacles, whiche comprehendeth verye many thinges, the cheife ſumme wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of bée theſe. Firſt of making warre vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>Sarracens,</hi> and recouering <hi>Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi> and the holye Sepulcher. The ſecond of rooting out hereſies. The third of mendinge of manners, and refour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming the Church. The ſame Chapters were propounded almoſt in al counſels, which haue bin holden from that time hitherto. They all intreate of thrée poyntes. Of repreſſinge the force of the Turkes, of rooting out of hereſies, and of refourming the Church.</p>
            <p>But although they haue celebrated many Counſels, within the precinct of 300. yéeres and more: yet haue they in
<pb facs="tcp:176431:92"/> none of them refourmed that was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe,<note place="margin">Counſelles</note> wherby it might deſerue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name of a reformation. For errours and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitions with ſundrye abuſes moe, are not taken away but more increaſed mutchleſſe haue they reformed anye whit in the head (as they ſpeake,) or members of the Church. And although the whole world, during the ſpace of cer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ten hundred yéeres haue woorthely ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed the abuſes, and moſt corrupt ſtate of the eccleſiaſticall order, with other e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>normities of the Church, which well de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue to be taken away and mended: Notwithſtandinge they haue not tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched them with their little finger, and therfore oftentimes ariſe ſome greater diſcordes, and they fall farther of from the Chriſtian diſcipline. Yea, &amp; all ſuch as ſéeke for, and require to haue ſome true reformation, reprehending the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orders and abuſes, and ſpecially y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> popes vnlawfull aucthorytie, the filthye, and lecherous lyfe of the Clargye, which all men are conſtrained to confeſſe to bée very culpable: the ſame men neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe are condempned for ſciſmatickes,
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:176431:92"/> and <hi>Hereticks,</hi> &amp; ar ſharply perſecuted.</p>
            <p>For vnto them all are Heretickes:<note place="margin">Whom the Pope cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieks.</note> whoſoeuer do not ſubmit themſelues to the Sea of <hi>Rome,</hi> and the Pope in all thinges, and beléeue in althinges which that Sea beléeueth and commandeth to bée beléeued, accordyng to the aboue na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med conſpiracie: and ſo <hi>Lucius</hi> the pope defineth Heretickes in his <hi>Decretall,</hi> wherof we haue made mention before, in the Chapter <hi>Ad aboliendum,</hi> to abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyſhe. Wherefore with them it is not ſufficient that a godlye man confeſſe all the articles of the antient, true, vndoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and Apoſtolick faith, ſaying: that hée beléeueth in one God, the father &amp;c. that hée alſo alowe, and confeſſe the foure or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of our beléefe ſet foorth by the aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient counſelles, and <hi>S. Athanaſius,</hi> and whatſoeuer are taught and confirmed out of the holy ſcriptures of both Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: &amp; moreouer doo condemne y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies which were conuicted &amp; condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> antient counſels. In ould time this kinde of confeſſion was ſufficient e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough for chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s in y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> auntient church but amongſt theſe men all theſe things aveile nothinge, neither ſuffice to the
<pb facs="tcp:176431:93"/> confeſſion of the faith, but a man muſte néedes confeſſe and beleue in the church of <hi>Rome</hi> as it is now vnder the Pope, and follow the conſent thereof: or elſe he ſhall léeſe honour, goodes, bodie, lyfe and all.</p>
            <p>And therefore during the time of the<note place="margin">Counſelles cauſe wars. and perſecu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tions.</note> Counſels, before, and after them, haue bin many bateiles, murthers, and foule waſtings committed, nether were theſe things done onely againſt the <hi>Sarracens</hi> and vnfaithfull men: but with mutche more extreamitie and crueltie againſt Chriſtians, which would bée indéed, and named Chriſtians, and not papiſts, and which diſallowed and alſo be wayled the pride, and tyrany of the Pope, his great and manifeſt abuſes and deprauations of holy thinges. Wherefore in the ould time it grewe into a prouerbe: <hi>Euery counſell breedeth warre:</hi> which is to be vnderſtoode of Papiſticall counſels, and found indéed to be true by proofe.</p>
            <p>For that I may paſſe ouer in this place, warres and moſte bloody perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of faithfull men, but enemies to the Sea of <hi>Rome,</hi> whiche were waged
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:176431:93"/> and committed in the reigne of Pope <hi>Innocentius</hi> the thirde and certen other Popes next enſuing: let vs onli examin thoſe thinges which are not farre paſt the memory of men that are aliue. The<note place="margin">The coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance.</hi>
               </note> counſel of Conſtance, I pray you, what warres, perſecutions, burninges, waſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyngs, and murthers purchaſed it vnto <hi>Boheme, &amp; Germanie?</hi> He that know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not this: let him learne it at leaſt wiſe out of Pope <hi>Pius</hi> the ſeconde, who when he was called as yet <hi>Aeneas Sylui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> wroat theſe thinges very dilligently in his ſtorye of <hi>Boheme.</hi> The troubles, ſeditions, &amp; ſlaughters, which the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel of <hi>Baſile</hi> brought forth are in part re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited<note place="margin">The Coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſell of <hi>Baſile.</hi>
               </note> by <hi>Platina</hi> in the life of <hi>Eugenius</hi> the fourth. But béeſids this, we haue a more freſh and certeine example of the <hi>Tridentine</hi> Counſel, which beeing firſt appoynted at <hi>Mantua,</hi> and afterwarde at <hi>Vincentia:</hi> was at the laſt by <hi>Paule</hi> the thirde in the yeare of our Lord. 1542 called at <hi>Trident</hi> nigh <hi>Atheſis,</hi> wholy in manner and fourme as we haue bée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore recited, whiche was conluded and<note place="margin">The <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent</hi> counſel</note> ended by Pope <hi>Pius</hi> the fourth in the
<pb facs="tcp:176431:94"/> yéere of our Lorde. 1563.</p>
            <p>Howbeit, what thinges were doone<note place="margin">Perſecurti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of our time.</note> certen yéeres before this counſel, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo ſince, againſt holie and faithfull men, which only beleeued in the Goſpell, but not in traditions of Popes nor in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſea of <hi>Rome,</hi> by <hi>Leo. x. Cleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. 7. Paul. 3.</hi> and<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 4. <hi>Iulius,</hi> the 3. <hi>Pius,</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>. 4. and. 5. and by this preſent Pope <hi>Gregorye</hi> the. 13. the ſpace of. 53. yéeres: I néede not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peat. For they are knowen vnto God and al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world, and as it were writen in heauen, vnto which place y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> blood of all innocents together with the blood of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel:</hi> crieth from the earth vnto God for vengeance. Many gréeuous, longe, and bloodye warres for ſundry cauſes were waged in thoſe yéeres, but at the ſame time no leſſe gréeuous and bloody perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutions wer committed againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full: for faith, and religions ſake. Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and Godly men were reprochefully and iniuriouſly dealt withal, apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, thrown out of dores, driuen into ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ile, ſpoyled of their goods, beheaded, han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged on gallowes, burned, vexed with al kindes of tormentes, and puniſhment.
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:176431:94"/> And by this meanes were oppreſſed tormented, &amp; ſlayne, hundred thouſands, of faithfull men and profeſſours of the Goſpell both in the higher, and lower <hi>Germanie,</hi> in <hi>Scotla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, England, Spaine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Note.</note> (which found out the new practize of the inquiſition) in <hi>Italie,</hi> and other regions. But cheiflye what hath bin doone in <hi>France:</hi> ther is no man at this day but knoweth. And there are extant whole bookes written of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gréeuous, and long Papiſticall perſecution, and the thinge doone is yet freſh in memory, wherfore it is not néedefull that I ſhould ſpecially declare it againe at large, ſince yet at this preſent they make no end of their crueltie, and ſheding of blood. Since ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore, thei which would ſéeme to be Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and paſtours of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church, do make themſelues executioners of this laſt pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſticall perſecution: wée may not only compare it w<hi rend="sup">e</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> olde perſecutions, but in reſpect of the greatnes prefer it aboue it.</p>
            <p>Moreouer, as in auntient times the ould perſecutors of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church were egged forwarde to rigour through an vnſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able deſire to rule, to th' intent they might kéepe and increaſe their dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie,
<pb facs="tcp:176431:95"/> pleaſures, ritches, and ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition: ſo likewiſe is the Papiſticall perſecution committed for the ſame cauſe. But like as the Chriſtian faith in the ould time was no whit the leſſe eſtéemed of for the perſecutions: ſo at this preſent the Euangelicall doctrine is nothinge the woorſe nor viler, bicauſe the Papiſts do perſecute the profeſſours of the Goſpell, and manie times ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come them. There are ſundrie cauſes, why God ſuffreth this to bée doone, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ought any man to accuſe, or call the iudgment of God into queſtion.</p>
            <p>And this mutch I had to ſaye of the perſecutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s which the Church of Chriſt hath ſuffred from the birth of our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our vnto our time: comprehendinge breefely the whole ſumme, wherby the matter beeing otherwiſe verie large: might ſeeme ouerlonge, and tedious to the reader. Howbeit, much more might and oughte to haue bin written of thys manifold, and ample argument.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="17" type="chapter">
            <pb n="113" facs="tcp:176431:95"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Of the Sundry cauſes,</hi> why God ſuffreth the <hi>Chriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian Church to be torne with Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantes</hi> and afflicted with per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutions. <hi>Chapter. xvii.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>HEerafter I intende to declare, the cauſes and effectes of the aboue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited perſecutions of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> chriſtian church, which doo worke in the faithfull, And although I haue already almoſt in eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one, ſhewed them: notwithſtandyng ther remaine ſome more ſpeciall, which are of vs with more diligence to bée con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered.</p>
            <p>Perſecutions are ſent to the Churche by the iuſt iudgment of god, as the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture plainely witneſſeth were ſent vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Iob</hi> the hollie man, and Seruant of<note place="margin">Iob.</note> God: the Croſſe, affliction, and perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from God. Vnto which purpoſe, God vſed Satan as an inſtrument, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribing him bonds how farre he ſhould perſecute <hi>Iob.</hi> And Satan through his malice ſtirred vp the rauenous and gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die
<pb facs="tcp:176431:96" rendition="simple:additions"/> people of the <hi>Chaldees,</hi> to breake in vpon <hi>Iobs</hi> goodes, to ſpoile him, and bringe him to pouertie. Then <hi>Iob,</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though hée vnderſtood y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>through the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtigation of <hi>Satan,</hi> hée was in ſutch ſort endamaged by wicked, and rauenous men: notwithſtandinge hée tooke regard vnto the principall cauſe of perſecution, and hée ſaide not as the maner is now a daies, that hée was ſore afflicted by <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan,</hi> and maliciouſlye ſpoiled by the <hi>Chaldees:</hi> but, ſaid hée, the Lorde hath giuen and the Lord hath taken away, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> name of the Lorde bée bleſſed for euer.</p>
            <p>Likewiſe, the ſcripture in the ſame<note place="margin">Captiuitie of Babilon</note> ſignification, calleth <hi>Nabuchodonoſor</hi> the ſeruaunt of God, which perſecuted his people, and lead them captiue into Babilon, for ſo it is write<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the ſecond booke of <hi>Paralipomenon,</hi> the laſt Chap. wherfore God ſent his Prophetes vnto them, exhorting the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to repent, but they mocked at them. And therfore the lorde béeinge diſpleaſed with them: brought vpon them the king of <hi>Chaldees</hi> (which was <hi>Nabuchodonoſor</hi>) and diliuered then into his hands. Likewiſe in <hi>Daniel</hi>
               <pb n="114" facs="tcp:176431:96"/> the. 9. &amp; y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> Lorde watched for a ſhrewd turne, and hath brought it vpon vs: Our Lord God is iuſt in all his woorkes, which hée hath doone. And although they were the <hi>Chaldees</hi> which lead away the people of God into hard, and ſharpe cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuitie: notwithſtandinge the Prophets of God, <hi>Ieremie, Ezechiel, Daniel,</hi> with many other hollie men, which ſawe, and felt theſe thinges: choſe rather with <hi>Iob</hi> to aſcribe their affliction &amp; perſecution vnto God and his iuſtice, then vnto the vnbéeléeuing and wicked men. So like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe at this day, the faithfull had rather to ſuppoſe, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> they abide their afflictions at the handes of God: then of men. For they know, that men can do nothing vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe God permitt them. And in that he permitteth them: againe thereby they know &amp; béeléeue y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> all thinges are done, &amp; ſuffred by him to bée doone: by his iuſt iudgment, and for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> profit of his people.</p>
            <p>Wherfore, by all theſe thinges we mai<note place="margin">The godly ſuffer perſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cution.</note> vnderſtand, that the croſſe, afflictions, &amp; perſecutions ar ſent fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God, &amp; laid alſo vpon holy and Godly men. And as tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching <hi>Iob:</hi> God himſelf bereth witnes:
<pb facs="tcp:176431:97"/> that hée was a ſingle and righteous man, fearing God, and eſchewing euell whoſe like was not vpon the earthe. Moreouer, all men acknowledge and confeſſe, that the Prophetes, <hi>Iohn</hi> the Baptiſte, and the Apoſtles: were holly men, and the ſeruantes of God, and yet notw<hi rend="sup">t</hi>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding they al ſuffred perſecutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Beſides this, S. <hi>Peter</hi> writeth: that Chriſtians ſhould not ſuffer as théeues, or malefactours: but only for God, and the truethes cauſe. The firſt epiſtle of Peter, the. 4. chapter.</p>
            <p>Secondly, God ſendeth perſecution vnto ſutch, as ought to bée the people of God, and partly alſo are indéede, and ſo are named: but are not ſo innocent, pure, and holly, as of duetie they ſhould bée, as wée ſayd erewhile of the people of God, which were lead away into <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon:</hi> And <hi>Cyprian</hi> teſtifieth, that the cauſe of the perſecution at his time vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Emperour <hi>Decius:</hi> was the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute life of the faithfull. <hi>Euſebius</hi> ſheweth the like cauſes, where hée de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribeth the perſecution of <hi>Dioclecian.</hi> And it is ſéene, that booth giltie and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giltie,
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:176431:97"/> good and bad, altogither are ſubiect to the croſſe. I call vngiltie, thoſe whiche béeynge vnlike to the children of this worlde: are not defiled with all kynde of wickedneſſe, neuertheleſſe haue their imperfections, and as it were, certein moales and ſtaynyngs. Wherefore, they confeſſe their faultes and defectes vnto God, and glorie nothyng of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues. Accordyng vnto which ſence and opinion, <hi>Iob</hi> ſayth: <hi>Surely I know it is true, that no man is iuſt if hee be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to God. If hee will ſtriue with him: hee is not able to aunſwere him vnto one for a thouſand. And althogh I haue doone ſome iuſt deede: yet will I not anſwere, but intreate my iudge.</hi> And <hi>Dauid</hi> in the. 142. Pſalme ſaith: <hi>Enter not into iudgment with thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant O Lorde, for there ſhall no liuing creature bee iuſtified in thy ſight.</hi> Wherfore, thoſe which bée giltleſſe, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they bée ſubiect to perſecution with the moſt wicked men: notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandinge they murmur not againſt y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> Lorde, but accordinge to the ſcriptures they confeſſe and ſay: <hi>Thy iudgements
<pb facs="tcp:176431:98"/> are iuſt, O Lorde, and all thy waies are trueth, and holineſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, perſecutions are ſent from god vnto the Church, to declare his glorie, and Maieſtie. For when the Diſciples vpon a time, had enquired of the Lorde touching the man that was borne blind, whether hée or his parentes had deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the ſame by their offences: the lorde anſwered them, as appéereth in Iohn the ix. chapter, that this was doone, that the glory of God might bée declared in him. The like alſo hée ſaid of the ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of his frend <hi>Lazarus,</hi> in Iohn the 12. that the infirmitie was not vnto death: but ſent to the glorye of God, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſun of God might bée glorified therby. For in perſecutions, the power of God is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared wherby hée preſerueth his in the midſt of afflictions, and when hée ſéeth time, deliuereth them with great glory, as it is euidently expreſſed in the ſtories of <hi>Daniell, Heſter,</hi> and <hi>Eſdras.</hi> Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, it is writen by Saint <hi>Paule:</hi> wée haue the treaſure of the Goſpell in ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then veſſelles, that the excellencie of the power therof may be Gods, and not our
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:176431:98"/> owne, while in althinges wée ar preſſed but not wronge: we are in trouble but wée do not want, wée ſuffer perſecution but wée are not therin forſaken, caſte downe, nor periſhe. wée carie the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification of our Lorde Ieſus Chriſte a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout with vs in our body, to the intente that the lyfe which commeth by Ieſus Chriſte: may bée made manifeſt in our body, the .ii. to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> the. 4. Chapter. For which cauſe, the ſame Apoſtle writeth how it was ſaid vnto him by the Lorde: my grace is ſufficient for thée, for my ſtrength is made perfect through weakneſſe, the 2. to the <hi>Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thias,</hi> the xii. chapter.<note place="margin">The trueth is knowen by perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</note>
            </p>
            <p>There is alſo another cauſe of perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutions, for that it pleaſeth God through them to reueale the trueth vnto men: namely, when the faithfull béeing appre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>hended in perſecutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, and brought into iudgment: do plainly and openly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe the Goſpell. And our ſauiour chriſt ſaith: you ſhalbée brought béefore Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenantes and kinges for my ſake, that this may bée a teſtimonie to them, and the Gentiles. <hi>Mathew</hi> the x. Chapter.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:176431:99"/>
            <p>Moreouer, by perſecutions whiche God layeth vpon the Church: hée proo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth the ſame how ſtrong and conſtant it is, purgynge thoſe that are vncleane, like as Goldſmithes vſe to trie &amp; clenſe their golde, and ſiluer in the fier. For if the fleaſh continue in reſt and idleneſſe, féelyng no maner of aduerſitie, oftenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes it waxeth wanton, and laſciuious: wherfore God exerciſeth his ſeruantes with perſecutions, to awake them that they ſhould not to mutch be wedded vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to temporall thinges, but with more er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt deſier ſéeke for thynges eternall. Vnto which purpoſe and meanyng S. Peter writeth: <hi>Deerely beloued, bee yee not troubled in this heat, whiche now is come among you to trie you, as though ſome ſtraunge thyng had hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vnto you: but rather reioyce, in as mutch as you are made partakers of Chriſtes paſsions, that when his glory appereth: yee may be mery and glad.</hi> Peter the firſt Epiſtle, the. 4. chapter. Wherunto alſo tende the wordes of the Apoſtle S. Paule: <hi>We reioyce alſo in tribulations, knowyng that tribulation
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:176431:99"/> bringeth pacience, pacience bringeth experience, experience bringeth hope and hope maketh not aſhamed.</hi> Paule to the <hi>Romans,</hi> the. 5. chapter.</p>
            <p>Agayne, when the Lorde layeth the<note place="margin">Perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens of the iudgment of God vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the wicked.</note> Croſſe vpon thoſe whom hée loueth, and ſuffereth men which are not altogether wicked to bée afflicted, but ſutch as feare God and ſerue him, although notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandynge they haue ſome blemiſhes: therwithall hée ſheweth what wicked men, &amp; the children of this worlde muſt looke for. Like as the Lord himſelf wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſeth, who bearyng his owne Croſſe when hée was lead to execution, ſayed: <hi>It it be thus in the greene tree that bea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>reth frute: what ſhall bee in the drye and vnfrutfull? And Saint Peter: For</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Peter. 4.</note> 
               <hi>it is time</hi> (ſaith hée) <hi>that iudgment be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin at the houſe of god:</hi> then if it begin firſt with vs: what ſhalbée the ende of thoſe y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> obey not the goſpel of God? And if the iuſt bée ſcarce faued: where ſhall the wicked &amp; ſinful man ſhew his face?</p>
            <p>By perſecutions alſo God draweth vnto him, and directeth in the right way thoſe which before that time walked not
<pb facs="tcp:176431:100"/> ſtrait in the waies of the Lord. And hée complaineth by his prophetes, and bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth his people, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> being put in mind of their duty with many ſtripes, yet wold they not turne vnto him.</p>
            <p>Moreouer, in perſecutions &amp; afflictions, there is geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto vs matter &amp; occaſion of trouble, that we may bring foorth good works w<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pacie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, &amp; w<hi rend="sup">e</hi> a good hope, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> we may cal vpon god in our paſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, &amp; neuer waxe wery w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> calling: like as the Lord. Ieſus hath manifeſtlye taught vs in <hi>Luke</hi> the. 18 chap. And in very déed we finde this dayly to be true, that wée are ſlouthfull and cold in prayer: when wée are gréeued with no perſecution, nor<note place="margin">Perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons awake vs.</note> touched almoſt w<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ani kind of aduerſity.</p>
            <p>Laſt of all, God exerciſeth the faithful with perſecutions, ſwiping from them, as it were, the duſt of worldly deſire or fleſhly luſts, that they ſhould not periſh in their ſins, w<hi rend="sup">e</hi> the wicked worlde. For it is ſure, and true, which S. <hi>Paul</hi> wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth: <hi>But whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we ar iudged of the lord: we are chaſtined that we should not be damned with the world. 1. Cor. ca. 11.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now when we be thus inſtructed: we
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:176431:100"/> muſt humble and ſubmit our ſelues vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the mightye hande of the Lord, who when he ſeeth his time, can deliuer vs againe, when it ſhall ſéeme conuenient vnto his good pleſure. Wherof we haue an example in <hi>Dauid,</hi> who whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he was perſecuted by his owne ſun <hi>Abſolon,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong other thinges he ſaide: <hi>If I haue found fauour in the ſight of the Lord: he will reſtore mee. But if he ſay vnto me, I haue no delight in thee: Behould I am here, let him doe vnto mee that which is acceptable in his ſight.</hi> The ſame Sainct <hi>Peter</hi> willeth al men to do which ſuffer perſecution, writing thus: <hi>VVherfore, let al them that ſuffer af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions, according to the will of God, commit their ſoules to him with well doyng, as vnto a faithfull creator.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe cauſes, and effectes of the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutions<note place="margin">1. Pet. 4.</note> of the Chriſtian Churche, I haue bréefly choſen out amongſt many, leſt that the ſtore and ouer long reciting of them at large: ſhould be gréeuous vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to any.</p>
            <trailer>The End</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
